in this comprehensive and
beginner-friendly course you'll learn
all the tools that you need to become an
advanced objectoriented programmer
writing clean code and maintainable
software you'll learn fundamental oop
Concepts the solid principles all 23
gang of four software design patterns
and more experience developer Danny
Adams created this course welcome to
mastering design patterns and solid
principles in cop so let me first give
you a quick introduction on what you
will learn in this course and what you
need to know before getting
started so the aim of this course is to
teach you how to design maintainable and
reusable object oriented software and
this is achieved first of all by
learning the objectoriented programming
principles such as encapsulation
abstraction inheritance polymorphism and
coupling you'll also learn the five
solid principles which are the single
responsibility principle the open closed
principle the list off substitution
principle the interface agregation
principle and the dependency inversion
principle you'll also learn unified
modeling language which is a way to
graphically represent your software
systems so you can model classes and
objects and the relationships between
those classes and objects in a graphical
way and you can do this before you
actually code out a solution and you'll
also learn the main 23 design patterns
from the gang of four book The Gang of
four design patterns consists of 23
design patterns from the original book
design patterns elements of reusable
objectoriented software written by four
guys in the 1990s and these patterns can
be grouped into three categories so
there are creational design patterns
which are the different ways to create
objects there are structural design
patterns which are the relationships
between those objects and there are
behavioral design patterns which are the
interaction or communication between
those objects so upon completion of this
course you will understand all 23 ganga
4 design patterns and where to and where
not to apply them in real applications
and you'll also learn the solid
principles and some more advanced
objectoriented programming Concepts and
these are all of the 23 design patterns
from the gang of four book that we will
be covering in this course so you can
see that there are five creational
design patterns seven structural design
patterns and 11 behavioral design
patterns so what are design patterns and
why should you learn them so design
patterns are essential in software
development for several reasons and
first of all they help to promote and
provide proven solutions to recurring
problems in software design so instead
of Reinventing the wheel developers can
Leverage The these patterns to solve
common issues efficiently for example to
implement an undo feature in an
application developers could reach for
the momento design pattern design
patterns establish a common language for
developers to communicate efficiently
and effectively about software designs
and this common vocabulary enhances
collaboration and understanding among
team
members design patterns also promote
scalable designs by providing flexible
and AD aable solutions they allow
systems to evolve over time without
extensive rework or architectural
overhaul and using design patterns often
results in more maintainable code AS
patterns encapsulate design decisions
and promote modular Loosely coupled
architectures making it easier to
understand modify and extend code bases
and some design patterns can help to
improve performance by optimizing
resource usage producing overhead or
facilitating efficient
algorithms design patterns serve as a
form of documentation for software
designs so by employing well-known
patterns developers can convey design
intent more effectively making code
bases easier to understand for both
current and future
contributors design patterns embody best
practices and principles of software
design they encapsulate years of
collective knowledge and experience
guiding developers towards uh solutions
that are more robust reliable and
maintainable and many design patterns
are agnostic of programming languages or
domains so they can be used across
different programming languages
essentially and they can they can be
applied across different Technologies
and IND Industries making them valuable
tools for developers working in diverse
environments so overall design patterns
fa itate the creation of highquality
maintainable software systems by
providing reusable solutions to Common
design problems and promoting best
practices in software development and
just as a note don't worry too much if
you don't quite understand everything
I've said so far and as everything will
become much more clear as we Implement
and discuss each of the design patterns
and objectoriented programming
principles during the course for example
many of you right now won't understand
the difference between extending a code
base versus modifying a code base and
all of these things will be revealed
during the course so here are some
things that you should understand before
starting this course so this course is
for developers that have at least a very
basic knowledge of objectoriented
programming and want to learn design
patterns to become better more complete
developers so here are some things that
you should understand before starting
this course so you should understand
what classes are you should understand
how to create objects from
classes access modifiers such as public
private and
protected class Properties or fields and
class methods so as you can see you just
need to understand the very basics of
objectoriented programming to find Value
in this course any other objectoriented
programming Concepts such as abstract
classes polymorphism and capsulation
will be fully explained in the course
and of course you will learn the very
important objectoriented programming
solid principles so all the examples in
this course are in CP so it will be
helpful if you understand understood the
basic syntax of C as I won't be
explaining the basic syntax however
there are plenty of free and great
videos on YouTube to help you get
started with C in very little time so a
little bit about me I am currently a
freelance software developer that builds
full stack web applications Shopify apps
mobile apps WordPress plugins and themes
and I'm also a technical writer that
enjoys writing technical blog posts
books and making videos and courses so
here are some links where you can find
me so I have a YouTube channel uh I have
a Twitter account I sell some products
such as posters and PDFs on
gumroad uh I have a free code Camp blog
where I write posts for free code camp
and I also have a Blog on dev 2 there is
also a full book version of this course
available and it includes everything
that is covered in this video course and
having the book can help to make
revision of these topics much easier as
you can quickly look up certain topics
principles and Concepts skim through and
remind yourself of what we covered in
this video helping these topics to stick
in your head and if you're a heavy
notetaker like me then it will also save
you a lot of time as everything we cover
in this video will be written down here
for you so if this book sounds like it
would be helpful to you to better learn
these Concepts then you can get the book
from Amazon in Kindle ebook and physical
print format and there's also a pdf
version available from gumroad and there
should be links to those down in the
description
below so for every design pattern or
solid principle or object oriented
programming principle that we cover in
this course we will go over an example
or two and usually each example will
include a bad example which violates a
certain principle and then we have a
good example where we usually refactor
the bad example to satisfy the principle
that we are covering and all code
examples for this course can be found at
this GitHub
repo okay so I'm now going to show you
how you can set up your computer so that
you can follow along with the examples
in this course so this course is all in
C so we need to set set up a sort of CP
environment so for me I'm going to use
Visual Studio code as the text editor
and I've provided a link to a guide here
to get you started and set up so let's
have a look at this guide so if you
click this link it will take you through
to this getting started with C in vs
code guide and it tells you everything
that you need to download and then
everything that you need to do to create
a new C application or project so first
of all you need to download Visual
Studio code if you don't already have it
so you can download it
here um and then you need to download
the cop devkit extension for vs code so
you can download that by clicking this
link and you can install the C devkit
extension you can also do it from vs
code directly so if you come into the
extensions uh sort of tab and then you
can search for C devkit and then you can
install I've already got it installed so
I don't need to do that and the next
thing you need to do is to download the
net software development kit and you can
download that from Microsoft so you can
download that here so that's everything
that you should need to get started uh
developing with
C so once you've done that you can then
create a new C application so if we come
into Visual Studio code here we've just
got a blank uh you know no folders open
so what we can do is let's create a new
C project using the extension the C
devit extension that we installed
earlier so you can press shift command P
to open up the command pallet and then
we can see we have some options here so
you can type in net uh co1 and then new
project and you can see you can click
net new project and then we want to
select console app because we're going
to create a very simple console app for
all of our examples in this course and
that's just an app where we can
basically log things to the console so
select console app and then you need
somewhere to actually store this project
so I'm just going to store it on my
desktop for now so I'm going to open
that and then I need to name the project
I'm just going to call it test because
I've already created the actual project
that we're going to use uh you can call
this something like um design patterns
in C uh tutorials or course or something
like that whatever you want and then we
just click create
project and you can see it's created
this project in my desktop folder so if
we come to the file explorer now and we
go into our program.cs file we can see
that we have console. right line hello
world and we can just run this file or
this application and we can see that we
get hello world logged to the console so
that is how you set up with Visual
Studio code for net and this is how I
will be uh doing all of the examples in
this course but just as a note feel free
to use whatever text editor or setup
that you want if you already have
something set up for
C before we start learning any design
patterns it's important that you
understand some fundamental
objectoriented programming principles so
here are some Concepts that you'll
understand by completing this next
section of the course so you will
understand encapsulation abstraction
inheritance polymorphism coupling and
composition so let's get started so the
first objectoriented programming
principle that we're going to take a
look at is encapsulation which is a
fundamental principle of objectoriented
programming that involves bundling the
data or attributes or fields and the
methods or behaviors that operate on
that data into to a single unit called a
class and encapsulation helps in hiding
the internal implementation details of a
class by only exposing the necessary
functionalities to the outside world so
if that doesn't make too much sense
don't worry because we're now going to
go through a simple example
demonstrating encapsulation and we'll
first go through a bad example with no
encapsulation and then we'll refactor
that example to use encapsulation so
first of all we're going to create a new
class called bad bank
account and this is going to have a
single field uh called balance and this
is a public
field and then inside of our program.cs
field so this is going to be a Class A
program class is going to use or be a
client of this bad bank account class so
we're going to say bad bank account
and we'll call this bad account equals
new bad bank account and we're going to
set the balance uh equal to 100 so
initially the balance is going to be 100
and let's just log that to the console
and let's run our program to make sure
everything's working correctly and we
can see we get 100 logged to the console
so the issue with this solution is that
because this is a public Fe Feld all
clients or so all classes that use this
class can just directly uh change this
balance field to whatever value they
want so if I change this to minus 50 and
then run the program we should get no
issues okay now this is actually a
problem because let's just say that in
our program Bank uh bank accounts should
not uh balances should not allowed to be
should not be allowed to be negative
okay so this is actually violating our
program's logic so in all of our clients
because we can just directly access this
field in all of our clients we then have
to provide some sort of uh conditional
statement so we'd have to say like if
the uh the amount that we want to set
the balance to is negative then we can
maybe throw some error or you know
display the user some issue and we
wouldn't want to have to do this inside
of every single client that uses bad
bank accounts okay so you can see that
we have some issues here because we can
set this to whatever we want because
this is public so let's now use
encapsulation to solve this problem so
let's create a bank account
class and we're actually now going to
make the balance field
private so that it can't be accessed
outside of this
class uh so let's actually create a
Constructor now so that we can set the
initial balance of the bank account and
we'll say decimal balance and what we're
going to do is we're going to provide a
method now called deposit and then we
can set the balance in here okay so
let's create a method called
deposit and we pass this an amount that
we want to deposit and then here what we
can do is we can check that if the
amount that we're trying to deposit is
negative then we can throw an error
because it doesn't make any sense to
deposit a negative amount of money you
don't deposit minus $50 into a bank
account you only deposit positive
numbers so we can say if amount is less
than or equal to zero then we're going
to throw a new argument
exception and we will say that deposit
amount must be posit positive so deposit
amount must be
positive okay so that is preventing now
users of this class from depositing
negative amounts of money and that
actually solves our issue of whenever of
actually having a negative balance
because we now can't have a negative
balance when we deposit money okay so
what we can do now is just add the
amount onto the balance so we can say
balance this. balance plus equals the
amount so let's also create create a
method for withdrawing money from the
bank account so currently we can deposit
money but we also need to get money from
the account so let's create a withdraw
method so we can say public void
withdraw and then we need to provide an
amount that we want to
withdraw now again we need to make sure
that balance can't be negative and so we
need to make sure we don't try to
withdraw uh an amount greater than our
balance so first of all we can check if
the amount is less than zero so we can't
withdraw a negative amount because that
doesn't make any sense so we're going to
say if amount is less than or equal to
zero uh then we're going to throw a new
argument
exception and we'll say withdrawal
amount must be positive so we'll say
with drawal amount must be
positive okay and we also need to check
to see if the amount that we're trying
to withdraw is greater than the amount
that we have in the account because that
shouldn't be possible so we're going to
say if amount is greater than the
balance then we can throw invalid
operation
exception and we can say insufficient
funds
insufficient funds
okay otherwise if we get down to here
then we can just subtract the amount
from the balance so we can say this do
balance minus equals the
amount okay and it would also be nice to
uh for the user to be able to actually
see what their balance is so let's
provide a geta method so a geta method
is just a method that essentially allows
the user to see a private the value of a
private field so we can say public uh
decimal and then by convention what you
do is you just basically prefix get onto
the name of the field that we're trying
to get so we say get balance and we're
just going to return the balance okay so
now let's take a look at how we would
use this new bank account class where we
have
encapsulated the logic and the fields
within this class and not made them
available publicly to all users of this
class so we're going to first of all
let's just remove everything from in
here and we're going to say bank
account and bank account equals new bank
account and we need to provide an
initial amount so we'll say 100 okay and
let's actually log the balance to make
sure that that has worked correctly so
we can get balance
and let's deposit uh an amount so let's
just say uh bank account.
deposit and we'll deposit say uh
$50 and we'll log the balance
there so let's put that up there and
then let's actually withdraw some money
so withdraw let's withdraw 100 and then
log to the console
the balance so that should be bank
account okay so let's make sure that
this is all working correctly so
initially the balance should be 100 so
we can see here that's correct then we
deposit 50 so we now have 150 then we
take out 100 and we now have 50 so let's
check if we actually try to initialize
the account with a negative amount of
money so we should get an exception
thrown it shouldn't allow us to do that
and as you can see we get an exception
the deposit amount must be positive so
that's working correctly what if we try
to withdraw more than we have in the
account so here we have 150 in the
account let's try to withdraw
$200 and we should get an exception
because we're trying to withdraw more
than we have in the account and the
withdrawal amount must be positive so
you can see here we're trying to
withdraw a negative amount I wanted to
actually withdraw a positive amount
there so let's just check that and it
says it
it tells us that we have insufficient
funds so that is all working perfectly
so in this example the bank account
class
encapsulates the account data so the
balance um and all the related methods
so deposit and withdraw into a single
unit this bank account class is the sort
of single unit and the data members the
balance are marked as private uh
encapsulating them within the class and
preventing direct access from outside of
the class and geta methods so get
balance are used to provide controlled
access to the private data member the
balance class uh field in this case and
methods deposit and withdraw are used to
um manipulate balance ensuring that
operations are performed safely and
according to the business rules so we
can see here we have checks to make sure
that nothing
uh incorrect so the sort of program
logic can't actually be violated from
outside of the class and the main method
or inside of this program.cs file we are
demonstrating how to create an instance
of bank account and interact with its
properties and methods without needing
to know the internal implementation
details so we can see that the user or
so this program uh class here the user
of B the bank account class
uh can't directly access the balance
field as it's marked as private so the
data is encapsulated within the class
and methods dictate the rules for how
this data is can be accessed and
modified ensuring that our programs
correct rules and logic can't be
violated by users or consumers of the
bank account class for example it's no
longer possible to withdraw more money
than is in the account and encapsulation
of logic inside of the methods in bank
accounts also means that users don't
need to worry about uh the
implementation details when we're
interacting with a bank account object
for example the user doesn't have to
worry about the logic involved in
withdrawing
money um they can just call uh the
withdraw method and the implementation
details of withdrawing money are hidden
from the client and encapsulated and if
the user tries to do something stupid
like deposit a negative amount of money
then the program will throw an error and
the user will be notified and
encapsulation of logic within methods in
bank account allows users to interact
with bank account object without needing
to know or understand the internal
implementation details of how
withdrawals or
deposits or other operations are carried
out users of the bank account class can
interact with it using simple intuitive
methods like we draw and deposit without
needing to understand the complex logic
behind these operations so encapsulation
abstracts away the complexity of the
implementation details allowing users to
focus on the higher level functionality
provided by the bank account class so
users only need to know the public
interface of the bank account class in
other words the public methods or
properties to use it effectively while
the internal implementation details
remain hidden so in summary
encapsulation allows for a clear
separation between the public interface
and the internal implementation of a
class providing users with a simplified
and intuitive way to interact with
objects while hiding the complexity of
those of how those interactions are
handled
internally abstraction is an
objectoriented programming principle
that is used to reduce complexity by
hiding the unnecessary details of a
class to a user of that class so a good
example of this is the when you press a
button on a TV remote you don't have to
worry about or interact directly with
the internal circuit board so for
example within a remote there will be
electrical impulses firing through a
circuit board and then some
electromagnetic waves will uh come out
of the remote and be received by the
television but you don't really need to
understand any of that or you if you
want to change channel to channel 2
you just have to press uh the two and
it'll change directly it'll change to
channel two and you don't have to worry
about any of the complex uh details of
how that happened uh all those details
are abstracted away so I've created an
email service class here to
demonstrate uh abstraction So currently
this class has no abstraction really uh
we are we have just a load of public
methods that are available to any user
of this email email service class so if
we want to send an
email um we create an email service
object and then we have to connect to
the email server authenticate send the
email then we have the user has to
remember to also disconnect from the
server once the email has been sent or
once we've finished um you know sending
any emails or doing what we're doing
with this email service
class so the issue of this solution is
that all users of this class have to
follow all of these steps in a specific
order and um for example if any uh if we
add another uh method to the email
service class such as uh log some
information um then all of the users of
this class would then have to add an
extra step such as log okay and we
couldn't just change uh this in one
place we would have to edit all of our
classes that were sending an
email so a better solution uh to this
would be to make uh these methods
private and only expose one method to
users of this class and that would be
the send email uh
method so what we can do here is we can
call all the methods all the the steps
that are involved in sending an email we
can call them in the send email uh
method and then we can see we have an
error now because these uh methods are
no longer available they are now private
methods so we only now have to call the
send mail uh method so if I just show
you this you can see that the only
method available now is send
email and if we run the
program we get the exact same thing as
we got before but now users of the email
service class um now don't have to worry
about the internal implementation
details involved in sending an email all
the complexity has been abstracted away
and encapsulated within this email
service uh
class so now the user can send emails
without having to know any of the
details or any of the
complexity uh and without ex scash uh
without abstraction you can you saw that
the user had more decisions to make
because whenever we looked at the
methods on this email service object
there was uh you know three more methods
to choose from whe it was connect
authenticate or disconnect and so the
user then has more decisions to make
whereas this it's very simple we can
just call send email it's very obvious
how to send an email so without
abstraction the user needs to know more
information and understand the internal
logic involved in sending an email and
importantly if any of those private
methods are changed EG uh for example
they take another parameter so let's say
uh when connecting we added um another
parameter such as uh I don't know a URL
to an email
server
then all classes using the email service
would then have to
change uh they would all have to add
this extra parameter and all those
classes would have to be modified and
you risk adding bugs into previously
working code whereas of this um with
this solution where these methods are
all kept um abstracted
away uh we could just add the uh
parameter to one method we would only
have to change the send email and say
connect method inheritance involves
creating new classes based on existing
classes so uh the new classes that we
create are often called subclasses or
derived classes and they are based on
the existing classes which are known as
super classes or base classes so a
subass inherits properties and behaviors
from their super class and can also add
new features or override existing ones
inheritance is often described in terms
of an is a relationship for example we
may have a shape class which could be a
base class or a super class and a shape
class could have uh subclasses which
inherit from shape so uh and that
relationship would be
represented uh by inheritance pretty
good because a a uh for example a circle
is a shape okay so shape could um
inherit
uh sorry a circle could inherit a shape
so here's an example where uh a a car or
a bike class can inherit from a parent
vehicle class so we have a vehicle class
here which has some properties some C
Properties for the brand of the vehicle
the model of the vehicle the year of the
vehicle and some methods that can start
or stop the vehicle so all vehicles um
whether they are cars bikes planes or
boats will have all of the these kinds
of
information so what we could do is
create a car class and have all of these
properties and methods in car class uh
so we could literally copy and paste
them all in here like so and then we
also have a bite class and we could have
again repeat everything and have the
brand model your start stop methods all
within bike but we're going to have to
repeat ourselves a lot with this this
and if for example vehicles um we need
some extra functionality for a
vehicle um that all vehicles have then
every single vehicle we would have to
add a new method and also if we changed
for example the way we start a vehicle
then we would have to change that method
in all of the vehicle classes rather
than just in one place so what we can do
is we can use inheritance we can see
here that car is inheriting vehicle so
the way that you uh inherit a class in
CP is by using this colon so car
inherits
vehicle and we can also make bike
inherit inherit vehicle as well so now
in our program.cs
file we are going to say uh we'll create
a car object so we'll say car equals new
car and that automatically gets imported
and we can say car let's first of all
actually have a look at the Shared uh
properties so bikes and cars now because
they both inherit vehicle have access to
all of these uh Properties or methods
within the class so let's have a look at
the Shared stuff first so we can say car
do uh
brand uh o sorry that should be
lowercase and we can say car.
start and car.
stop and then
also we can see that cars also have
their own properties which are only
available or only accessible on car
objects such as the number of doors for
example because bikes don't have doors
so we cannot put that onto the vehicle
class because bikes don't have doors so
that shouldn't be available on a bike uh
class or a bike object so then we can
say the unique uh properties and methods
to a car such as the number of
doors um
so so now when we run this
program we can see the vehicle is
starting and the vehicle is stopping uh
so these uh are the inherited methods
shared by bike and car or whatever
vehicle we have and we also have some
unique methods which are uh individual
or unique to the individual uh type of
vehicle so now if we change this to a
bike object let's just change it to a
bike object you can see we got an error
because number of doors doesn't exist on
bike but these start and stop uh methods
and also the brand are all available
because they are inherited from this
vehicle class so uh uh one of the
advantages of using inheritance is that
it means that we don't have to write the
commonly used fields and methods for
every single type of vehicle and also if
we want to change the start method then
we only have to change it in one place
because we aren't writing the start
method onto every single type of vehicle
it's all it's just one method inside of
the uh vehicle class meaning that we
only have to change it in one place
and another great thing about uh
inheritance is that it allows for
another very important object oriented
programming principle which we're going
to look at next called polymorphism
polymorphism is the ability of an object
to take many forms so poly means many
and morph meaning forms so I've got an
example here where we have a parent
vehicle class which stores the brand
model year and has a couple of methods
for starting and stopping a vehicle and
these are virtual methods which in c
means that these methods can be overit
by any uh subclasses or child classes
and we have a a car child class which
extends vehicle meaning that it uh sort
of um inherits these properties and
methods from
vehicle and then what we're doing is we
are over riding these start and stop
methods in car um because for example
starting a car
involves some different uh logic than
say starting a motorcycle or starting a
plane so motorcycle is also a vehicle
and it overrides these uh start and stop
methods but there are different steps in
starting a motorcycle so we have to
implement this these methods in inside
of the motorcycle class so you might be
wondering why do we bother extending
vehicle with these start and stop
methods when we are just uh when we're
having to implement them or specify them
within each individual type of vehicle
doesn't really make sense and the reason
for this is because it allows us to use
polymorphism uh which essentially allows
us to treat uh these objects in uh in
the same way so let me demonstrate what
I mean by what this means so if we
create a list
of uh any objects so this can be any
object this list of vehicles and then we
just add some vehicles to this list so
we H we add a new car object and we um
give it a brand of Toyota uh cam model
of Camry year 2020 and then we add a new
motorcycle so let's just call this uh
harleydavidson and let's give it a uh
model of uh let's see sport
fer and let's give it a year of
2021 okay so now we have a a list with
two uh of these vehicle uh classes but
in this list we can have any objects so
we can add you know a banana or a person
even though we've called it Vehicles we
can actually add anything to this list
because it's just a list of objects so
let's say we want to perform some sort
of uh vehicle uh in
inspection so what we need to do is we
need to Loop through this list of
objects so we can say VAR vehicle in
vehicles and let's say we want to start
the vehicle so we want to test starting
the vehicle so we can call vehicle.
start but the start method isn't here
which is unexpected
because all these are all vehicles so
far we were expecting to be able to call
this start method but our program has no
idea it's not it's not guaranteed that a
start method exists on one of these
objects because they're just any objects
they're not they're not
Vehicles so what we would have to
actually do is we'd have to actually
check what the type of this object is
before we can call any methods so for
example we would have to do this if
vehicle
is of type car we then have to cast this
object into a car object okay so we we
do uh we can say VAR car equals car
vehicle so we're casting it into a from
a generic object into a object of type
car and now it's a car object now we
know that it's a car object we can then
call car.
start okay but then if we want to also
uh test uh we also need to account for
testing motorcycles and planes so we
then have to do another elsif statement
to say uh check if the vehicle is a
motorcycle for
example and if it is we can say uh we
can cast the uh the object into a object
of type motorcycle and once we know it's
a motorcycle object we can call the
start method and then we would also have
to do the same for plane and the issue
with this is first of all it's hard to
read we have to have a lot of if uh and
else if conditional statements and also
if we add more uh vehicles to our
program such as uh a boat for
example then we also have to keep on
modifying our um our uh client classes
the classes that are using these vehicle
objects have to be modified which is not
good we don't want to have to keep on
modifying our code every time we add a
vehicle we just want to be able to add a
vehicle and not have to keep on
modifying our uh vehicle inspection
logic
okay so how do we fix this so first of
all rather than having a list of objects
we know that all of the uh
objects in this list are of type vehicle
because they're all extending the
vehicle class so we can say uh that this
is a list of vehicle
objects and now when we Loop through
this list of vehicles we know because
they're of type vehicle and we know that
all vehicles have this start and stop
method uh start and stop methods we can
simply just call vehicle.
start and that's it it's that simple so
we've actually used polymorphism here
because we're actually treating
different types of
objects uh as the same we're just
treating them as Vehicles okay we're not
worrying about whether it's a car or a
motorcycle or a plane because there are
all vehicle classes which have these
methods we can just call the method
directly and treat them all the same
okay so in this example let's just sum
things
up uh we have a list of vehicles
containing instances of both car and
motorcycle and then we iter iterate
through each vehicle in the list and
perform a gen General inspection so
we're just starting the vehicle that's
just a simple
inspection
um and despite the vehicles being of
different types polymorphism allows us
to treat them all as instances of the
base vehicle class the specific
implementations of the start and stop
method methods for each vehicle type are
invoked dynamically at runtime based on
the actual timee Tye of each
vehicle and because the list can only uh
contain objects that extend the vehicle
class we know that every object will
share some common fields and methods
meaning that we can safely call them
within the client
code uh without having to worry about
whether each specific vehicle has these
fields or
methods so this demonstrates how
polymorphism enables code to be written
in a more generic and flexible manner
allowing for easy extension and Main
maintenance of new types of vehicles as
they are added to the system so if we
add another type of vehicle we don't
have to say alfe vehicle is type of boat
and then cast it to a boat and then call
the start method whatever the start
method may be called on that boat
because it we have no uh reason to
actually call it start we could call it
start boat and then we could call start
boat it doesn't even have to be called
start if we don't uh extend the vehicle
class the vehicle class ensures that all
vehicles have this start
method and we can treat all vehicles the
same uh within our client code coupling
refers to the degree of dependency
between different
classes um so high coupling means that
classes are tightly in interconnected
making it difficult to modify or M uh
maintain them independently whereas low
coupling indicates loose connections
between classes allowing for greater
flexibility and ease of modification if
classes are tightly coupled then
modifying one class could break the
other which could break the whole
program so first of all let's consider
an example of uh where we have high
coupling and then we will improve this
example by reducing the
coupling so let's first of all create a
a bad example so we're going to create a
uh email sender
class and within this email sender class
we're going to have a
a method called send
email which takes a string
message and we're going to have some
email sending logic such as connecting
to the uh email
server
um uh authenticating all that kind of
stuff uh but we're not going to worry
about that we're just going to log
sending
email and then we're just going to
concatenate the message okay so then
let's let's say that we have some sort
of e-commerce application where a user
can can place orders they can order
certain items and once they've ordered
an item they get an email to say that
the order was placed successfully so
let's create this order class and let's
give it a uh method called place
order and then we have some place order
Logics and first kind of logic will be
inserting the order into the database uh
reducing the uh stock quantity of items
that have been ordered processing
payment all that kind of stuff but we
don't need to worry about that and then
once all that's been done we can send a
um email to the
user to say that the order has been
placed successfully
reassuring the uh user so we can send
email and give them a message to say
order placed
successfully okay then let's simulate uh
let's simulate a user
actually um placing an order so we can
say order equals New
Order and we can say order. place order
okay so let's run this
program and as we can see the order is
placed successfully and the user gets an
email to say that the order is placed
successfully so this all looks okay but
in this example the order class is
tightly coupled to the email sender
class because it directly creates an
instance of the email sender class okay
we we're calling the new keyword this
means that we're we're directly creating
an instance of email sender which makes
the order class dependent on the
implementation details of email sender
and any changes to the email sender
class may require modifications to the
order class okay so uh if we make a
change to email sender we may have to
also make modifications to the order
class okay and it just means that we may
you know if we change one class and also
have to change another class it means
that we are risking introducing bugs
into this class we'd rather not have to
modify this class if we change the
implementation details of email sender
it should just be all contained within
here we shouldn't it shouldn't affect
the order
class so let's now discuss how we can
reduce the uh
coupling so to to reduce coupling we can
introduce an abstraction or an interface
between the the order class and the
email sender class and this allows the
order class to interact with the email
sender class through an abstraction or
an interface making it easier to replace
or modify the implementation of email
sender without affecting or the order
class okay so if that doesn't make too
much sense uh we will we'll go through
an example now and it should make more
sense so let's create an interface
called I notification
uh
service
and all classes that implement this
interface should have a
send
notification uh method which takes a uh
message
string so now what we can do is we can
go into email sender and we can say that
email sender implement
notification service okay and what we
can do is if you can press if you press
command and then dot you can implement
the interface uh on Windows that's I'm
guessing that's control and
Dot and what we can do is we can copy
and paste this send email logic into
this send notification method and we can
get rid of send
email okay now in our order
class we can see that we
we have an issue now because the send
email class doesn't exist so what we
could do is call uh send
notification but you can see that this
order class is still tightly coupled to
this email sender uh for and the problem
with this is it's not very flexible
because for example let's say that the
user um wants to be uh send a text
message once the order has been placed
successfully there's no way of doing
this because the email send it is is
just hardcoded into this placeholder
method there's no way of switching out
the way that we uh send a notification
to the user so let's actually make that
possible so what we can
do as we can add a private field private
read only uh field of type I
notification service and we'll call this
notification service we'll create a
Constructor so whenever we create a new
order object we have to pass in the
notification service that we want to use
and we can set that notification
Service uh field
here and then what we can do in the
place order method rather than having
this email sender we can just
call notification service do send
notification and of course what we can
do
here is
uh we can pass this a message of order
placed
successfully
successfully okay so let's have a look
how this now uh works so we have an
error here because we actually need to
pass a notification service to any uh
order objects when we are creating order
objects so we can pass um an email
sender
and then place the
order and as you can see we are sending
email order placed
successfully okay so let's say that the
user wants
to uh have uh a notification by text
message so SMS so we can create an SMS
sender uh and then what we will do this
needs to implement the I notification
service interface we can implement the
method and what we can do is we can just
say uh SMS message and then we can just
concatenate on the
message so now what we can do if if um
the user wants to be notified by SMS we
can just say new SMS sender now the
reason we can CH switch out uh what kind
of notification service we use is
because in the order class we're saying
that we have to pass any type of
notification service and because we now
have this abstraction this
interface SMS sender and the email
sender are both of type or implement the
notification service so we can treat
them uh in the same way here we can pass
either an SMS sender or we can pass an
email sender so now we place the order
you can see here we're sending an email
we're now passing an m sms
sender and let's see what happens we get
an SMS message okay and we we were able
to switch out this SMS uh we were able
to switch the uh type of notification
service that we used without having to
modify this order class so in this
improved
example we have decoupled the order
class from the specific implementation
of the notification service allowing
different implementations for example
email sender or SMS Notifier SMS sender
whatever to be easily substituted
without modifying the order class uh and
this reduces coupling and improves the
flexibility and maintainability of the
code
base composition involves creating
complex objects by combining simple
objects or components in composition
objects are assembled together to form
larger structures with each component
object maintaining its own State and
behavior composition is often described
in terms of a has a
relationship so let's go through an
example to show you what composition
looks like so first of all we have a
load of uh sort of items or parts that
make up a car for example a car has a sh
chassis and here we just have a method
called support
so it just says chassis is supporting
the car we have an engine with a start
method uh we have seats with a Sit
method and we have some Wheels with a uh
rotate method okay so these are all the
parts that a car is composed of so now
if we have a look in the car
class we can see that H we have a car
class here that uses composition it is
essentially uh composed of these
different uh different parts and I
mentioned earlier that
um uh composition is often described in
terms of a has a relationship well we
can see here that a car has an engine uh
a car has wheels uh a car has a chassis
so you can see this is a good example of
a composition
relationship and uh in this example the
car class uses composition to assemble
it it components the car class is
composed of all of these items where
each component um for example the engine
or the wheels is a separate class
responsible for its own
functionality and the car class contains
instances of these component classes and
delegates tasks to them and you can see
here in this uh start car method you can
see that this car class is delegating
work to these component classes it's
saying engine start Wheels rotate
chassis support seat sit it's delegating
that work to those classes rather than
doing that kind of work itself uh and so
to start a car all we have to do is
create a car
object and I believe it is this
one and we run the start car method and
we run this uh this
program and we can see that all of this
work is has been has been delegated to
each of these component classes so as
you can see in summary we have a car
class which is composed of multiple
components and it delegates work to each
of these components so let's now take a
look at the differences between
composition and inheritance and when you
should probably use composition and when
you should probably use inheritance so
let's first have a look at when you
should use uh composition so you should
use composition when you need more
flexibility in constructing objects by
assembling smaller reusable components
so a good example for this is a car
class which is built from multiple
components or multiple smaller objects
such as an
engine uh Wheels chassis uh its seats
its dashboard uh GPS all these kind of
things a car can be uh constructed from
or composed from so um a composition
provides us good
flexibility and uh constructing objects
from uh smaller reusable
components uh you should also reach for
composition when there is no clear is a
relationship between classes and a has a
relationship is more appropriate so for
example a car is is a engine doesn't
make any sense uh whereas a circle is a
shape does make sense so maybe
inheritance would be uh an okay solution
there
whereas uh with uh the car and the
engine a car has an engine so
composition would uh make more sense so
that that seems to be a good solution to
start
with and you should also use composition
when you want to avoid the limitations
of inheritance such as tight coupling
and also the fragile Base Class problem
and this is a a problem which we are
going to look into shortly but for now
let's take a look at the advantage
advantages uh of inheritance and when
you should probably reach for
inheritance so you should reach for
inheritance when there is a clear is a
relationship between classes and
subclass objects can be treated as
instances of their superclass
so for example a uh a circle or a square
can be treated as shapes for example
which is their
superclass uh inheritance can also be
used when you want to promote code reuse
by inheriting properties and behaviors
from existing
classes and uh inheritance can be used
also when you want to leverage
polymorphism to allow objects of
different subclasses to be treated
uniformly through their common
superclass
interface so the fragile Bas class
problem is a software design issue that
arises in objectoriented programming
when changes made to a base class can
inadvertently break the functionality of
derived classes this problem occurs due
to the tight coupling between base and
derived classes in inheritance
hierarchies so let's now have a look at
what are the issues caused by the
fragile Base Class problem and then
we'll look into why we should probably
use uh what generally you should
probably reach for composition over
inheritance for uh most of your
Solutions so let's first of all consider
a a simple example so let's say we have
a shape class which is our Base Class
and let's say we have lots of different
derived classes or
subclasses uh which are going to be
actual shapes
such as a square rectangle circle
triangle Etc okay so our shape class is
our base class and then we have lots of
different derived
classes so first of all one of the
issues with using uh
inheritance or having a fragile base
class uh not necessarily inheritance but
having the fragile Base Class is
inheritance coupling so inheritance
creates a strong coupling between the
base class or the super class and the
derived classes or the subclasses any
changes made to the base class can
potentially affect the behavior of all
derived classes so if we change our
shape class in our example it could
affect the behavior of all of our
derived shape classes okay so another
issue is limited extensibility so the
fragile Base Class problem limits the
extensibility of software systems as
modifications made to the base class can
become uh increasingly risky and costly
over time developers May avoid making
Necessary changes due to the fear of
breaking existing functionality and this
is kind of known as brittle software
where making a change to one part of the
program can cause uh all sorts of
different parts of the program to uh
break making it uh brittle so this is
kind of um if if we have like a base
class where we hundreds of different uh
uh subclasses or derived classes then
you can kind of see that uh making
changes to this base class uh becomes
very risky because um it could have an
effect on so many different uh derived
subclasses and it could cause all sorts
of uh issues and uh it can break a lot
of the existing functionality and this
is uh very much a good example of having
a fragile Base Class where we have lots
of derived classes over time and making
changes to this Base Class becomes very
risky so how can we mitigate uh uh or
prevent having a fragile based class in
our uh
software so to mitigate the fragile Base
Class problem software developers can
use design principles such as the solid
open closed principle and they can also
use uh the dependency inversion
Principle as well as using composition
over inheritance and these approaches
promote loose coupling encapsulation and
modular design reducing the impact of
changes in base classes so generally
it's often recommended to use
composition over inheritance and the
reason for this uh is because
composition results in less coupling and
more flexibility
and it's also easier to build classes
out of various components than it is to
try and find commonality between them
and build a family tree as you kind of
have to do with
inheritance so uh there are still cases
where inheritance makes more sense but
generally it's uh recommended to reach
for
composition uh more so than inheritance
due to uh those uh reasons
so uml stands for unified modeling
language and it is a language used to
model our systems or our relationships
between our classes in our program and
throughout this course I've decided to
handdraw the uml diagrams uh as it's
quicker for me and gives me more
flexibility to annotate them uh but you
could also use a web app such as this
one that I have linked here and if I
just show you this this one you can see
that you can create your uml diagrams
with a sort of uh
GUI um but you can also handdraw them if
you find that easier such uh and that's
the case for me so first of all I'm
going to show you how you can represent
a simple class using uml so let's say
that we have a dog class a public class
dog which has one field uh which is just
a private string with uh of
name and we also have a method called
bark which returns void and just
logs uh a wo woof so this can be
represented
inl as as this diagram so at the top of
the uml diagram so we just have a sort
of box here and then we have three
sections and then we have the class name
at the top we have the fields listed in
this next section and then we have the
methods listed in the bottom section so
if we have a look at this name field now
we can see that this is a private field
so first of all we specify the access
modifier in this case it's a negative
sign which means that this is a private
field uh the name of the field which is
name and then we specify the return uh
sorry the type of the field after a
colon which in this case it is a
string and then we have the methods uh
so we have one method uh and we have a
plus sign here which means that it's a
public
method and it's called bark and it has a
return type of void so after the call
one we can just leave a blank space
which means that it returns
void and if you use the modeling app
that I referenced uh earlier and then it
would look something like this so same
thing just a computer computer drawn
version so we've discussed all of this
um and also I should just mention that
if the access modifier is emitted so if
I've left the access modifier out then
you should just assume that fields are
private and methods are public okay so
if I leave out the negative sign or the
plus sign you can just assume that this
is a private field and you should assume
that this is a uh public uh method okay
so that's just a kind of convention that
I've used throughout this book um yeah
so now let's have a look at how we can
represent inheritance relationships
using
uml so inheritance relationships are
represented by an arrow so we can see
here that the dog class inherits from or
extends the animal class so we have an
animal class here and it is extending
and dog is extending or inheriting from
the animal
class okay so if we have a look at the
uh how this would look in code we have
a a public class dog and in cop we
represent inheritance with a colon so we
can see the dog inherits or extends the
animal class and this is like um
inheritance is kind of like an is a
relationship so here we're kind of
saying like a dog is an animal okay so
that is
inheritance uh composition is
represented by by an arrow with a filled
Diamond so here's the filled diamond and
here is an arrow and composition is kind
of like a has at relationship so we're
saying dog has a
size okay so here's the sort of computer
drawn version um so how is how would
this look in code so we have our dog
class and then we're saying that dog is
composed of h a size class okay uh and
here we have a field of size
okay and if you if you're unsure on what
composition is exactly uh and you know
the difference between composition and
inheritance then I will be covering that
uh shortly Association relationships are
represented by an arrow and they're kind
of similar to uh composition
relationships however there is a
difference between uh Association and
composition so
Association uh a good example example
for this is a person has a car so a
person has a field for uh owning a car
but a person is not composed of a car a
person holds a reference to a car so
that it can interact with it but a
person can exist without a car so this
is an association relationship whereas
with composition uh is when a child
object wouldn't be able to exist without
its parent object for example a hotel is
composed of its rooms or holds reference
to its rooms and a hotel bathroom cannot
exist without a hotel without the hotel
class so if you destroy the hotel then
you also destroy the hotel bathroom the
hotel bathroom cannot exist by itself
otherwise it's just a bathroom it's not
a hotel bathroom also if a customer is
destroyed they shopping cart and orders
are lost too therefore a customer is
composed of shopping cart and orders and
if orders are lost then order details
and shipping info are also lost so
orders are composed of shipping info and
Order details so that is the main
difference between Association and
composition Association is where the uh
if you
destroy say a person uh class then the
car class can still exist because a
person isn't composed of or sort of made
up of cars it's just that a person can
own a car so so that so that the person
can interact with the car whereas
composition on the other hand is where
um if you destroy the CL the sort of
class that is made up of it of these uh
other classes or composed of these other
classes then these other classes are
also destroyed so that's the difference
between Association and
composition so now we're going to have a
look at depend relationship which is
represented by a dashed Arrow so here
you can see that dog um depends has a
dependency of
documents
okay so what does this mean so here we
have a public class dog and we have a
render method and we pass a document to
this render method so you know
presumably this means that we are
rendering the dog onto some documents
and we can pass the documents uh into
this render method so above documents is
not a field in this class okay but it is
used somewhere in the class in this case
it's a parameter to this render method
but it could it could also be a local
variable defined in the render method So
within this render method we could say
VAR documents equals new documents and
then that would also mean that dog has a
document dependency so somewhere in dog
class we have a reference or dependency
to the document class okay and that is a
dependency relationship so essentially
we have a parameter or a local variable
in one of the methods and that is as um
called a dependency
relationship so uh that is all of the
uml uh that I want to discuss for this
course there are uh many other
relationships that we could discuss but
that is all we all that you need to know
for uh studying uh design patterns so
one final thing that you should
understand before beginning to study
design patterns are the five solid
principles so here are the five solid
principles and the design patterns that
we're going to learn in this course are
very much based on both objectoriented
programming principles that we covered
earlier as well as these five solid
principles so they're very crucial to
understand so first first of all we're
going to learn the S of the solid
principle so this is an acronym in case
you've not noticed and that is the
single responsibility principle we're
going to also learn the open close
principle the lisof substitution
principle the interface segregation
principle and the dependency inversion
principle so by following these
principles developers can create
software designs that are easier to
understand maintain and extend which
leads to higher quality software that is
more robust and adaptable to change so
let's get started learning the solid
principles so the first solid principle
is the single responsibility principle
which states that a class should only
have one reason to change meaning that
it should only have one responsibility
or purpose and this principle encourages
you to create classes that are more
focused and perform one single well-
Define task rather than multiple tasks
so by breaking up classes into smaller
more focused units makes code easier to
understand maintain and test so first of
all what we will do is we will create an
example that violates the single
responsibility principle and then we
will refactor that code so that it aders
to this
principle so first of all what we're
going to do is we're going to create a
uh user class
and this is going to have uh two uh C
Properties uh so we're going to have a
username and we are going to have an
email uh
property and we're also going to have in
this user class a method for registering
a user so once they sign up to our
platform uh this should be
register this method will be called once
the uh while the user is signing up to
our platform and at the top we're going
to have some register user logic here so
this logic would be uh stuff like
fetching the user from the database by
their email and if they already exist
maybe we could redirect them to the
login page uh all that kind of stuff
related to registering a user saving
them to the
database uh and then once all that's
done we can send the uh user an email
notification okay so we're going to
create a uh an email uh sender class now
for sending email
notifications and this email
sender is going to have a send email
method which takes an email that we want
to send the email to and we will have a
message
and in here we're just going to console
log uh and we'll say sending email
to recip uh let's see send an email to
email and then we will put the
message okay so now we can uh use this
class to send the user an email
notification once they've signed up
successfully so we can say email sender
and then the message we'll say Welcome
to our
platform
okay so in this example this user class
is actually violating the single
responsibility principle because it uh
it manages user data okay so it
contains uh all data related to a user
such as their username or email and it
also contains the logic for registering
a user okay
so this class has more than one reason
to change so you can see here that the
single responsibility principle states
that a class should only have one reason
to change meaning that that it should
only have one responsibility or purpose
but this class has two reasons to change
because if we
change uh if we make modification to our
user data management uh for example we
might add more Fields here we might add
first name gender Hobbies age all that
kind of stuff uh if we add that to to
our user we would have to modify this
class we'd have to mod add more Fields
uh but another reason to that we we
could modify this class um or another
reason why this class uh would need to
be changed is if we changed the logic of
registering a user for examp example we
may choose to fetch a user from the
database by their username rather than
by their
email so we now let's refactor this
class so that it uh satisfies the single
responsibility
principle so to do that we can create a
separate class called user service so
let's do that
and in this user service class we will
we will put all of the methods or all of
the business logic uh related to uh
registering a user or maybe logging a
user in or updating a user all those
kind of methods can go into this user
service uh but we do need access to
certain user data so what we can do is
we can just pass the
user into this um method and then we can
call user.
email okay so in this refactored code
the user class is now solely responsible
for representing user data okay so it
has one responsibility a single
responsibility and the user
service uh the user service class now
handles user
registration uh
and this class can contain all sort of
business logic related to users So
currently we only have a register
function but we could also have a login
method or an update
method um to manage uh any sort of
business logic related to a
user um and this re this separation of
responsibilities aders to the single
responsibility principle and so it makes
our code easier to understand maintain
and extend the open close principle
states that software entities such as
classes modules or functions should be
open for extension but closed for
modification and this principle promotes
the idea that existing code should be
able to be extended with new
functionality without modifying its
source code so and it encourages the use
of abstraction and polymorphism to
achieve this goal allowing for code to
be easily extended through inheritance
or composition so if that doesn't make
much sense to you we're now going to go
through an
example uh where we have a shape class
hierarchy that calculates the area of
different
shapes and initially this is going to
violate the open close principle because
when we add any new shapes uh it
requires modifying uh the existing
code so first of all what we're going to
do is we're going to create date and
enom for uh our types of
shapes okay so we're just going to
support a circle and a rectangle
initially and we're going to create a
class uh for
shape and this is going to be a class
which stores the shape type uh and
radius length and width so it supports
lots of different
shapes
okay so I'm just going to paste those in
so we have a shape type so it going to
be for example a rectangle or a circle
so it's it has a radius so if the shape
is a circle we're going to set the
radius if it's a rectangle we'll set the
length and
width and then we're going to have a
method for calculating the area of the
shape and we're going to have a switch
statement which takes in the type of the
shape and it's going to look at the type
of the shape so for example if the shape
type is C Circle we are going to return
uh P pi r 2 which is the equation for
calculating the area of a
circle so math.
po so this is just the radius squared
radius to the^ of
Two And if the shape type is a
rectangle we are going to return
the
length times the
width okay and
if our uh shape type doesn't match any
of the uh shape types here then we're
going to throw an
exception to say that we do not support
this shape type
okay so in this
example uh the shape class has a method
for calculating the area of a shape
based on the type of
shape so if we add a new shape such as a
triangle so if we added a triangle in
here and then we wanted to support
calculating the area of a triangle angle
it would require modifying this existing
shape class okay so if we add a new
shape every time we add a new shape we
have to modify this shape class we may
have to add uh new properties to support
triangles we may have to add things like
the uh hypotenuse the
um uh whatever the other sides of a
triangle or I've forgotten and then we
have to calculate the
area of uh a triangle okay so this this
class is just going to keep on getting
modified every time we had a new shape
this calculate area method is just going
to get bigger and bigger and bigger it's
going to be hard to understand and every
time we add a new shape we risk adding
bugs into code that has been tested and
we know and we know works so this is a
really poor uh way to
implement a uh this kind of uh
application or
functionality so let's now refactor this
code to adhere to the open close
principle so that whenever we add a
shape we don't have to modify any
existing uh
code so essentially we want to allow for
extension which means adding uh new
classes to our codebase for example uh
we we can extend our code Base by adding
a new shape but we don't want to modify
our existing class existing source code
so now let's refactor this code uh using
inheritance and
polymorphism so I think what I'm going
to do is I'm going
to Let's remove all of these properties
from the shape uh
class and let's remove all of
this and what I'm going to do is I'm
going to make this class
abstract meaning that we can create uh
methods that essentially have no uh body
okay like that so that when we in any
classes that inherit this shape class
now have to provide their own
implementations of this calculate area
method so what we're going to do now is
we're going to create uh individual
shape classes so we're going to create
a circle
class and this is going to uh inherit
shape and when you can see we have an
error here so if I press command and
full stop or I guess control full stock
on Full Stop on Windows we can then
implement this abstract class so we now
override this uh calculate area method
from the uh shape abstract class Okay so
so this is an abstract class and then we
are providing uh
concrete um implementations of shapes
okay so circle is a concrete
implementation of the shape class and
concrete basically meaning that it's not
abstracted you know it's a proper normal
class so in here to calculate area we
need to do p pi r squ so now we need to
uh store a
property for radius
and here we can just return uh math.
pi
times math. power radius to the power of
two okay so there's our Circle class and
now we want to add a rectangle class so
let's
add
that and a rectangle has a length and a
width so we'll add properties for length
and width and then to calculate the area
of a uh rectangle we just return the
length times the width okay but what we
need to do here is make sure that we uh
inherit the shape now it gives us an
error because the shape if we inherit
shape it's forcing forcing all of the
concrete shapes to implement the
calculate area method so let's Implement
Implement that and we just want to
return the length times the uh
width
Okay so we've now refactored the code so
that we have individual shape classes
rather than having this shape class
which kind of man manages multiple
shapes and this actually also satisfies
the single responsibility principle
because the shape class now isn't
managing
uh calculating the area well it isn't
managing multiple different types of
shapes and we now have individual shape
classes rather than having the shape
class manage all of the different types
of shapes so in this refracted code we
Define an abstract shape class with an
abstract calculate area method and we
Define uh concrete uh shape classes uh
Circle and rectangle which inherit the
shape class class and provide their own
implementations of the calculate area
method so now with this new solution
whenever we add a new shape such as uh a
triangle it would involve creating a new
class which inherits from shape and
implements the calculate area method uh
without having to modify any existing
code so if we wanted to create a if we
wanted to add a triangle uh shap shape
and we wanted to add the ability to
calculate an area we would just create a
new triangle class uh with which extends
shape and includes the calculate area
method and that's it we just extend our
code base we add a new class without
having to modify any existing code so
we're not risking uh adding bugs into
previously tested working code and that
satisfies the open close principle by
allowing for extension without
modification so being able to add
functionality without modifying existing
code means that we don't have to worry
worry as much about breaking existing
working code and introducing books so
following the open close principle
encourages us to design software so that
we can add new features only by adding
new code and this helps us to build
Loosely coupled maintainable software
the listof substitution principle states
that objects of a super class should be
replaceable with objects of its subass
without affecting the correctness of the
program so this principle ensures that
inheritance hierarchies are
well-designed and that subclasses adhere
to the contracts defined by their
superclasses and violations of this
principle can lead to unexpected
Behavior or errors when substituting
objects making code harder to reason
about and maintain so this is very
confusing so let's consider consider an
example involving a rectangle class and
a square class which inherit from a
common shape class and initially this is
going to violate the lisof uh
substitution principle by not adhering
to the behavior expecting uh expected
from these classes and then we'll fix it
to ensure that the principle is
respected so first of all we're going to
create a shape
class and this is going to be an
abstract uh class this is going to be
this is going to sit at the very top of
our uh sort of shape class hierarchy and
we're going to create a public
abstract uh property uh for
area and so all shapes should have this
area
property so next up we're going to
create a concrete implementation of our
abstract shape class so we're going to
create a uh rect angle
class and this is going to
inherit shape and then we can press
command full stop Implement abstract
class and we can see vs code
automatically uh implements this area
property for us
so if we look at a rectangle a rectangle
has a width and a height so let's add
properties for width and height
because we need those properties to be
to be able to calculate the area of the
rectangle and the area of a rectangle is
very simply just its width times its
height
okay so that's a
rectangle uh we're now going to create a
square
class and this is where things get
slightly more
interesting because the way we're going
to implement the Square class is we are
going to
extend or inherit from the rectangle
class and why are we doing this because
well a a square is mathematically just a
special type of
rectangle where the width and the height
are equal to each other okay so that's
our line of thinking we're just thinking
right a square class is a special type
of rectangle a square is a rectangle so
let's actually inherit the rectangle
class uh but we need to make a few
modifications because if a square if we
set the width on a
square then we can't we need to make
sure that it's equal to the height and
if we set the the height on his uh
square and we need to make sure that the
width is also set equal to the height so
that the side lengths are always the
same and a square always remains Square
so let's actually do that so what what
we can do is we can
override the uh width
property and we can say
that uh the GAA Remains the
Same we just return the width the base
referring to our base uh class which in
this case is
rectangle and then we can update the
seta so that the uh base dot width
is equal to the base dot height which is
equal to the value that we are setting
to okay so the width and the height are
always going to be equal and then we can
do the same for the height and I'm just
going to save a little bit of time here
and copy and paste that in so as you can
see uh the GAA just Returns the the
height and when we set we also set the
width equal to the value that we are
setting to okay so a square always
remains Square
okay so now what we're going to do is
we're going to write a
test um and in the test what we're going
to do is we're going to make sure that
our program is
calculating uh areas correctly or as
expected so we're going to create a
rectangle and we're going to set the
rectangle's height equal to
10 and we're going to set the
rectangle's width equal to
five and
then we can say that the
expected uh
area is going to be equal to 10 Time 5
which equals
okay and then we can log the actual area
that the rectangle calculates
um by calling re.
area so if we' run this
program we can see that the expected
area is equal to the calculated area and
this test passes successfully but now if
we look at the lisof substitution
principle uh objects of his super class
should be replaceable with objects of
its subass so the super class in this CL
in this case is
rectangle and a rectangle
subass is shap uh Square sorry because a
square is a subass of rectangle in this
case right it inherits from rectangle so
according to the lisof substitution
principle we should be able to
substitute a rectangle for a square and
our program should still be correct so
let's see if that works so we we
substitute it for a square run our
program and we can see that the expected
area is 50 but the calculated area is 25
because when we set the width it also
sets the height to five as well so then
when it calculates the area it's going
to be returning height time width which
is 5 * 5 which equals 25 and this is not
what we expected so we are here
violating the list lisof substitution
principle you you can kind of see how
this makes it it easier for a program to
contain books
because if we treat a square as a
rectangle which according to our code we
should be able to we we shouldn't get
any errors but we are getting errors
this P this test no longer
passes so let's um refactor our program
to to satisfy the lisof substitution
principle so what we are going to
do is we're going to modify our uh
Square
class so that it no longer inherits from
rectangle okay so what we're going to do
is we're going to inherit from shape
okay we're just going to say a square as
a shape and not a
rectangle okay so and a square
really it doesn't really feel feel very
correct to store width and height
properties on a square it doesn't really
make much sense because a square just
has a side length and all the side
lengths are equal it has four sides and
each side is an equal length so really
we only need to store one property
called side length so if we create a
public uh
property for side length
and also we can see here that we are
getting an error because we need to
implement the shape abstract class by
providing an area uh property and the
area is just going to be the side length
squared or the side length times the
side
length
Okay so we now have a rectangle and a
square which are both shapes they both
inherit the shape class so
so now let's create a
test for
our uh square and rectangle so what I'm
going to
do uh let's uh comment this out for now
and we'll create a new test so we're
going to just say shape rectangle equals
new
rectangle and I think what we'll do
actually is we'll just set the uh width
and height when we uh create the
rectangle just to save a little bit of a
few lines of
code okay and then what we will do is we
will
log the uh
area of the rectangle
okay and then what we'll do is we'll
also create a
um a test for our Square class and as
you can see here both rectangle and
square are shapes they are classes of
type shape and we're going to create a
new
square and we will set the side length
equal to
five and then we can say
area of the
square is equal to square dot
area okay so here we're expecting 25
because 5 * 5 is 25 and above we are
expecting 20
okay okay perfect so now what we can do
is we can
essentially uh
we've we've redesigned the square class
to directly set the side length so now
that uh so now a square is correctly
modled as a subclass of shape and it
adheres to the lisof substitution
principle because now all shapes are
substitutable with each other and they
they calculate their uh areas uh
correctly okay or as
expected so how does this satisfy the of
substitution principle well we've
created a super class called shape and
subclasses rectangle and square okay and
both rectangle and square maintain the
correct expected behavior of a shape uh
and in our case that is providing an
area and they should both behave
appropriately when interacting with
other parts of the program that expect
shapes so we can now treat rectangle and
square as
shape uh of type shape and they both
always uh calculate areas as we expect
them to the expected area of a square
here I mean we haven't logged what the
expected area is but we could log that
the expected area is going to be 25 and
we here we could log that the expected
area is going to be
20 okay and whatever we change the side
length to whatever we set the side
length to it's always going to uh give
us the corre correct area Okay so shapes
now are always going to return the
correct area we have no problems with
substituting shapes with other shapes
and then calculating their areas okay so
now we are satisfying the lisof
substitution principle and our program
is less error prone okay less prone to
introducing bugs and um uh less prone to
unexpected Behavior the interface
segregation principle states that
clients should not be forced to depend
on interfaces that they do not use and
this principle encourages the creation
of fine grained interfaces that contain
only the methods required by the clients
that use them it helps to prevent the
creation of fat interfaces that Force
clients to implement unnecessary methods
leading to cleaner and more maintainable
code so this may sound confusing again
but actually this principle is pretty
straightforward so let's consider an
example that involves 2D and 3D shapes
and we'll initially we're going to
violate this interface segregation
principle and then we are going to
refactor that code to adere to the
principle so first of all we're going to
create an
interface called I
shape and this is going to contain a
methods for calculating certain
properties on a shape so such as as area
or
volume okay so now what we're going to
do is we're going to create a uh Circle
class a concrete Circle
class uh and that's going to uh
implement this I shape
interface okay so we're getting a red
red squiggly line here which means that
we need to implement this interface or
you know implement the methods on this
interface so so a circle class is going
to have a radius
property and what we're going to do is
to calculate the area of a circle we
just quite simply do pi r 2 so we do
we're going to return pi times uh the
radius to the power of 2 and then for
calculating the
volume well here we have an issue
because circles don't actually have
volumes because they are a 2d shape all
2D shapes don't have volumes they only
have
areas so here we've been forced to
implement this volume method from I
shape because I shape states that we
must Implement a volume method otherwise
we'll get an error so what we're going
to have to do here really is we're going
to return an invalid
operation
exception and we'll say that volume
is volume not
applicable uh for 2D
shapes okay
so um so that is the circle and now
we're going to uh create a 3D shape now
called sphere so basically a
ball and this is also going to implement
the I shape class uh sorry the I shape
interface and we press command full stop
or control full stop and we're going to
implement the uh methods on this
interface so to calculate the area of a
sphere we have to do the uh
radius uh to the^ of 2 * piun * 4 that's
just the equation for calculating the uh
area of a sphere so I'm just going to
paste that
in so we we have 4 * pi * the radius
squar and then the volume of a
sphere is this equation so it's uh four
4/3 or 4 over 3 * piun * the radius
cubed Okay so so 4/3 pi R
cubed okay so this all looks okay I
think what we'll do next is we will
create uh we will actually use this
solution so let's create a circle if we
come into
program.cs and we will create a new
circle from the
from
here
and we'll set the radius equal to
10 and let's log the
area and let's also log the uh
volume okay so according to vs code um
we have no problems here this this code
should be safe to run
but if we run the
code
um we can see that we get an ex
exception because volume is not
applicable for 2D shapes we are uh in
our program we are calling circle.
volume and VSS code even suggests that
we can call this function uh this
method and everything looks okay but
when we run the code we have a
problem
so really
this volume method should not exist on
Circle because it
really well all 2D shapes don't have a
volume so it just doesn't make any sense
it's making our code more prone to bugs
by allowing us to call this method on a
circle so it's it's easy to see that uh
how violating this
interface uh segregation principle can
introduce bugs into a program because
above everything looks okay until we run
the program
and then we get the exception
thrown
um because this I I shape interface is
forcing forcing us to implement volume
methods on all of our shapes even when
it's not relevant so how can we solve
this
problem so let's refactor our code so
what we're going to do is we're going to
we're going to
segregate this I shape interface into
two separate interfaces
so we're going to create a i shape 2D
and an i shape 3D so this actually can
be changed to 3D because 3D shapes have
both an area and a volume so I'm just
going to rename this file to I shape
3D and I'm going to create another
interface called I shape
2D and 2D shapes only have an area they
don't have a volume
volume okay and again this should be an
interface not a
class okay so now we have we've
segregated the ey shape interface into
two separate smaller uh more sort of
finely fine grained interfaces that are
more specific okay rather than large and
sort of
general and now what this allows us to
do is in our Circle class we can
implement the I shape
2D and we can remove this volume uh
method because we are no longer being
forced to implement a volume method and
then in our sphere class we can
implement the 3D uh
interface and now if we go back into our
program we can see if we try to call
volume on a 2d shape we are now getting
an error so vs code is straight away say
this method uh does not exist basically
and and it shouldn't exist because 2D
shapes don't have uh
volumes so as you can see the interface
segregation principle ensures that
clients are not forced to depend on
methods that they do not use clients can
now depend only on the interfaces that
they need promoting better code and
reusability and if you are't sure on
what a client is a client essentially
just means classes that are using the uh
shape interface okay so for example a
circle is a client of the I shape 2D
interface the dependency inversion
principle states that highlevel modules
should not depend on low-level modules
both should depend on
abstractions so dependency inversion is
the strategy of depending upon on
interfaces or abstract classes rather
than upon concrete classes this
principle promotes decoupling between
modules and promotes the use of
interfaces or abstract classes to Define
dependency uh dependencies allowing for
more flexible and testable
code so this probably doesn't make any
sense whatsoever so we're going to start
with an example that first violates the
dependency inversion principle and then
we are going to correct it so first of
all I'm going to create an engine
class and the engine class is just going
to contain a single method uh called
start which is just going to log uh
engine
started okay and then we're going to
create a car
class and car is going to be built up
from different parts and one of those
parts is an engine a car of course would
also have wheels and a chassis and all
different uh other things that it will
be built up from but we're just going to
keep things simple for now and just
include the engine and uh we're going to
have a
Constructor for this
car and in the Constructor we're just
going to set the engine so we'll just
say this. engine equals new engine so we
have uh this car class which has a
direct dependency on this concrete
engine
class and this car class is also going
to contain a method for starting the
car and to start the car we actually
need to start the engine so we can start
uh we can call engine.
start and we
can just log car started
okay so in this example the car class
directly creates an instance of the
engine class leading to a tight coupling
between core and engine so if this
particular engine class changes it may
affect the car class which violates the
dependency inversion principle so if I
just show you the uml diagram what we
have
here we have a car class which depends
directly on a concrete engine
class okay
so let's go back
here so how can we fix this uh issue
well first of all let's let me just uh
discuss what the issues with this
Implement with this solution are
so uh if we change the engine class then
it could break the car class okay so
that's uh a problem if we if we change
the implementation details of this
engine class it can affect the car class
and another thing is is that this code
isn't very flexible so if we go into
program.cs and we create a
car uh that's not the correct one uh
let's
see
okay uh we actually have no way when we
when we create a new car we have no way
of changing the type of engine that that
car is built with so uh
currently if we want to change the type
of engine so say we have currently we
only have one engine class but say we
have another class called uh electric
engine or I don't know V6 engine or some
other powerful engine there's no way of
uh changing the engine type when we
create a new car you know we can't just
add the engine uh in here we have to
change it within the car class okay so
this isn't very flexible so if we wanted
to say electric engine we would have to
come in here and change it to electric
engine and obviously we would need to
create that class so this is not a very
flexible or maintainable solution
because we're having to modify uh
existing source code in order to uh
change the type of engine that a car
uses so this isn't very good
so uh we can fix this uh uh to adhere to
the dependency inversion principle we
can introduce an abstraction or an
interface between core and engine
allowing core to depend on an
abstraction instead of a concrete
implementation so let's come into
our uh folder and create an interface
called I
engine and in here we're going to have
uh we're going to that all engines
should have a start uh
method then inside of our uh engine
class we can say that engine implements
I engine okay so an engine is an engine
obviously and we don't need to do
anything here because our engine class
already has a start
method and then in
core So currently we have core depend
depending on the concrete implementation
of an engine rather than an abstraction
such as an interface or an abstract
class so let's change this so we can say
that rather than engine being this
concrete engine we can say um we can say
the engine is some some type of engine
some abstract
engine and then within the core
Constructor we can specify we can
actually pass a type of engine
that we want the car to be built with so
we can say this. engine equals engine
okay so the advantage of this method is
that it provides us with a lot more
flexibility because now whenever we
create a new car we can at runtime we
can pass in what type of engine that we
want the car to be built with like so
and currently we only have one type of
engine but let's just say we also had
another type of engine that implements
the i engine interace face such as
electric engine then we can create some
sort of electric car we can build this
car up uh with an electric
engine okay so this is called dependency
injection where we inject the dependency
into uh the class okay and this is a
very popular term that you may have
heard before uh Frameworks such as laral
or spring boot uh use dependency
injection throughout a lot of the
framework so let me show you the uml so
what this looks like so beforehand we
had car which directly depended on
engine whereas now we've added this kind
of abstraction this interface between
car and engine so car now depends on
this abstract engine interface and
engine
implements uh the engine interface okay
so now we can create multiple different
different types of engines each in uh
implementing this interface so we could
have um a V6 engine which implements
this engine interface or an electric
engine and we can then inject that
engine whenever we create a new car
object into car to be built with that
type of engine so this has really
improved the uh
flexibility of our uh program
so um a few uh advantages that I just
want to mention of dependency injection
or that uh dependency injection uh
promotes loose coupling between
components by removing direct
dependencies uh so that comp uh
components rely on abstractions rather
than concrete implementations making
them more independent and easier to
maintain and dependency injection
simplifies unit testing by allowing
components to be easily replaced with
mock or stub implementations during
testing this enables isolated testing of
individual components without relying on
their dependencies and as we discussed
it improves flexibility because we can
swap out dependencies at
runtime uh and then one more thing that
I just wanted to uh mention so if we go
to the dependency verion principle uh
kind of definition it states that
highlevel modules should not depend on
low-level modules both should depend on
abstractions so we saw that car and
engine are now depending on abstraction
and abstraction the i engine interface
rather than on each
other but which which of these is the
high level module and which is the
lowlevel module
so um so the engine is actually
considered the lowlevel
module or the lowlevel abstraction
because it deals with uh specific
detailed operations related to power
generation whereas the car in this case
would be considered the higher level uh
abstraction or the higher level
module because uh it encompasses a
broader scope
coordinating uh multiple components
including the engine So currently we
only have the engine but in a real car
would of course have multiple
components uh and to deliver the overall
uh functionality of the vehicle so the
car is the higher level module and the
engine is the lower level module and the
high level module no longer depends on
the lowle module they both depend on an
abstraction and therefore our code is
much more flexible and much more
testable uh easier to
maintain and that is g to uh the
dependency inversion
principle so now we can start looking at
design patterns and there are three main
groups of design patterns there are
creational design patterns and these are
related to the different ways to create
objects there are Dru uh structural
design patterns and these uh design
patterns are related to the
relationships between those objects and
then we have behavioral design patterns
uh which are related to the interaction
or communication between those objects
and first of all we're going to have a
look at the behavioral design patterns
behavioral design patterns focus on how
objects interact with each other and how
they communicate to accomplish specific
tasks these patterns address
communication responsibility and
algorithmic issues in objectoriented
software design they help in defining
clear and efficient communication
mechanisms between objects and classes
these patterns help in making the design
more flexible extensible and
maintainable by promoting better
communication and separation of concerns
between objects and classes in the
system each pattern addresses specific
design issues and provides a
standardized solution to common problems
encountered in software
development so if you're unsure on exact
what exactly these words mean such as
flexible extensible and
maintainable then uh throughout this
course I'm going to be using these words
a lot and you're going to have um
they're going to become part of your uh
sort of uh programming
vocabulary uh as as you go along this
course and yeah these are words that
you're going to use uh quite often to
describe uh the code that you are uh
writing or or
analyzing uh and here you can see that
we state that these design patterns
provide a standardized solution to
common problems so for example if you
need to uh uh Implement some sort of
undo mechanism in your program then
maybe you know the first design pattern
that comes to mind could be something
like the M momento pattern uh so uh yeah
these are design patterns are really
nice tools and when you're also uh
analyzing other people's code you you're
probably going to rec recogize uh
certain words or or certain uh yeah
certain words that are used in class
names and it's going to give you a sort
of clue to the solution that the
developer went with so that being said
let's get started the momento pattern is
used to restore an object to a previous
state and a common use case for the
momento pattern is when implementing an
undo feature for example most text
editors such as Microsoft Word have undo
features where you can undo things by
pressing contrl Z on Windows or command
Z on Mac so here are some things that
you might want to do in a text editor so
you want might want to add a title to
the document such as test title you
might want to write some text such as
hello there my name is Dan and then you
might want to update or change the title
of the document to the life of a
developer my M was and a simple way to
implement this text editor in code will
be to create a single editor class and
have a field for title and content and
also have a field that stores each of
the previous values for each field in
some list so here we have the uml for a
editor class it has a title field and a
Content field both of uh type string and
then we have a previous titles field
which does a list of all of the previous
titles so if we update the title it will
push the current title onto to this list
and then update the title and the same
thing for Content okay we have a prev
previous content list too uh so but the
problem with uh this solution is that
every every time we add a new field such
as author date or is published uh we
have to keep storing a list of previous
States or all of the changes for each of
the new Fields so you can see that this
editor class is going to become very
bloated with a large number of
fields and also how would we actually
implement the undo feature with this
solution because if the use the change
the title then they Chang the content
then pressed undo the current
implementation has no knowledge of what
the user last did it doesn't know
whether the title last changed or the
content last changed and so when undo is
pressed our solution doesn't really know
whether we should undo the title or undo
the content or both at the same time so
this isn't a great solution so let's uh
think of a better way of doing this so
instead of having multiple fields in the
editor class we could create a separate
uh class to store the state of our
editor at any given time so here we have
our editor class title content fields
and now we have a list of previous state
objects and this is a uh State object
which stores the title and content of
the editor at at any given time and note
that this is a composition
relationship uh represented by the
diamond Arrow uh where editor is
composed of or has a field of the editor
State class and it has a list of editor
States and this is a better solution
because we can undo multiple times and
we also don't pollute the editor class
with too many fields we just have one
field for storing a list of editor
States
however this solution is violating the
single responsibility Principle as our
editor class currently has multiple
responsibilities it is currently uh
managing the state of the editor so it
is storing a list of states and it's
also providing the features that we need
from an editor so what we should do is
we should take all the State Management
stuff out of the editor and put it
somewhere else into some separate class
and this is what we end up with
so now we have a separate class called
history which is basically managing the
uh list of states or list of previous
States uh from our editor so here we can
see that we have a create State method
inside of the editor and the create
State method simply returns an editor
State object or the current state of the
editor uh and that and that is
represented by a dotted line L Arrow uh
here so we can see that editor has a
dependency of editor State because one
of its methods is returning and editor
State object which is the create State
method uh is returning this editor State
object and then we also have a history
uh class which has a field with a list
of editor States hence the diamond Arrow
or composition relationship uh
represented
here so um
history this history class we have a
backup method and the backup method
whenever this is called it will add uh
onto the list of states the current
editor state so editor. create State
Returns the current state of the editor
and then we push or add it onto this
States list okay which is storing our
sort of history from the editor and then
we also have an undo method in this
history class which basically gets or uh
yeah pops off the last state from the
states list uh it then removes that
state from the list and then restores
the editor to that last state so that is
how we sort of implement the undo
feature now so um this is actually the
moment momento pattern this uh kind of
represented by this uml
diagram uh but let's have a look at how
the momento pattern is represented in in
the gang of four uh book so here are the
abstract names that each class would be
given in the gang of four
book so um here we have the originator
which is uh analogous to our editor
class we have the momento which is
basically our state object and then we
have the caretaker which in our case is
called the history
object um
and um we can see that our solution
actually differs slightly from the uh
original ganger 4 um uh momento pattern
as our caretaker uh our caretaker class
which is the history class also has a
field that stores a reference to the
editor class so that the history class
can restore the editor State when the
user clicks undo so when the user goes
into their history clicks undo then we
have a reference to the editor class so
we can actually call editor. Restore and
pass in the state that we wanted to
restore the editor too and that's just
nice sort of convenient uh way of doing
that and it works for uh our kind of
program or our application so you can
see that the with these design patterns
they are not you don't have to follow
them exactly you can uh change them
slightly it's just the general uh shape
or idea that um we can um we can kind of
follow okay so you don't have to follow
them exactly they can be uh customized
or slightly changed but the general
shape is still there this is still the
momento pattern okay so now what we're
going to do is we're going to implement
this uh solution in code so that it
makes more sense to you so first of all
we are going to create our editor class
or using the gang of for abstract name
that would be the originator so let's
come into here and create a new C Class
called
editor and I'm just going to make a note
to say that this is the
originator okay so our editor has uh
currently just two Fields it has a
public uh string
field sorry it has a
property it has a public public
property uh for
title which can which has a getter and a
Setter and it has a public property
called
content and we have a geta and Setter
for that and we're now going to create
um the uh momento or the editor State uh
class okay so let's come into here and
create a new SHP class called editor
State and editor state is just going to
uh store two Fields so it's going to
have two private fields and I'm going to
make these read only so that once the
editor state is created uh it cannot be
changed so that's going to just add to
the robustness of our code because once
the editor State uh has been created
once we've took a backup of our editor
then we shouldn't then be able to uh
edit that okay it should just be sort of
constant so let's create a field for
title and a private readon string for
Content okay so now what we're going to
do is we're going to create a
Constructor and in the Constructor we
can pass in the title and content
and then we're just going to set our
title and
content uh and then what I want to also
do is create a geta for
title so that we can actually uh
retrieve the uh title uh for this
current state so we'll create a method
called get
title and that is very simply just going
to return the title and we'll also
create a gter because we will need
access to the content if we're going to
restore uh the content and the title to
previous States uh we're going to
restore the editor to a previous state
then we need to be able to actually get
the uh the title and the content from
this editor State object so let's create
another geta called get
content and we're just going to return
the
content and what I'm also going to do
here is in this editor State object I'm
going to add
uh some State
metadata okay and I'm going to make it
private read
only and I'm just going to store the
date that the state was created
at and I'm going to call the state
created
at and what I'm going to do is when a uh
editor State object is created we can
set the state created at uh field equal
to datetime do now so whenever we create
a backup we're kind of storing the date
and time that the backup was created
okay so it's just like a little bit of
extra
metadata uh to give us a little bit more
information about the state or when the
state was backed
up so let's also create a geta for this
get uh for this date um
field so this is going to
return uh a date time
uh piece of data and we're just going to
return the state created at okay so
that's everything we needed to do in our
uh momento object so I'll just make a
note that this in the gang of four is
referred to as the uh momento object the
state
object okay so now what I'm going to do
is I'm going to come back into our uh
editor class and I'm going to create a
couple of Meth methods so I'm going to
create a method called uh create state
which is going to return uh an editor
State
object okay and
this editor state is going to take uh
the
title and the
content okay so whenever we create a
state we're just simply returning the
current state of the editor the current
title and the current
content okay and then to
restore the uh Editor to a previous
state we can create a restore method
which takes in an editor State
object and we can just simply set the
title equal to that state state title so
we can say let me change this actually
we'll we'll just call this
State and we will
say this is going to be equal to state.
tile so get
title and then we'll set the content
equal to state. getet
content okay so that's everything we
need to do in our editor class we have
our fields in the editor uh we also have
a method for creating a sort of backup
or um a sort of State object of the
current state of the editor and we also
have a restore method for restoring the
editor to any previous state okay so now
what we're going to do is we need to
take uh make our uh sort of history
class or in the gang of four that would
be referred to as our uh caretaker class
so we're calling we're calling it the
history uh object or the history class
and the history class stores a list of
all the previous editor States
and we're going to call the
states and we'll just set it equal to a
new list of editor
States and in our case we're also going
toore a reference to the editor class uh
the editor
object okay and then when we construct
the history uh object we need to
actually pass in the editor that the
history class is uh referring to so
let's create the uh Constructor and
we're going to pass an
editor as a parameter and we're just
going to set the editor equal to the
editor that we pass into this history
object upon object
creation okay so now we need to add our
backup method so let's create a public
uh method called
backup and all this is going to do is
it's going to uh add onto the states
list um the current state of the editor
and we have a create State method which
does that for us so that's pretty simple
and we also need a uh undo
method uh so this is going to allow us
to um restore the the editor to its last
uh backtop state so what we need to do
here is we need to just perform a check
to say um to check if we actually have
any backed up States so we can say if
states. count equals zero then we can
just return okay so if we don't have any
backed up uh if we have no States in our
states list then we can just return here
there's nothing to undo
otherwise we can get the last state from
the
editor so the previous state and that's
going to be equal to states.
last we can then remove this uh state
from the state's
list so this is the equivalent of just
popping the uh State off of the list off
of the end of end of the list and then
what we can do is we can call our
editor and we can call the restore
method and we can pass the last state or
the previous state and the editor will
be restored to its previous
state and what I'm also going to do is a
kind of nice uh method that we can add
to this history
class uh is one called show history
where we basically list all of of the uh
all of the history all of the backed up
states that we have of our editor so
let's actually implement
this I'm just going to put a new line
here and I'm going to say
history here's the list of
mos and what we're going to do is we can
Loop
through all of the uh
States and we can just console uh
write uh state DOT
get
uh actually I think we need to add
another method to the uh editor
State uh
class yeah cuz I wanted to call a method
called get name but we actually haven't
implemented that yet so if we go back
into our editor State uh class we're
going to create a another method called
get
name and this is just going to return
something that we can display on the
console
um to sort of represent the
state so uh let's see
so what we're going to do is we're going
to log the the created ad date and we
will also log the uh
title okay so this is just basically
going to be our kind of uh some way of
uh a sort of unique identifier for the
uh State object so if we go back into
history we can see the error has
disappeared and now everything should be
be ready to start using so now if we
come back if we come into our program.cs
file let's actually test out our momento
pattern solution for this editor so I'm
going to create a uh new
editor I'm also going to create a
history uh
object and we're going to pass the
editor into this history
object and it says the name space is
missing so let's see ah so we need to
move that into
here and let's
see yeah so we just need to change the
name space here and hopefully that fixes
things okay good and then what we can do
is we can create a backup of our uh
editor so we can call the backup
method and then let's change the uh
title to
test and then let's also back up the
editor okay so here we are backing up a
sort of blank editor and then we are
backing up uh the editor where the title
is Chang change to
test uh and
then we can change the uh let's change
the
content
to hello there my name is
Dan and then we can back up
again and then we'll change the title to
my momentos why not
okay so now let's actually log out what
the uh title of the editor
is and let's also log the
content okay so let's actually just
check what is going on
here so we can see the title is what we
last changed the title to which is this
the life of a Dev which is correct and
the content is hello there my name is
Dan so this is correct um and now what
we can do let's test out our undo
functionality so let's call history.
backup and uh sorry history. undo
and let's actually log the uh title and
the content here after
undoing so let's see what we got
here okay so the title is now test but
the content has remained the same so is
this correct so the last thing we did is
we updated the title uh from test to the
life of a Dev so the title should be
test and the content should remain the
same as hello there my name is Dan so
that is correct so that's working
correctly the state has been restored uh
to its previous state and that is
working perfectly uh let's also test out
our history show history function so if
this was I don't know a web browser I
guess this would allow us to view the
list of uh histories I
guess or a list of web pages that we
have visited and you can see here the
backups that we have of our
editor uh or our list of momentos uh we
can see here we have one where the title
is test and one where the title is blank
so this is working pretty good and
finally let's call uh undo
again and then log out the
values and we can see the title is test
and the content has gone from uh this to
nothing which is correct and then I
guess if we do it one more more time we
should just get a blank
document okay perfect so our solution is
working correctly so when should you use
the momento pattern so the momento
pattern can be used when you want to
produce a snapshot of a of an object
State and to be able to restore the
object to a previous state it's a
commonly used pattern for implementing
the undo feature and so provides a
common solution that a team of
developers can quick
understand and get on the same page with
so what are some pros and cons of the
momento pattern so one of the pros is
that you can simplify uh the originator
code which in our case was the editor
class uh by letting the caretaker or the
history class maintain the history of
the originator State satisfying the
single responsibility principle and this
kind of makes our code more easy
or easier to understand uh and and
improves the readability and also means
that
um uh our classes have sort of less
reasons to change you know uh if we need
to change the way that we store history
then we just need to update the history
class we don't need to touch the editor
class and uh one of the cons of this
momento uh pattern is that it can
consume a lot of uh RAM or random Access
Memory if lots of momentos are created
so if we have to create uh thousands of
momentos and potentially each momento
could be storing a large amount of data
for example if we wanted to uh restore a
video to a previous state if we had some
sort of video editor application then
taking a backup of an a whole video
would consume a lot of ram so taking
lots of momentos of this would be uh
potentially very bad because it could uh
slow down the application or cause it to
crash so um there are other design
patterns that can be used to restore
States uh if um the momento pattern is
causing uh too much RAM to be consumed
the state pattern allows an object to
behave differently depending on the
state that it is currently in so say
that you are writing a BL post using the
popular content management system
WordPress and the documents or post can
be in one of three states so it can be
in draft moderation or under review by
an admin or it can be published and
there are also three types of user roles
within WordPress there are readers that
can only read uh posts there are editors
that can read or edit posts and there
are admins that can read edit
or uh create new posts or delete posts
and only admins can publish documents
okay so if a post is under moderation
then only an admin can publish uh that
document or that post I should
say so first of all we're going to
create a simple solution that uses if
else uh if else conditional statements
to check the current state of the
document to see whether the state of the
documents should be upgraded so first
first of all we're going to create an
enom called document states which is
going to store all of the uh possible
States for our document or our
post and we're going to have a draft
State a moderation
State and a published
State and we're also going to create an
enor to store our possible user roles
and we have readers uh
editors and
admins okay so now I'm going to create
uh the document
class or the post
class and in here we are going to store
a uh the current document uh state
okay so this is going to be oftype
document
states which means that it's going to be
one of these uh values either draft
moderation or
published
and this is going to be a property so
we're going to give it a getter and a
Setter and we're going to do the same
for user the user role okay so the
current user role
okay so now what we're going to do is
we're we're going to create our uh
publish method so let's create
that and this publish method is
essentially uh responsible for updating
or upgrading the state of the document
to the next state so what we're going to
do is we're going to write some
conditional statements here so we're
going to check if the
state is
in a draft
State then we are going to upgrade the
state to document states do moderation
okay so we're going to upgrade from
draft to moderation the next or sort of
Step Up where the admin can uh review
the um the state of the
document
else else if the state
is equal to the document states.
moderation so if we are currently in
moderation State then we need to check
the user roles because only admins can
publish a document from uh moderation to
published so we here we can say
if you kidding me
keyboard's
locked what are you
doing okay so here we can say if current
user
role is equal to user
roles do
admin we can set the state of the
document to
published okay otherwise we do nothing
so if the current user is not an admin
then they cannot upgrade the state of
the document from this moderation state
so we do nothing and then what we can
say is
else
if State equals document
states do
published then we can basically do
nothing
because there's no higher uh state than
published so technically we could get
rid of this uh but we'll just leave it
here so that uh it's clear that we are
doing nothing if the uh document state
is already published and one other thing
that we could also add up here uh is
that if the document state is in a draft
State then we could also check to see if
the current user role is an admin and
then just uh skip this moderation State
and go straight to published that's
something that we could do uh otherwise
um if the user is not an admin then we
go to this state so that's something
that we could do but just for Simplicity
we'll keep it as
this okay so let's actually try to use
this solution so if we go into
program.cs and we create a new
document and we will need to import this
from uh let's see should be from here
and let's um set the document state to
uh
moderation and then let's set the
current user role to admin
and we will just log the document state
okay so let's run this to see what we
have and we can see that the document
state is currently in moderation which
is correct but now if we try to publish
the
document and we log the document state
let's see what we get so the current
user role is an admin and the current
document state is in moderation so the
admin has moderated or checked that the
document is okay they've then clicked
the publish button and now the document
should be in a published state so let's
check if it is in a published
State correct so the documents has gone
from moderation to published but if we
change the user role to uh something
less than admin such as an editor
editors can't publish uh documents they
need to be checked by an admin before
being published so now we should see
that the state is uh remains in
moderation and that is correct we get
two logs of moderation so that is all
working
correctly now can you spot the problems
with the current document
class okay so if you take a look at the
document class Can you spot any issues
uh is it violating any of the solid
principles for
example so if you uh check out this
publish method we can see there's lots
of if else conditional statements right
um so what we're actually doing here is
we are violating the open closed
principle because if we add any other
states or user roles many of the
document uh classes methods such as this
publish method currently we only have
one method but a real document would
have multiple methods and we're going to
have to modify all of these methods so
if we add uh another user role we're
going to have even more IFL statements
right and this class is going to become
extremely bloated uh with all of these
if else conditional statements in every
single one of its methods pretty
much and uh yeah with more States this
class is going to become uh bloated
unwieldy and difficult to understand and
the code is very difficult to maintain
because any changes in logic may require
Changing State conditionals in every one
of this document classes methods so
let's see how we can improve on our
solution and solve some of the issues
that we encountered where by using the
state Pat so the state Pat suggests that
we should create State classes for each
possible state of the document object
now if you remember we have three
possible States uh and those were draft
moderation and published so that means
we should create three new uh classes
for each of those possible States and
extract All State specific logic out of
this document class and into these
individual State
objects the document class will then
store a reference to one of these State
classes to represent the current state
that the document is in then instead of
the document implementing State specific
behavior by itself it delegates All
State related work to the state object
that it has reference to so here is the
uml diagram that we are going to uh
Implement in code so we have a document
class which stores reference to a state
uh object and it can be uh any one of
these concrete State objects provided
that these uh concrete objects uh
implement the state interface okay so
this is going to be a an object of of
type state which can be any one of these
State concrete State objects and we're
also going to store reference to the
current user
role so uh then we just have a publish
uh method which delegates All State
related work to one of these uh concrete
State
objects so we can see here above that
document uh keeps reference to or is
composed of uh represented by this
diamond Arrow uh a state object
and notice that we are using
polymorphism as the State field uh in
the document class can be any one of the
concrete State classes so draft
moderation or published as we are coding
to an interface not concrete classes so
we are coding to the state interface not
these individual concrete classes and
that improves
flexibility in documents the published
method calls state. publish and it
delegates the work to the concrete State
object so why is this a good thing
because our solution now satisfies the
open close principle because if we want
to add a new state so a new concrete
State we create a new concrete State
class that implements the state
interface we essentially extend our code
codebase uh in other words add new
classes to our codebase without having
to modify any of the current existing
classes such as the document class and
beforehand if you remember if we added a
new state we we had to uh modify
existing code the uh methods in the
document class whereas now we just have
to extend our codebase by adding a new
class that implements the state
interface so here's how the state
pattern is represented in the gang of
four book with its abstract uh class
names so we can see here that the uh our
document class is the context object
which is composed of a state
object and then we have a load of
concrete States so let's actually now
implement this solution with the state
pattern in code okay so first of all I'm
going to create the document
class and I'm also going to create the
state interface
and the state interface uh just has a
single publish
method and if this was a uh a real
document it would have more State
dependent methods such as render but
we're just going to keep it simple for
this example with the one publish method
so I think now what I'm going to
do is I'm going to create the uh
document uh class actually create it
properly so let's uh give it a field bu
uh or property for storing the current
state of the document and we're also
going to have uh store the user roles as
well uh say so current user
role okay and then in the uh
Constructor we are going to pass the the
current user
role and this should be a type user
roles
and we're going to set the state equal
to new draft
State and we have not actually made this
uh class yet so we'll create this
shortly and in here we're going to pass
this uh document object okay so um by
default what we're saying here is that
when we create a new document the uh
sort of default initial state of the
document is just going to be the uh
draft State okay so then what we can do
is we can also set the current user
role okay so now we're going to add our
publish method
and in here we are just going to Simply
call
uh
state. publish okay so we're delegating
All State specific work to these
concrete State objects which we are
going to create uh now so let's create
the draft State first of
all and all states should implement the
state
interface okay so they all should have a
publish
method and all states also need to store
reference to the uh document object so
let's uh keep store a reference to
that and then we need a
Constructor and we can set the document
in the Constructor
so what we do here is so if we're in
draft State and the uh user uh clicks
publish okay so what we should do here
is we should uh change the state of the
document to the moderation State we
should upgrade from draft to moderation
okay so that the admin can review the
documents so what we can do here is we
can return a new moderation
State and we pass the
documents okay and we need to pass the
documents because each of these states
need to have the ability to change the
uh State field within the documents okay
so now we get a red squiggly line here
because we need to create this
moderation State object so we create a
new C Class called moderation
State and in here again we need to store
for uh reference to the
documents and we also again need to have
a
Constructor where we set uh the
documents and then remember this uh
needs to implement the state
interface and if we Implement that
interface we will need to implement a
publish method and within the publish
method we can uh add our logic so if
we're currently in moderation state so
if we have a look at the old solution we
can see that if State equals moderation
we need to check the current user
role and if the current user role is an
admin then we can upgrade the state to
published otherwise we don't do anything
so that is the logic for uh when publish
is uh
clicked uh when we are currently
in um in moderation state so what we can
do here is we can say
if
document do current user Ro equal is
equal to user roles dot
admin then we can upgrade the document
state to published
published
State and we pass the
document okay so let's now create this
published
State and in here we need to implement
the uh
State
interface and we also need the same as
before we need a reference to document
and we also need to uh initialize the
documents in the Constructor so let's do
that we can just copy and paste that in
and change the name of the
Constructor okay so what happens when uh
a user clicks publish if we are already
in the publish State well we should just
do nothing so we can just return
or we can just leave uh this blank okay
so we just do nothing basically so I'll
just write a
comment if already in published
State okay so that's pretty
straightforward uh so let's actually now
have a look how we can use this uh State
pattern solution uh but before we do
that what I'm just going to do is I'm
going to
change uh I'm just going to copy and
paste this
enom into our good Solutions
folder so let's add this in here so this
is a user rolles
enum and we can paste those
in and that should
hopefully uh enable us to
use this state solution State pattern
solution so let's see so new documents
and we need to import this so should be
that one and we're going to use user
roles
dot
editor and we're just going to log the
uh document state so dog doc.
State and then we'll publish the
documents and console
log and then we'll publish
again and log the doc.
state so let's run
this and we can see that initially we
have a draft state so that is correct
whenever we create a new document it is
in draft State and then uh the user role
for this document is an editor so when
we publish a document that is in draft
state it should then go to moderation
State and that is correct and if we
publish again uh we should stay in
moderation State because the user is not
an admin so that is all working
correctly and let's now
change the uh user role from edit
to uh admin so now we should go
initially we should have the uh draft
State then we should have moderation
State and then we should have the uh
publish State because admins can publish
documents so let's see if that
works and there we go that is all
working correctly and it's also possible
to actually change the state directly so
if we wanted to go back to draft state
we can just simply add in the draft
State like so and if we log the
state of the
document we can see here that we go back
into draft
state so now if we create any new States
we don't have to modify the document
class as its publish method is coded to
an interface and so delegates the work
to a concrete class and as you can see
here the state class is coded to an
interface not a concrete State class
which means that the document class can
use polymorphism to delegate the work to
any of the concrete State classes uh and
this gives our program good flexibility
so let's now have a look at the pros and
cons of the state patent so the state
pattern can actually be Overkill or over
engineering for example consider a
simple stock watch that has two states
so it has a running state is running or
it has a is running State equals false
so it's either running or it isn't
running it's stopped and if
um this is a very very simple uh class
and we can be pretty certain that the
stopwatch isn't going to get more
complex uh we're not going to have any
more States than either stopped or
started and so using the state pattern
and creating more classes here adds uh
unnecessary complexity so this class
even though it has a few uh conditional
statements in its click method it's
pretty straightforward and there's not
really any need to go ahead and create a
l you know separate State classes just
for this stopwatch it's pretty
straightforward as it is and there we're
not going to add any more states in the
long
run um so when to use the state pattern
so a good indication
uh that you should use the state pattern
is if you have a class that behaves
differently depending on its state and
you have a large number of conditionals
or if else statements in the methods so
like we did before in this document
class we started it started to get
pretty bloated we were having lots ofl
statements to check the current state
and then do some particular Behavior Uh
and this is a good indication that we
should abstract this um this sort of St
dependent Behavior into it into their
own uh
classes
um uh so the state pattern can be used
with uh abstract classes to reduce
duplication uh so in our case we used an
interface we use the state interface but
you could also use an you could also
have used an abstract class uh where we
kind of keep um you know maybe some
fields or a few uh methods that are sort
of shared between the concrete State
objects so it's also possible to use
abstract class uh classes to reduce uh
code uh duplication and you can also
create a hierarchy of State classes and
Abstract common code into these abstract
base
classes so the pros and cons of the
state pattern so some of the pros are
that a the state pan improves
readability and simplicity of the
context class by eliminating
conditionals it satisfies the single
responsibility principle by abstracting
state specific logic into separate
classes and it satisfies the open close
principle because we can introduce new
states without modifying existing
classes so our code is open for
extension but closed for modification
and one of the uh cons of this pattern
as we have just discussed with the
stopwatch example
is that this pattern can be Overkill if
there are only a few States or if State
logic rarely changes for example uh this
class here the strategy pattern is used
to pass different algorithms or
behaviors to an object so first let's
consider an application that stores
videos before storing a video the video
needs to be compressed using a specific
uh compression algorithm such as mov or
MP4 then if necessary uh apply and over
to the video such as black and white or
blur let's create a video storage class
to handle uh this situation so first of
all what we want to do is create some
enom for the compressor types that we
have and also for the overlays so first
of all let's create the uh
compressors and this is going to be an
enob and we have M
moov MP4
web
M and then let's create the
overlays so we're going to have another
enor for
overlays and we going to we're going to
have no
overlay uh we're going to have black and
white and we're also going to have a
blur
overlay okay and the reason we create
these enom is because it's uh it's
better than it's better practice than
using uh hardcoded values for example uh
if overlay is equal to this should be
just overlay by the way um see will it
let me if overlay is equal to mov so
this is bad practice because we're
hardcoding a literal string value into
the conditional and the reason one of
the reasons why this is a bad practice
is because let's say we want to change
the name of this extension we would then
have to search through all the code and
change the values one by one whereas if
we have an enor and we want to change
you know the name of the mov extension
to mvv for example then we can just use
our uh vs code or our text editor and we
can on Mac I can press function F2 and I
can rename to mvv M ovv for example and
that will change all through the program
okay so that's why one of the good
reasons why using an enom is good
practice
okay so now let's create our video
storage class so let's create a new
class called video
storage and a video storage class is
going to have two
Fields it's going to have a compressor
field and I'm just going to give this an
underscore because it's uh a sort of
convention in
C
and we're going to have an overlay
okay and now we need to create a
Constructor where we pass H the
compressor that we want to use and we
also pass the overlay that we want to
use but uh if the user doesn't want to
use uh any overlay what we can do is by
default provide a default overlay of
none okay so if the user doesn't Supply
an overlay when they create the video
storage object then we're just going to
apply no overlay
then in here we can just say compressor
equals compressor overlay equals overlay
so set the values of the fields and then
I'm just going to create a couple of uh
seta uh methods here so that once the
video storage object is created we can
change the uh compression algorithm or
the overlay that is used in the video
storage object to store videos so let's
uh create a gter called set compressor
and this is going to take a
compressor and we can just set the
compressor and we'll also do the same
for overlay so that the overlay can be
updated so we can uh use the same video
storage object with different uh
overlays and
compressors
okay and then we're going to create our
store method which will contain the
logic for storing a
video okay so this is going to take a
file
name and we're going to perform a check
where we check if the compressor is
equal to uh compressors do move
mov then we will have some Logic for
compressing a video using moov but of
course that's beyond the scope of this
course so we're just going to log comp
com pressing using
mov okay and then we're going to have
another
conditional if it's an
mp4 and then we can just copy this down
and say compressing using
MP4 and then we're going to have the
same kind of thing for if the video is a
web m
if the uh compression algorithm is web M
so this is all of our logic uh related
to compressing the
video and then we also need some Logic
for um applying an
overlay to uh a video so I'm just going
to write overlay logic here and then I'm
just going to copy in this uh overlay
logic to save some time so let's copy
that
in and I just need to change this
to
uh not all
capitals okay and then at the end we can
simply store the video to the file
location so we will say storing video
to uh file
name and this should be
here okay and then we can also uh uh
concatenate on the extension as well so
um
compressors uh
actually compressor
dot
um yeah it's just the compressor isn't
it
okay uh so that will give us the file
extension okay so that is our video
storage class
so let's now discuss some of the
problems with this solution so first of
all it violates the open closed
principle because adding new compression
algorithms or new
overlays means that we have to modify
the existing video storage
class uh so this working and tested code
has to be modified which risks
introducing bugs to to previous ly
working code and also developers could
get lots of merge compli uh conflicts uh
in git uh as multiple developers may
have to edit one big class for example
if one developer is working on
compression algorithms and another
developer is working on overlays then
both developers will be editing this
video storage class which means that
developers can sort of step on each
other's toes and things can get kind of
difficult to work with and messy
okay so you can also see that this is a
very bloated uh video storage class um
this method is difficult to follow even
with just three overlays and three
compressors so you can imagine the more
compressors and overlays we had the more
bloated and difficult to read this is
going to be so let's now try to solve
this problem using the strategy pattern
so the uml below shows that when we
create a video storage object we pass it
to the concrete compressor and overlay
objects that we want to use and this is
polymorphism so video storage can accept
many different forms of compressor and
overlay objects uh video storage is
composed of uh compressor and overlay
objects uh as represented by the arrow
with a diamond and there are multiple
concrete compressor and overlay
implementations that extend the
compressor
and filter interfaces
respectively so you can see here uh we
have our video storage class which is
composed of uh a compressor and an
overlay and our video storage class is
talking to or coded to an interface not
a concrete uh implementation of a
compressor or or
overlay and this uh provides us with a
lot of flexibility because we can very
easy IL swap out um the compressor that
the video storage is using or the
overlay as long as they implement the
compressor or overlay
interfaces okay so this is the strategy
pattern and now I'm going to show you
how it looks with the abstract class
names from the gang of four
book so you can see that our video
storage class is known as the
context and the context is composed of
or stores a reference to a strategy okay
and the strategy is represented by an
interface and then we have concrete
strategies um each with some sort of
method okay so if we have a look at our
our solution our video storage is the
context which has a reference to uh a
strategy and currently we have two
different types of strategy in our video
storage class we have compressor and
overlay Strat IES or algorithms I guess
you could call them and then we have our
concrete strategies which um Implement
these imp
interfaces okay and you can see here uh
in the context or in the video storage
uh class when we call one of the methods
we we are now delegating work to a
concrete strategy okay rather than
actually doing the logic uh within the
uh context object itself with all the if
uh else conditional statements we can
just simply delegate the work to the
concrete strategy
object so let's let's now implement this
in
code so first of all let's create the
interfaces for our two strategies uh our
two strategies being the compressor and
the overlay so I'm just going to create
a new uh folder here called uh good
example using the uh strategy uh design
pattern and in here what I'm going to do
is I'm going to create a compressor
interface called I
compressor and in C it's generally
considered good practice to start
interfaces with with the letter I so
prefix with the letter I so that it's
clear that it's an interface and not
just a class and in here we're going to
have a single method called compress
which returns void and then we're going
to create another
interface called I
overlay and this is going to have a
single method called
apply okay so now we have our interfaces
or our
strategy um interfaces we can create the
concrete um our concrete strategy object
uh classes and we have two strategies so
we're going to need two sets of concrete
uh strategy objects or
classes uh first of all let's start with
the
compressors so I'm going to create a new
C Class called
compressor
mov and this needs to implement the I
interface and then we can implement this
interface and what we're going to do is
we're just going to
log uh
compressing video using
mov okay and then we're going to do the
same for MP4 and webm so let's quickly
do that so we can say compressor
MP4 and I'm just going to copy this in
to save some
time so it needs to implement the I uh
compressor into
face and then we can have our compress
function uh
method and then we're going to do the
same for compressor web m
okay so those are our concrete
compressors we can now create our
concrete overlay
strategies so first of all let's create
the black and
white and this needs to implement the I
overlay
interface and we can Implement that
and here we can just put
applying black
and white inter
overlay okay and then we also need a
overlay for the blur strategy
and then we need
a uh and then let's actually call this
make sure that we prefix with compressor
and the reason I like to do this is
because then uh they all kind of Stay
Together in vs code so let's just change
the name of
this and we just need our compressor for
uh sorry overlay for
none actually this should be overlay
sorry
apologies and let's make sure this is
correct okay and yeah what do we doing
here so this should be I
overlay okay so let's change this to
apply get rid of this
okay so that is correct and now we need
our uh no
overlay uh
class so overlay
none and this should be I
overlay Implement
and not applying overlay
okay so now we need to create our uh
video uh storage class so what I'm going
to do is I'm going to copy and paste the
class from here and then we're going to
refactor this class uh to make it uh
sort of satisfy the strategy pattern so
let's create a new class called video
storage and I'm just going to paste in
what we had before
okay so how do we refactor this to uh
satisfy our uh strategy pattern well
first of all we need rather than um uh
coding to these uh enom we're going to
change this so that the compressor is
coded to uh the compressor
interface and we're going to do the same
for
overlay and we also need to update this
to I
compressor and this needs to be updated
overlay
okay
um and we also need to change this to I
compressor this should be I
overlay and now the biggest changes are
going to be in our store method So
currently all of the logic for uh
compressing a um video is stored in this
store method and also all of the logic
for applying an overlay is in here so
what we can now do is we can get rid of
all all of
this and we can delegate this work to
the concrete compressor and overlay
objects so video storage will have no
knowledge of the implementation details
of each compression and overlay
algorithm so we can say compressor do
compress and we can say
overlay do
apply okay and um in a real application
we probably need to pass the file name
to uh the the this compress method and
also the apply method so it you know can
get or maybe pass a video object
something like that but for now we're
just going to keep things simple and
we're just going to call the compress
and apply uh methods but as you can see
we we no longer need to check what the
compression algorithm uh should be um we
also don't need to check what the uh
overlay is that we are applying we just
simply call the compress and then uh
compress method and then we apply the
overlay so this is way way more simple
than we had
before so let's actually now have a look
at how a client would use this uh
solution so we can create a video
storage uh object
and should be this one and then we can
pass in a compressor so let's uh let's
just pass in a uh mov
compressor so we want to compress
toov and for the overlay let's do black
and
white okay so let's actually call the uh
store method
and let's pass the file name so let's
just say the file location is videos
slash uh some
movie okay and then let's see what
happens
here okay so we've compressed the video
using mov applied uh black and white
overlay and then the video has been
stored okay so that's good and
uh because we um added seta uh methods
onto the video storage uh
class so if I just go back into here we
can see we we added set compressor and
set overlay methods so that allows us to
uh change
the
um compressor or the overlay that we use
uh within the video storage class we
don't have to create a new video storage
object just to use a different
compressor for example so say we wanted
to use a MP4 this time and the overlay
we wanted no overlay so if we just said
overlay
none uh oops sorry this should be just
the compressor and then we can call
video storage.
set
overlay and pass overlay
none and then and we call video
storage.
store and then we pass some uh location
videos some movie we can actually uh
compress and O set an overlay for the
same video but we can use a different
compression algorithm and a different
overlay just by calling these set
methods okay so these seta methods give
us a little bit more sort of flexibility
with the way that we use the video
storage uh
object
okay so so this is great so this
solution follows the open closed
principle for example to create a new uh
compressor so a new concrete
compressor um we simply create a new
class that extends the I compressor
interface uh which is
this and our code is extended so our
code base is extended meaning that we've
just added a new class and not modified
meaning that we we don't have to uh
modify any existing classes to add a
compressor and same for overlay so now
we can just extend our code base so we
can add a new overlay or add a new
compressor and we don't have to modify
any existing code
to to do that so you may be wondering
what is the difference between the
strategy and state pattern because the
two patterns probably seem quite similar
to you and the truth is the two patterns
are actually similar and the difference
between them varies depending on who you
ask and some popular answers uh to this
question are that states store a
reference to the context object that
contains them whereas strategies do not
states are allowed to replace themselves
in other words to change the state of
the context object to something else
while strategies are not and strategies
only handle a single specific task while
states provide the underlying
implementation for everything or almost
everything that the context object does
so when should you use the strategy
pattern A good rule of uh thumb for when
it might be a good time to reach for the
strategy pattern is when you have a
class with a large number of conditional
statements the switch between variants
of the same algorithm so in our video
storage class um we saw that there were
a large number of conditional statements
that switch between variants of the same
algorithm so the algorithm being a
compression algorithm and the variance
being uh mov or
MP4 and uh we could see that by
switching to the strategy pattern we got
rid of all of those uh kind of bloated
messy conditional statements
and the algorithm logic can be extracted
into separate classes that implement the
same interface and that is what we did
with our solution we extracted the
compression logic as well as the overlay
logic into separate classes that
implemented either a compressor or
overlay
interface and the context object in our
case the video storage class then
delegates the work to these classes
instead of implementing all of the
algorithms itself so the pr pros and
cons of the strategy pattern so the pros
it satisfies the open close principle
because we can add new strategies
without modifying the context or class
and we can swap algorithms used inside
an object at runtime so it provides lots
of
flexibility uh and some of the cons of
the strategy pattern are that clients
have to be aware of the different
algorithms and select the appropriate
one so in our program.cs file we had to
pass the uh appropriate well we had to
pass the strategy uh the compression
algorithm or the overlay object that we
wanted to
use and if you only have a few
algorithms that rarely change then using
the strategy pattern may be over
engineering because we're creating uh
potentially lots of new classes um and
it's not really necessary if there are
only a few algorithms that aren't going
to be changing often the iterator
pattern provides a way of iterating over
an object without having to expose the
object's internal structure which may
change in at some point in the future so
changing the internals of an object
should not affect its
consumers so this probably doesn't make
too much sense to you so let me show you
what this means with an example so here
we have a shopping list class which
stores a list of items
and we have a push method to add an item
onto the list a pop method to re uh
remove the last item on the list and
then return it and we have a get list uh
method which Returns the whole shopping
list and as you can see here the list
the shopping list is of type list it is
a list data structure and each item in
the list is of type string so let's
actually use this shopping list in our
Pro program.cs file so I'm just pasting
in here where uh to create a new
shopping list called list and then we're
just pushing a a few items onto the list
so milk bread and
steak and now what we want to do is I
want we want to Loop over each item in
the shopping list and log each of the
items so we can create a for Loop
starting from
zero and uh the loop will keep running
until as long as the
list as long as I is less than the uh
list
length and we can call count on here so
uh let's see list.get list.
count and we want to increment I by
one so this is giving us an
error cannot convert type in to BU so
this should be be uh as long as I is
less
than the uh length of the shopping list
okay so this is going to Loop over each
item in the shopping list and increment
I by uh one each time so let's have a
look at each item in the list and we can
do that by um
saying
list do get list
and we can um access the
uh the nth or the e in this case uh item
in the
list and then we're just going to log
this
item okay so let's run this program and
see what we get returned and as you can
see we have milk bread and steak as
expected so this looks like a decent
solution uh however there is one problem
and uh the clue if I give you a clue
what the problem could be it's this
sentence here so changing the internals
of an object should not affect its
consumers so if we change the internals
of the shopping list object meaning we
change something within the shopping
list class then it should have no effect
on its consumers and currently this uh
program . CS uh main method is a
consumer of shopping list okay so uh let
me show you what the issue actually is
so if we changed the data
structure inside of shopping list uh to
a fixed length array so if we just
comment this out for now and then we say
uh private string so a string
array list equals
new
string array and it's a fixed length
array of 50 items long so if we change
the data structure used to uh store uh
shopping list
items and then let's just say that we
updated all of these methods to uh push
pop and return the list okay we're not
going to do that for now because uh we
we don't really need to but if we go
into our program
CS then it would actually cause an error
because uh fixed length arrays do not
have a count field and currently uh
list. Gat list uh inside of our shopping
list would return a a fixed length array
okay it wouldn't return a list and a
fixed length array does not have a count
field so therefore it would cause an
error it would cause our program to
break
uh in in this consumer it affects this
consumer so by changing the internals of
the shopping list object it would affect
its consumers any consumer that is
iterating over the list will
break so uh we can fix this by using the
iterator pattern so we can use the
iterator pattern to ensure that changing
the internals for example changing the
list data structure doesn't affect any
of its consumers so we can do this by
adding some methods to the shopping list
class to allow iterating over a shopping
list without uh knowing about its
internal
representation so here we have a uml
diagram of the shopping list class and
we can see that we still have our push
and pop methods but we've added some
extra methods to allow iterating over a
shopping list
and you can see here we have a next uh
method a current method and a has next
method so with what we've done here is
we've added these three new method
methods to help consumers to iterate
over the uh
list uh data structure or the or just
the object itself without having to have
any knowledge of the internal data
structures so the next method goes to
the next item in the list the current
method Returns the current item and the
has next method checks if there is
another item in the list and with this
structure we don't know the internal
representation of the list object so if
we change the data structure used in
shopping list to store items its
consumers wouldn't break or need to be
changed we'd just have to perhaps update
the iterator methods to account for the
new data
structure so the problem with the the
above shopping list class is that it
violates the uh solid single
responsibility principle because
shopping list is now responsible for
list management using push and pop and
it's also responsible for iteration
using next current and has next so to
follow the single responsibility
principle we can put the iterator
methods into a new class and that class
can be called
iterator okay and as you can see the
shopping list has a dependency on
iterator and as you can see here we also
have a method inside of our shopping
list class called create iterator and
the create iterator method returns an
instance of iterator that allows
consumers to iterate over shopping lists
without knowing its internal
details however we have another problem
because if the data structure inside of
shopping list changes then we will need
a different iterator to manage it so
iterator needs to be an interface and
then we can have concrete classes for
each data structure that implements
iterator to ensure that they contain the
iterator methods the correct iterator
methods and the interface determines the
capabilities that we need from a real
concrete iterator so the data structures
could be an array a list a stack Etc so
here is our uml representation we have
our shopping list which has a create
iterator method uh which returns a it an
iterator uh an we have an iterator
interface here and iterators should have
a next current and has next method and
then we have our concrete
representations of iterators and each
concrete
iterator uh can be used to iterate over
specific data structures in this case we
have a list iterator for iterating over
lists and an array iterator for
iterating over
arrays so we can see here that shopping
list has a dependency to the iterator
interface uh as we discussed because the
create iterator uh method returns an
object of type iterator and the concrete
iterator classes extend
iterator and Implement its
methods so here's how how the solution
uh looks using the gang of four abstract
class names so we uh have a collection
uh class which uh contains the create
iterator method and obviously this is
our our shopping list class in our
example we have the iterator interface
okay and create iterator returns an
object of type iterator
and then we have our concrete uh
iterators okay so now uh let's implement
this in code so let's now implement the
uh shopping list using the iterator
pattern so I've created a good example
folder here and I've copy and pasted the
shopping list from earlier into this new
folder and we're going to refactor this
to uh satisfy the iterator pattern so
first of all what we need to do is
create an interface
uh for the iterators so I'm going to
call this I
iterator and this needs three methods so
we need a method called
next uh we need a has next method which
has a return type of
Boolean and we also need a current
method which Returns the current item in
the loop So
currently um
this current uh method only works with
strings and current that's fine for our
shopping list because we have a list of
strings however what if we wanted to
Loop over a list of orders or customers
or integers so this iterator uh
interface isn't very flexible it can
only work with lists of
strings so what we can actually do to
make this more flexible is use a generic
type and pass this uh to the current uh
method and if this doesn't make sense to
you it will make more sense when we use
this uh I iterator interface uh
shortly so what we now need to do is
create our concrete iterator classes so
we're actually going to create these as
nested classes inside of this shopping
list
class
um so let's create a a uh nested uh
iterator and I'll explain why this is
nested uh soon so we're going to create
a private class called list iterator and
this is uh a concrete class which is uh
going to iterate over lists so currently
that's what we are rep that's the data
structure that we are using for our
list and this needs to implement the I
iterator interface and we can just pass
a string data type to that now as you
can see we get an error because we
haven't implemented this interface so
let's do that and let's now
um um create some fields in this
concrete uh iterator object so we're
going to have a shopping
list uh
field because that's what we are looping
over and we will also have a uh an index
so the current position in the
loop and then we also need a
Constructor which takes a shopping
list and we assign it to the shopping
list
field okay so now let's update our
current method so this should return the
current item in the uh
list so we can
return the shopping
list do
list and then we can uh just pass the
index like so and this will return the
item at the current index in the loop
and then
next uh let's implement this next
uh method so all next needs to do is
increment the index by one so we can
just say index equals index +
one and then the H next
method needs to check if we are
basically at the end of the list so we
can
return uh index is less than shopping
list. list. count
and here we do have access to the uh
count field because we know that we are
iterating over a uh list because this is
an A List iterator okay so we just need
to put colod one there
okay so this is all looking
okay and then in
the uh in our shopping list class we
just need to do one more thing and that
is is to create a new method called
create iterator which is going to return
the correct iterator okay so in this
case we need a list iterator because we
are using a data type of
list so let's uh create this method and
this has a return type of iterator which
allows us to use uh multiple different
types of concrete iterators so we can
return any concrete iterator and it
isn't going to cause our clients to
break so here we're going to pass a
string because we are iterating over
strings and we can call this create
iterator and this needs to return new
list
iterator and we pass the current uh
shopping list okay so um
that is all looking good so let's
actually test this solution
out so uh we are no longer going to need
this so let's remove that and let's
create our new iterator so we can say I
iterator uh in fact let's just do this
we can say VAR
iterator equals
um hold on a second
so okay so we can say V iterator equals
uh list. create iterator so now we have
our
iterator and now what we can do is we
can create a while loop so we can say
while the iterator has
next we we can um console uh
write iterator do current so get the
current item in the uh iteration cycle
and then we just call the iterator do
next uh method to it to go to the next
uh item in the list so let's log this
out and as you can see we still get milk
bread and steak as we would expect and
and the advantage of this is now we can
safely change the data structure in
shopping list and the code in all of our
consumers will still run because if you
look at our shopping list currently we
have a list of strings but if we change
this to a fixed length uh array we could
create a new class called uh fixed
length array iterator which implements
the I
iterator uh interface
and it provides these
methods and then in our program.cs file
this would still work because we're just
interacting with the methods that are
specified on this interface so because
we are effectively coding to an
interface we now don't have to worry
about the specific internals of the
object that we are iterating over so
when should you use the iterator pattern
so it's a good idea to employ the
iterator pattern when you're collect
possesses a complex internal data
structure or a data structure that is
likely to change so that clients can
iterate over the collection without any
knowledge of the data structure so if
the internal data structure uh of an
object or of a of a class changes then
it shouldn't affect the clients so what
are the pros and cons of the iterator
pattern so one of the pros is that it
satisfies the single responsibility
principle because the traversal logic is
abstracted into a separate class or
separate classes and it also satisfies
the open close principle because you can
create new Collections and iterators
without breaking the code that uses them
and one of the cons of the uh iterator
pattern is that it can be over
engineering if your app only works with
simple
collections the command pattern is a
behavioral design pattern that
encapsulates a request as an object
object allowing you to parameterize
clients with cues requests or operations
it enables you to decouple the sender
from the receiver and provides
flexibility in the execution of commands
and supports undoable operations so that
probably makes absolutely no sense so
let's uh make it make sense by going
through an example so we're going to
create a remote control that is
connected to a light that can either
either be switched on or off so first of
all let's create the
light so this is going to be a standard
class with two methods and it's going to
be uh one method called turn
on and we're just going to log uh light
is
on and then we're going to create a
another method called turn
off and we're just going to log light is
off
okay so this is the receiver class this
is receiving
um from the uh remote okay and then
we're going to create the remote control
class okay so this is going to be like
our invoker class this is invoking some
command uh to the light which is
receiving the command so so in here our
remote control is going to store a uh
reference uh to the
light and we will set the light in the
Constructor and then we're going to have
a method called press button so it's
going to be a very simple remote with
one button for now
and this is going to have uh one
parameter which is a Boolean and this is
whether if it's true then we want to
turn the light on if it's false then we
are going to turn the light off so we're
just going to have a simple if statement
so if turn
on then we will call the turn on method
on the light
otherwise we just turn the light
off and let's now have a look at how a
client would use this
solution so in remote control we pass
the light object that we want to control
okay and then we can call remote control
do press button and if we pass true we
should turn the light on and if we pass
false we should turn the light off so
let's run this
program and we can see that we got light
is on and then light is off okay but
there actually uh are some issues with
this solution so in this example there
are control
class uh directly calls methods on the
concrete light uh object okay so we pass
a light object to the remote control and
we are directly uh calling methods on
this concrete light class because here
we can see we're calling light turn on
and light turn off so this direct
coupling between remote control and
light makes it challenging to extend the
functionality or introduce new commands
without modifying the remote control uh
class so for example uh suppose that we
want to add the functionality to dim the
light in addition to being able to turn
the light on and off so if we were to uh
continue with this implementation then
we would need to modify the remote
control class directly uh so to if we
wanted to add a method to dim the light
then we would need sorry if we wanted to
add functionality to uh be able to dim
the light light then we need to edit
this remote control class for example
we'd create a method called uh dim
light
and we would call light. Dim light for
example this doesn't exist at the moment
but this is you know
something uh what we what we could do so
this actually uh violates the uh solid
open close principle and it makes it
challenging to extend the functionality
without having to modify existing code
and as you've already seen multiple
times by now this isn't ideal so here is
the uml for our current solution so we
have a remote control which is composed
of a light uh
object and it's tightly coupled to this
concrete light object because it's
calling uh methods
directly uh that are contained within
this light
object um so light is tightly coupled to
remote control if we want to add new
features then we have to modify uh
remote
control so let's have a look at how we
can improve this solution and make it
satisfy the open close principle so that
we don't have to uh modify existing code
to add new features we can ideally just
create some new class or extend our code
base so we have a look at the command
pattern
uml we can see here that rather than
having remote control talk directly to
the light uh object object instead we
can pass a command to remote control and
then whenever the uh button is pressed
we can simply call command. execute and
we can see here that this command is an
interface so the remote control is now
talking to an interface rather than
concrete objects and this provides us
with a lot of flexibility because now we
can create multiple uh concrete commands
and we can pass any of those commands as
long as it implements this command
interface to the remote control and the
remote control needs no knowledge of the
specific uh command that it is working
with okay and then we can see here that
the commands have an association
relationship to light so that they can
interact with the light so for turnon it
just needs to call the light. turn on
method so using the command pattern we
can decouple remote control so this is
the sender class from the light class
which is the receiver and then to add
new functionalities such as dimming the
light we can extend our code Base by
adding a new dim command without having
to modify the remote control class so if
we created a dim class we could then in
the client just pass this command to
remote control without having to modify
the remote control
and the remote control is composed of a
command as we just discussed and the
concrete commands turn on and turn off
Implement command and store a reference
to light so let's Implement our remote
control and light uh sort of example
using the command pan so I've created a
new folder called good light for so
we're going to use the command pattern
here so this is going to be like a good
example and first of all we're going to
create the command interface so let's
create a new interface called I command
and this is going to have a single
method called
execute and we are also now going to
create our remote control
class and our remote control class or
our invoker class is now going to store
a reference to a command so it's going
to be composed of a command object and
we're going to code to an interface here
so that we can use
polymorphism and we're going to pass a
command in the into the
Constructor
okay uh and then what we're going to do
is we're also going to add a uh set
command method so this is going to allow
the uh client
to swap commands at
runtime so we're going to create a
public void method called set command
and this is going to take a command
object so any command object any command
that implements the I command interface
and here we can just set the
command and we're also going to uh have
our uh press button uh
method and now all we have to do is call
the execute uh method on the command
object and this will execute whatever
whatever command we have passed to our
remote
control okay so let's now create the
receiver or the light uh
class and this is pretty much the same
as we had before so I'm just going to
copy those methods
in so you can see here we have a turn on
turn off and I've also added a dim
method so that we can now dim the light
as
well uh and now we can create our
concrete commands so let's go ahead and
do that um so let's first of all create
a turn on
command and this is going to implement
the I command
interface so so if we implement this
interface we have our execute method
and uh what we need to do here is we
need to store a reference to the object
that we are kind of controlling and in
this case it is the light uh class so
let's add that
in and then we can pass that uh into the
Constructor
okay and uh the light here this light
field can only be uh set in the
Constructor we're not going to add any
Setter methods uh so uh basically a
command is a mutable so meaning that it
can't be changed uh once it is created
and for our execute method we can now
simply just call the turn on method on
the light uh object
okay so let's also create our turnoff
command so again we're going to
implement the I command
interface okay and it's going to be
pretty similar to the turn uh off
command
so sorry the turn on
command and let's copy that in and we
just need to change this to turn off so
we pass a light object into the
Constructor of the turnoff command and
let's also create our dim
command and again it's going to be
pretty similar so but we just need to
rename the
Constructor and we also need to
implement the I command
interface and call
light.
dim okay pretty
straightforward uh so let's now have a
look at how a client would use this
solution so if we go into
program.cs and create a
light and let's also create our remote
and actually we don't need to import
that so it's seeing here we as you can
see here it's telling us that we need to
pass uh some command object so initially
I think it's a good idea to actually
turn on the light so let's pass the turn
on command and we also need to pass the
light to the
command okay and now let's press the
button so if we press the button we've
passed a turn on command so the remote
is just going to execute
this turn on command so let's call the
press
button and if we run
this you can see that we got the light
is on so the light is being switched
on and now if we want to say uh dim the
light so it's too bright we can call
remote. set command and we can pass the
dim
command and then if we press the
button and run
this we can see that we get the light is
dim okay so we have lots lots of
flexibility now in in in terms of what
command we use and whenever we want to
uh create a new uh command or new
functionality for our remote we can
simply extend our code Base by creating
a new concrete command class without
having to touch our invoker class or our
uh remote
class the command pattern is also
commonly used in UI Frameworks
especially for handling user
interactions with buttons or menu items
uh each button or menu item can be
associated with a specific command
object allowing the framework to execute
the appropriate action when the user
interacts with the UI elements and this
decouples the UI components from the
actual operations that they perform form
which provides F uh flexibility and
maintainability in UI development
Additionally the command pattern
facilitates features such as undo or
redo functionality and event loging in
UI applications so here's how a UI
framework that implements the uh command
pattern M look so above this green line
we have the
framework and we have a button class
which is like our invoker and this is
composed of a command and you can see
the button or the UI component is
talking to the command interface not a
concrete uh command class or and it's
also not talking directly to the
receiver
so um we also have our concrete commands
here so we currently we just have an add
user command but we could also have
things like delete user or update user
and then this talks to a user service
which actually performs the uh business
logic related to adding a user so the
framework would be the code that you
couldn't edit so for example some a UI
package and the app part is the part
that you would create so the so custom
code your actual app that you are
building and you will create concrete
commands that extend the command
interface uh that that is found in the
UI package and your concrete commands
keep a reference to a class that
contains the B business logic as we
discussed
such as a user service and this contains
the methods related to adding updating
or deleting users so this is going to be
uh maybe interacting with your
database uh a simpler solution so if we
didn't use the command pattern uh and
and we sort of come up with a sort of
more obvious solution uh and this would
be to create a load of button subclasses
uh for each place where a button is used
and these subclasses would contain the
code uh that should happen when the
button is clicked so here we have some
sort of abstract button class this might
be from uh maybe the UI framework and
then our code uh or in our application
we would then create a load of button
subclasses uh where each subass contains
the logic that should happen when for
example a button is clicked and the
problem with this approach is that we
could end up with a huge number of
subclasses and this would be okay if
there was no risk of breaking the code
in these sub classes every time that the
base button class is modified uh but if
we update our UI library and that
includes a breaking change to the button
class then it could break all of our
button subclasses so this is a very uh
fragile solution and also uh some
operations such as copy need to be
called from multiple places for example
a user can click the copy button uh
press contrl C or right click click and
then select copy from a context menu um
with this solution we'd either have to
duplicate the copy logic in multiple
places uh or make
shortcuts and context menus dependent on
buttons which is a very bad solution so
the command pattern solves this issue by
essentially breaking the app into layers
following the good software design
principle called the principle of
separation of concerns so the command
pattern has broke the app into two
layers we have the guei and the business
logic and the guei is responsible for
rendering things on the screen capturing
user input and showing results then when
it comes to the important stuff such as
validating the info from a contact form
and sending an email the guei delegates
that task to the underlying layer of the
business
logic so if we have a look at the gang
of for uml you can see here that we have
a our light class or our sort of button
class this will be called the invoker
class in the gang of for book we then
have our Command interface with some
sort of execute uh method and we usually
I think have a single execute method in
the sort of command interface then each
command will uh implement this command
interface uh and have a execute command
and then we have a receiver uh where the
the concrete commands sort of delegate
the work to this receiver class and we
can see that the invoker is completely
decoupled from the receiver and this
provides us with lots of flexibility
because we can now use polymorphism to
pass different command objects to the
invoker and the invoker needs no
specific knowledge of the command that
it that it's being passed another
advantage of the command pattern is that
it gives us the ability to implement
undo functionality so for example say we
have a text editor like VSS code that
allows the user to highlight some text
then the user could click a button and
make uh make some text in the HTML
document italic which just means uh
slanted so here we have the uml diagram
uh for implementing uh this undo
functionality so above we create a new
interface called undoable command which
extends the command interface and this
is because all undoable commands are
still commands they're just special
types of commands that can execute both
forwards uh or backwards with the
execute and onexecute command uh methods
so why not add the onexecute method to
the command interface itself uh well
it's because not every command is
undoable for example making text italics
is undoable but saving a document or
zooming in or out is not and if you can
remember the uh solid interface
segregation principle it basically
States that uh classes should not be
forced to implement methods that they do
not need so it's much better to create
this separate undoable command interface
so we then Implement uh these methods in
the concrete command classes so for
example here we have an italic command
which implements both the execute and
unexecuted methods from the undoable
command
interface okay so we can also use use
the momento pattern which we discussed
earlier to implement undo mechanisms but
what's the difference between momento
and the command pattern when it comes to
undo operations so with the momento
pattern if you can remember we store the
changes in the state of an object so in
other words we store multiple snapshots
of the state over time and sometimes
storing these snapshots can be expensive
for example videos are Lar files that
take up lots of memory and in those
situations it's better to use the
command pan because every command knows
how to undo itself so we don't have to
store multiple snapshots of an object
for example think of the resize
operation if a user resizes a video we
only have to store the previous
dimension of that video we don't have to
store the entire snapshot of the video
object so here's how we will implement
the command pattern with with undo
capability so here we have some slightly
confusing
uml uh but we have a an undo command uh
a new class called undo command that we
have created to handle all undo
operations so the way this works is that
it pops the last command from history
and then calls the onexecute method on
that command as all commands know how to
onexecute themselves so this is kind of
confusing to talk through and just look
at the diagram so it's going to make
much more sense when we go through this
in code so let's do that okay so I have
created here a an
undoable um folder where we're going to
uh put our code solution in here so
first of all let's create a HTML
document
class so in this class this is where we
are going to implement our business
logic so this class will know nothing
about uh commands it simply TS it's
simply the business layer of our
application okay so let's first of all
uh create a uh property for the content
of the HTML
document and we will have a getter and a
Setter and we'll also include here now a
public void make italic
method and this is how where we're going
to have our business logic so so
basically the HTML document knows how to
make itself bold so what we can do in
here is we can set the content equal to
uh the content wrapped in HTML italic
attacks
okay like
so so what we will do next is we will
create the command interface with the X
cute
method and we'll also create the
undoable command interface which uh
extends the command
interface and this extends
command Okay so that means that it gains
the execute method from command and we
will also add an onexecute
method
and um undoable command extends command
which means that every undoable command
is actually also a command object okay
so next up we're going to Comm create
our Command history class which is going
to which is a class that's going to keep
track of of the commands that we've
applied so let's create that class
called
history and in here we're going to store
a uh list of undoable
commands and we'll just call this
commands and we will set it equal to a
new
list and then we're going to create a
push method so we're going to create a
few method methods which will allow us
to easily interact with the uh history
class so we'll create a method called
public void
push and this is going to take an
undoable
command and we can just call
commands. add
command and we'll also create a pop
method for removing the last item on the
uh uh commands
list and this returns that last
item so we get the last command from the
list then we remove it from the
list and then finally we return it okay
so we pop it off the list and remove it
from the list then we return that last
item and we're also going to have a
method called uh size for getting the
current length of the uh commands list
and this is going to be useful in
another class uh a little bit later on
so let's create
this and we just want to return
uh commands.
count okay so what we're going to do
here with this size method is we just
simply uh check that we have some
commands in the commands list and if we
do then you know we can onexecute them
for example so that's why we are using
this we're sort of adding in this size
method
so what we can do now is we can create
our concrete italic command uh class so
let's go ahead and create a new class
called italic
command and this needs to implement the
undoable command
interface so let's Implement that
interface so we have an execute method
and an
unexecuted some Fields up here so we
need to store reference to the HTML
document
so let's um sort of reference to that we
also
need um a field for the previous
content and we'll initialize that to an
empty
string and we also need to store
reference to the history
object okay so we're going to need to to
create a Constructor now to set these
values and what we need to do is we need
to pass the history object as
well
okay and then we can IM uh Implement our
execute and
unexecuted what we want to do is we need
to get the current content in the HTML
document and set it to previous content
we can then uh make the document italic
and we can push uh this command object
so this command object onto the history
class okay so we are getting the uh
current content from the document
storing it into previous content we then
make the document italic and then we
push this command object onto the
history list so let's do that so we can
say previous content is equal to doc.
content and then we can say
doc. make
italic and we are
delegating this
work uh to the doc business
object okay so we're not doing this work
within the command we are delegating to
the uh document business object and then
we call history do
push and we want to push this command
onto the uh history
list now for
unexecuted all we need to do is we call
Doc do content equals previous content
okay so we go back to what the content
was before we executed the command so
that's pretty straightforward uh but
we're now going to create a a new class
called undo command and this is going to
sort of manage all of um the undoable
commands so this is going to make more
sense uh shortly so stick with me so
let's create a new class called undo
command and this is going to implement
the command
interface and what we need to do here is
we need to store dra a reference to the
history
class and we can pass this into the
Constructor so in the execute method
what we want to do is we want to check
if the history has uh any item any
commands in its list so if it does then
we can pop the last item the last
command off of the list and then we can
call its own execute method so let's do
that so we can say if
history do
size is greater than zero so if we have
any commands on the list then what we
can do is we can pop the last item off
the
list and we want it this should be
history.
poop and we can say last command.
execute uh sorry onexecute
okay so we unexecuted
command um and again here we are
delegating the uh this undo logic to the
undoable command
object so this is going to make a little
bit more sense when we actually use this
solution so let me show you how this is
used in a client so first of all let's
create a HTML
documents and let's also create our
history
object and we don't need
that and let's set the HTML documents
content equal to hello
world and let's just log what the
content
is okay so let's run this program see
what we
get and we get hello world as expected
so what we want to do next is let's try
and make the content um italic so to do
that we can create an italic command and
object and we pass in the HTML
Doc and the history object
okay we can then call the execute
command on the itell command sorry the
execute method on the itell command so
um let's actually log the content now so
we would expect this hello world to now
be wrapped in italic HTML tags so let's
run this and see what we got and as you
can see it's working correctly so it's
executed the italic command and made the
content in the HTML document italic so
the last thing we need to test out is
the undo command so what we can do here
is we can create a new undo command so
undo command equals new undo
command and in here we need to pass the
history object that we are working
with and we can
call undo command.
execute and then we can log
the uh content so we would
expect um the content now to have no
italic tags around it so you can see
here that we are back to having uh just
regular text that isn't
italics okay so that's pretty good so
you can see here let's have a look at
this undo command so undo command that
we call undo command. execute um so if
we have a look at this execute method we
are getting the last command from
history so if we have a look at our uh
history first of all we create this new
ellic command which is an undoable
command and we call execute and when we
call uh execute this command is going to
be pushed onto the uh history
class uh the history list and then when
we call the undo command it essentially
pops this uh command that we just
executed off of the history and calls
onexecute on this command to essential
uh revert the content to what it was
previously so when should you use the
command pan so you can use the command
pattern when you want to implement
reversible operations the command
pattern is probably the most popular
pattern for implementing the undo or
redo functionality and it uses less Ram
than the momento pattern which has to
back up the whole state of the object
and the command pattern is great when
you want to cue operations or schedule
their execution as command objects can
be serialized which just means
converting the objects into Strings and
then you can store them in databases or
send them over networks then at a later
time these can be converted back into
objects and executed so what are the
pros and cons of the command
pan so first of all it's satisfies the
single responsibility Principle as
classes that invoke operations are decou
coupled from classes that perform these
operations it also satisfies the open
close Principle as new commands can be
added to the code base without having to
modify existing
code uh one of the uh negatives or cons
of the command pattern is that code can
become more complex as you're adding a
new layer between senders and receivers
so if your program is fairly simple uh
with not too many uh operations
then using the command pattern can be
Overkill or over engineering the
template method allows you to define a
template method or skeleton for an
operation the specific steps can then be
implemented in sub classes so suppose we
are designing some software that will be
installed on a machine that makes hot
beverages at the beginning we just had
tea and coffee but after some feedback
from customers we needed to add some
more beverages such as calt
so we started out pretty simple making a
separate class for each hot beverage but
the number of beverages but as the
number of beverages grows we see a lot
of code
duplication uh so if we have a look at
this uh example here we have um tea
coffee and chamomile each with a make
beverage method and we can see inside of
the make beverage method we are calling
the boil water method and a pour into
cup method and these uh methods are
actually uh or these steps are used in
tea coffee and chamomile in fact they're
used in all beverages all hot beverages
require Bo boiling water and pouring
that water into a cup uh but we also
have some methods that differ between
the different beverages for example The
Brew method uh may require different
amounts of time and the add condiments
method uh May will differ as well
because different beverages will require
different condiments for example uh tea
it might be possible to add say milk and
lemon whereas with coffee uh it may be
possible to add
cream
so uh so one of the issues is with this
solution as is is that as the number of
beverages grows we see a lot of code
duplication so we are duplicating this
boil water and pour into cup uh um uh
logic in each uh of the
Beverages and we also have no way of
ensuring that each class follows a
particular structure which means that
the client code will have have to
include lots of if else conditional
statements to pick the proper course of
action depending on the particular
beverage class so I have made a te class
and we're just going to add some methods
for uh boiling water pouring the water
into the cup and Brewing the tea so we
also need a uh method to see if the
customer wants condiments and then we
need to add those condiments to the
beverage or to the tea so let's create a
method called
uh uh called add
condiments and what we're going to do
here is we're going to check if the
customer wants condiments so we're
actually going to create a method called
customer wants
condiments and if they do then we're
just going to add some lemon to the
tea so let's create this customer once
condiments
method and this is going to be a method
that returns a Boolean value
so what we're going to do is we're going
to log to the console uh a question so
we're going to say would you like lemon
with your
te and the user is going to be able to
input yes or
no okay so now what we need to do is we
need to read the users's input from the
console so we can say console do
uh read
line okay and then we can simply return
the input
dot to
lowercase so we input uh we take the
user input so either a pro it should be
either a y or a no and we make it
lowercase and we check if it is equal to
to yes so if the user inputed y for yes
then this will return true meaning that
the customer wants condiments and so we
add some lemon to the tea okay so pretty
straightforward so now we just need to
make one final uh method and that is
going to be called make beverage
and this is where we
basically uh call all of these methods
in the correct order to make the T so
I'm just going to paste those in to save
some
time okay so we boil the water pour it
into the cup Brew the tea and then check
if the user wants condiments and if so
we add them to the tea so pretty
straightforward so let's actually go
ahead and test this out so let's clear
out our program.cs file and we're going
to create a new T OB uh
object and we're going to call t. make
beverage okay so let's see how this
works so we have boiling water pouring
water into cup Brewing tee for 3 minutes
and then it says would you like lemon
with the OT so if I UT y whoops so if I
come into the console at Y and enter
let's see what we get here okay so it
says adding lemon to the te so this is
working correctly if I say put no so n
let's see what
happens okay nothing happen so that's
perfect okay so this is working
correctly so now let's also go ahead and
create a uh coffee class for creating
coffee beverages
so okay so let's now also create a
coffee class for making coffee
so what I'm going to do is I'm just
going to paste in these methods for
making coffee just to save some time
because it's largely the same as the tea
class so as you can see we have boil
water pour water into cup so these
methods are identical to the methods in
in uh this tea class and then we have
the Brew method which Brews the coffee
for 5 minutes so slightly different to
brewing tea and we also uh have the add
condiments where rather than adding
lemon we add cream to the
coffee so we can see that we have two
methods that are identical to the ones
in
t so the issue is that the more of these
beverages that we create we're having uh
to create we're having a lot of code
duplication so there are two good ways
to solve this issue of code duplication
and they are polymorphism and
inheritance so first of all we're going
to use polymorphism which actually leads
to a design pattern that we covered
earlier so let's see if you can spot
which design pattern that is so here we
have uh our solution using
polymorphism so here we provide a common
beverage inter face to force all
concrete beverages to follow a specific
structure we then have a beverage maker
class that manages preparing the
different Beverages and this beverage
maker class includes the common
operations for making all beverages such
as boiling water and pouring it into a
cup and it also includes uh operations
specific to each beverage uh but these
operations are delegated to each of the
the concrete beverages so this beverage
maker actually talks to a or is coded to
a beverage interface meaning that we can
use polymorphism so we can pass
different concrete uh beverages into the
beverage maker and then this beverage
maker can simply call beverage. prepare
it doesn't actually care um about the
specific uh concrete be uh beverage
class that's been passed to it because
it's coded to an interface it can just
call prepare so we are essentially using
polymorphism to make things nice and
flexible and um so now when we create a
new beverage so if we get some more
feedback from a customer that we need to
uh and we want to add a new beverage we
want to start selling a new beverage
then uh we can just create a new
concrete beverage class that implements
the beverage interface okay and we only
have to include in these concrete
classes codee that is specific or unique
to that beverage because the um sort of
shared code is placed inside of this
beverage maker class so by using
polymorphism here we have inadvertently
used the strategy pattern so you can see
here this is the strategy pattern uml
where our context object is the beverage
maker and we have a strategy interface
and in our case this is the uh the
beverage interface and then our concrete
strategies or our
beverages let's now implement this
strategy pattern or polymorphism uh
solution into code so first of all I'm
going to create an interface called
beverage and I'm going to add a prepare
method
okay so now let's create our TCL class
that implements the beverage uh
interface so this beverage uh interface
is kind of like our uh command
interface uh sorry our strategy
interface okay and then we're going to
create our concrete strategies which are
basically our concrete beverage classes
so first of all let's cre create the uh
T class and this is going going to
implement the beverage
class so let's implement this uh
interface and what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to copy and paste in uh
some of the uh methods that we had
before so we had the Brew method and the
add condiments uh method and also the
customer wants condiments method so
let's add those in and these are the
kind of methods that are unique to this
specific concrete uh beverage okay so
now what we can
do is we can inside of the prepare
method we can call
brew and add
condiments okay so if you can remember
before if we go into T beforehand we we
also had a boil water and pour into cup
method before we called brew and add
condiments but now we're going to create
a separate class so that this kind of uh
these two steps can basically be shared
between all of the beverages to reduce
uh code dup uh
duplication so let's
continue and let's create a uh coffee
class so this is another sort of
concrete uh strategy uh class and this
implements our uh strategy interface
which is the beverage interface so if we
Implement that and I'm just going to
copy and paste uh The Brew add
condiments and the customer wants
condiments methods
into uh this class to save some
time
and let's see what did we do
here okay so I think that's okay
yeah okay so now in the prepare
method we can call brew
and add
condiments
okay so we can also do the uh same for
chamomile so let's create a chamomile
class so this is another uh concrete
beverage and
this needs to implement
beverage and I'm just going to uh for
for cam mile let's say chamomile is very
simple because all we really have to do
of chamomile is put the uh tea into the
cup and Brew it we don't really have to
um we don't really have to um add
condiments to C mile okay so we can just
call the Brew method so let's create a
brew method
and let's just Brew camomile for three
three
minutes okay so to prepare cam mile all
we need to do is Brew it basically uh
that's the only specific step to Camile
Brewing it for 3
minutes so now we can create our
beverage maker uh
class and this is going to contain our
sort of shared
code so first of all we need a field for
referencing the particular beverage that
we are going to be
making and this is coded to the beverage
interface allowing us to pass uh
different types of Beverage into the
beverage maker
class and then we're going to need a
Constructor where we set the beverage
and we also need a set beverage uh
method so that we can easily change the
beverage that we want to
prepare and in here we are just going to
set beverage equal to
beverage
okay so next up we need a uh boil water
and pour into cup uh methods so let me
just copy and paste those
in so okay so these are our shared
methods or shared steps every be every
single beverage we have to uh boil some
water and then pour it into the
cup uh so then what we can do is we can
have a a method called make
beverage and in here we can have our
common operations though so the oper op
ation or steps that every single
beverage has to
follow and those are boil
water and pour into
cup and then we can call our unique
operations by simply calling
beverage.
prepare and as you can see our beverage
maker needs no specific knowledge of the
particular beverage that is that it's
preparing because we are coding to an
interface using polymorphism we can just
call the prepare method and it will call
the prepare method on any of the
concrete uh
beverages
okay so now if we go into uh a client
and show how a client might use this
solution so first of
all we would create a beverage maker
and in here we pass the beverage that we
want to make so let's say we want a cup
of tea and we have the beverag maker.
make
beverage so let's see how this works
okay so boiling water uh pouring boiled
water into the cup so those are our
shared methods which are actually inside
of the beverage maker class so you can
see here when we say make beverage we
call these common operations from within
the make beverage sorry the within the
beverage maker class and then we call
the unique operations so in this case we
Brew the tea for 3 minutes and then we
ask the customer if they would like
lemon with their tea
I do and I get lemon in my tea
perfect so um let's say we want to now
make a coffee so we say beverag maker do
set beverage and we can say new
coffee and we can call beverag maker.
make
beverage now this time it will call the
two shared methods and then it will call
the methods uh specific to make making a
coffee so uh first of all it's making
the tea so let's do the tea and then it
makes the coffee and it asks if I want
cream with the coffee yes and let's see
it adds cream to the coffee so this is
working
perfectly so let's just uh summarize
what we have done here so inside of
Beverage maker we Define the common
behavior for making a beverage and that
is boil oil water and pour water into
cup and we have a an interface called
beverage and uh this has a prepare
method and we also have our concrete
beverage implementations for chamomile
coffee and tea all of which implement
the beverage interface and this allows
us to treat all beverages the same way
in the beverage maker uh class
and from here from the beverage maker uh
class uh we specify the beverage uh when
we create uh the beverage maker object
or we can set the beverage
here and then we are delegating or uh
forwarding the execution of tasks
related to making a specific beverage to
a concrete beverage object and this is
the strategy pattern so we've just
solved this problem using polymorphism
which actually led to us using the
strategy pattern uh but we could also
solve this problem using inheritance so
tea coffee and chamomile have things in
common so we we can create an abstract
class called beverage that implements
the prepare method but after we've
boiled the water and poured it into the
cup what happens next is unknown in the
abstract beverage class as it depends on
the particular beverage and these
beverage specific steps will be
determined later on when the beverage
class is extended by the concrete
classes so we can provide a base
abstract class called beverage that
contains all common operations for
making a beverage and we can provide
methods called brew and AD condiments
which can be implemented or overridden
in the concrete beverage classes so you
can see here we have our beverage class
with a prepare method and you can see we
have the brew and AD condiments methods
which are sort of dled out in Gray which
is implying that they are uh not
implemented in this in this beverage
class they are abstract uh methods which
need to be implemented in the
concrete um tea coffee and carom mile
classes so you can see here this prepare
method is known as a template method so
it's providing a template for the steps
involved for prepar in a beverage so we
have the boil water and pour into cup
methods which are
defined um in the beverage class itself
okay because these are our shared
methods that are used by all Beverages
and then we have brew and AD condiments
which are to be defined later on when
this beverage class is extended so this
prepare method is acting as a template
method okay and this is known as the
template method pattern so the beverage
class has a template method that
provides the common setup and structure
uh for preparing a beverage and here's
how the template method pattern is shown
in the gang of four book so we have an
abstract class with a template method a
public template method which calls the
um some abstract methods in a particular
order okay so then we have our concrete
methods uh sorry our concrete classes
that Implement those
um those
methods uh and the template method will
call those methods in a particular
sequence so we have an abstract class
with a concrete implementation of the
common shared template method and the
abstract methods that will be
implemented within the concrete classes
can be used to alter the behavior of the
template method and we can also give the
primative operations a default
implementation and leave it up to the
subclasses to either take them as they
are or override them in this case we
refer to these methods as hooks or hook
operations so you can see here in this
abstract class the um these sort of
methods that are to be implemented in
the concrete classes are not dled out
anymore so they're basically we're
providing a default implementation for
these methods and it is now optional in
these concrete classes whether they are
uh sort of
overridden so we have uh method one and
Method two here with default
implementations within this class and
we've just decided in this concrete
class in particular uh in this example
we're just overriding method one and
leaving method two to its default
implementation within the abstract class
so we're not going to bother to
overwrite it we're just going to take it
as it is and we refer to these kind of
methods as
hooks so let's now implement the
template method pattern in code so here
we have our base beverage class and
currently we have our template method
with all of the steps involved in
creating a beverage now if you remember
the boil water and the pour into cup
steps are shared between all of the
concrete beverage classes so we can
actually Implement these two steps
inside of this beverage class so let's
copy and paste those in just to save a
little bit of time so here we boil the
water and pour into the cup so those are
the first two steps that every beverage
has now in this template method we can
now provide a uh we need to provide a
brew and add condiments uh methods so I
think for brew what we will do is we
will make it a uh virtual uh method so
in fact actually we'll make it an
abstract method which means that all uh
subclasses must uh implement this Brew
method okay so every uh every concrete
Brew needs to specify how long to brew
the beverage for so what we will do is
we will create a uh
protected uh an abstract void
brew and it will just be like this so we
must provide this uh Brew method inside
of all of our concrete beverages now we
can see that we are getting an error
because this class now needs to be an
abstract class because we have it has a
it has an abstract method now let's also
create this ad condiments method so the
ad condiments method what we're going to
do is we're going to create um this
method with a default
implementation so we will say protected
virtual meaning that it can optionally
be uh overridden in in its sub classes
and what we're going to do is we're
going to provide a default
implementation of an empty body which
basically means that uh we don't add any
condiments by
default okay so that's our base uh
abstract beverage class so now what we
can do is we can create the concrete
classes so let's start off with the T
class and T needs to inherit from
beverage and we also need to implement
this AB abstract class so the only
method that we have to implement is this
Brew uh method because it's an abstract
method and in
here we can just say uh Brewing t
[Music]
for three mens okay and then optionally
we can provide a uh add condiments
method here so we can override this
default implementation so this is
essentially a hook method so I think
what we're going to do is we'll just
copy this from inside of uh what we did
before so let's copy and paste that in
and what we need to do is we need to say
that we are overriding this method from
the beverage
class and we have an error here let me
check um oh yeah so we need to make sure
that this is
protected to match the uh method
signature from the beverage class okay
so that all looks okay and just to save
some time I'm not going to make the
coffee class but I'll just make the
camomile class because that is a little
bit different to uh the tea class so
camomile and again we need to inherit
from beverage and then we need to
implement the abstract
class so here we'll just um we'll say
Brew camk M for three
mins and this is uh all we need to do
for the cam mile class because cam miles
don't have any optional uh
condiments so that is everything we need
to do there so let's now have a look at
how a client would actually use this uh
solution so if we go into our client and
we create a uh T
beverage and let's make sure we're using
the correct namespace here so this is
the template
method and we can just call T do
prepare and then run this
program and we can see we got all these
are the two shared steps the boiling the
water and the pouring into the cup then
we have our uh sort of concrete class
specific uh logic here
uh Brewing the tea for three mens and it
asks us would you let lemon with your
tea and we get lemon in our tea and then
for the cam mile we can do the same
thing pretty much and there are no
optional condiments so it just makes the
beverage automatically without uh us
having to answer any
questions so this is a nice and simple
solution for clients to make beverages
uh all beverages provide a simple API a
simple and consistent API uh where with
a prepare method and the rest of the
complexities are abstracted away as the
clients require no knowledge of those uh
complexities let's now have a look at
the differences between the template
method pattern and the strategy pattern
as we've just previously used both to
solve the same problem so you can use
the template method pattern when you
have an algorithm with a fixed structure
but with certain steps that need to be
customized or implemented differently by
subclasses and this pattern is ideal
when you want to define a common
algorithm skeleton or in other words the
template method in a base class and
allow subclasses to selectively override
specific steps to provide their own
implementations of those specific steps
and the template method pattern is
suitable when the over overall algorithm
structure remains consistent but
specific parts of the algorithm can vary
based on different requirements or
contexts
and for the strategy pattern you can use
the strategy pattern when you want to
define a family of interchangeable
algorithms or behaviors and encapsulate
each algorithm into its own class and
the strategy pattern is ideal when you
need to dynamically select and switch
between different algorithms at runtime
depending on the situation or context
and the strategy pattern is suitable
when you want to decouple the client
code from specific algorithm
implementations allowing for greater
flexibility and
extensibility so in summary if you
primarily need to customize or override
specific steps of an algorithm while
keeping the overall structure intact the
template method pattern is a good choice
on the other hand if you need to
encapsulate entire algorithms or
behaviors as interchangeable components
that can be dynamically selected or
replaced the strategy pattern is
probably more appropriate so both
patterns have their strength
and are used to address different design
scenarios the choice between them
depends on the specific requirements and
design goals of your application so when
should you use the template method
pattern you can use this pattern when
you want to allow clients to implement
only particular steps in an algorithm
and not the whole algorithm it's a good
pattern to use when you have a bunch of
classes with the same logic or algorithm
but with differences in a few steps so
if the algorithm changes it only has to
be modified in one place and that is the
base class so the pr uh pros and cons of
the template method pattern so the pros
uh we can reduce code duplication by
having the sort of shared logic or
methods in the base class that can be
inherited and clients are only allowed
to modify certain steps in an algorithm
which reduces the risk of breaking
clients if the algorithm changes and
some of the cons are that some clients
may be limited by the provided
template and template methods can be
hard to maintain if they have a lot of
steps The Observer pattern involves an
object known as the subject maintaining
a list of dependent objects called
observers and notifying them
automatically of any state changes so
that may not make too much sense to here
so let's go through an example to learn
the Observer pattern so here we have an
Excel document with two spreadsheets
spreadsheet one and spreadsheet 2 and in
spreadsheet one we have a data source
which is essentially do just a two
column table with City in the left hand
column and number of dogs in each of
those cities in the right hand column
and then we also have a bar chart with
dogs on the Y AIS and the city name on
the x axis and this bar chart is
essentially um uh built from this data
source and then in spreadsheet two we
have um a sum so we have one of the
cells is basically summing up the number
of dogs to get the total number of dogs
in all of the Cities so let's first of
all come up with a naive or sort of
obvious uh solution to this problem
so uh we have a data source object which
has a list of observers so The Observers
are going to be sheet two so spreadsheet
two which is calculating the total uh
number of dogs and we have a bar chart
which is uh um producing a bar chart um
from the the data source
so uh here uh we we also have the values
of the data source and a getter and
Setter for getting and setting the
values in the data source now the
problem with this solution is that we
have tight coupling to the concrete
Observer objects which are spreadsheet 2
and the bar chart meaning that we need
conditional statements to check the
object type before we actually update
The Observers so this will probably make
a lot more sense as as we implement this
solution in code so let's do that so
first of all let's create a new folder
for the Observer
pattern and what we will do in here
first of all is create our spreadsheet 2
class so our sheet two will have a field
for storing the
total it will also Al have a geta which
just Returns the
total and then we'll have a method for
actually calculating the
total and this will take a list of
integers and we'll keep track of the sum
in a uh variable called sum and we'll
initialize that to zero and what we're
going to do is we're going to Loop
through each uh value in this values
list and uh we're going to add it to
this sum uh uh
variable so we can do sum plus equals
value and then let's just log what the
value is
and return the total at the
end okay so that's everything we need in
spreadsheet this spreadsheet 2 class so
let's now create our bar chart
class and then here we're going to have
a single method called
render and this is going to take the
list of integer values from the the uh
data
source and we're just going to keep it
simple and log rendering bar
chart okay so obviously if this was a
proper bar chart we'd need to pass in um
probably an object with keys and values
or some sort of dictionary where we have
uh the key as maybe the city and the
value as the value but we're just going
to keep things simple for now and just
pass a list of in integers because we're
not actually going to be drawing a bar
chart so finally we can create our data
source class and this class is going to
store a list of uh the dependent objects
or essentially The Observers uh that
rely on the data uh data source and
those being sheet 2 and bar chart so
that when the values in the data source
are changed ER the data source can uh
update those dependent objects so let's
create the data
source and in here we're going to have a
list of uh
values so this is kind of analogous to
our uh number of dogs in each of the
Cities
basically and we'll create a new list of
integers
and we'll also create a list of
dependent objects or our Observer
objects and these are just going to be
sort of uh of type objects we're not
going to specify uh the exact type of
object so that we can pass in uh either
bar charts or or sheet twos or any
object that needs to be updated when the
data source uh values are changed so
we're going to call this uh
dependence we could also call it a
observers but dependence we'll do for
now and we'll just initialize that to a
list of objects so next up we're going
to create a uh geta for the
values so that the other objects can uh
get the
values and we just return the values
there and then we'll also create um a
seta uh method called set
values and this needs to be a list of
integers and we just set values equal to
values now in here whenever we update
these uh values we also need to notify
our bar chart and Sheet two so that the
bar chart can render itself with the new
values and Sheet two can
recalculate the uh total so what we're
going to do
is we are going to uh loop through all
of our
dependents or all of our dependent uh
Observer objects so we can say for
dependent in
dependence and this needs to be for each
Loop
sorry and in here we need to check uh
the type of the dependent the object
type so we can say if
dependent um is sheet
two then we can uh cast the uh dependent
to a sheet 2
object by writing dependent as sheet two
and this will allow us to uh recalculate
the
total and then in here we need to pass
in the new
values okay and we also can check if if
the dependent is a bar
chart and if it is a bar chart we can
then cast the dependent object to a uh
object of type bar chart uh bar chart
and we can call the render method to
reender the bar chart with the new set
of
values okay so that's actually
everything we need to do uh for this set
values method uh but now we also need to
a way of um adding dependence to our
data source so that we can actually
control uh which objects are going to
observe this data source so for that we
can create a method called add
dependent and in here we can pass any
object
and we quite simply just uh add this on
to our uh
list okay and we also uh want to create
a method for removing
dependence and in here we can pass the
object that we want to
remove and we can call dependent do
remot move and pass that
dependent okay so that's everything that
we need in data source so we have our
sheet 2 and by chart observers and we
also have our data source so now let's
have a look at how we could use this
solution in a client so let's clear this
out and create a new data source
object and let's also create create our
uh sheet 2 and barart
observers and now we need to add these
um these objects to the data source as
dependents so we can call data source
dot add dependent and pass in sheet two
so this can be any object
and we can also add our bar
chart
okay and then what we can do is we can
set some values in the data
source and in here we're just going to
pass a simple uh list of integers so we
can say five five 1
10 and let's actually run the program
now to see what we
get so you can see here when we called
set values it has actually uh updated
the total in the sheet two and it's it's
the total is 21 which is correct and
it's also rendered the bar chart with
these new values so if we then call uh
the set values uh method again and we
just set the values to say 1 2 3 run the
program and we should then um get a new
total and we should also get the bar
chart rendered which we do so this is
all working uh
perfectly however there are some issues
with this solution so can you uh see
what solid principles uh we are
violating so maybe take 30 seconds or a
minute to have a look at the solution
that we've just come up with and see if
you can spot uh what solid principle uh
principles of being violated and the two
of the most obvious uh principles that
we are violating are first of all the
single responsibility principle because
this data source class actually has two
responsibilities it is storing data so
managing data storage and it is also uh
managing the dependent Observer
objects so it has two reasons to change
and we also are violating the open close
principle because every time that we
create a new Observer object we have to
modify data source so if we create I
don't know pie chart we then have to
modify data source uh we have to come in
here and check if the dependent is of
type pie chart and then call the
appropriate method to actually update
that pie chart with the new values so we
are uh violating the open close
principle and this is because because we
are uh programming to concrete objects
rather than to a generic
interface so how do we solve the issues
that we spotted uh in our last solution
so we were violating the single
responsibility principle and we were
also violating the open close principle
so to solve the single responsibility
principle we could actually create a
separate class for managing the
dependent Observer objects and to solve
the open close principle we can ensure
that all of our Observer objects so
sheet 2 and bar chart in this example
Implement a common interface so that
they provide consistent methods allowing
us to use polymorphism in the data
source class so it's now time to
introduce the Observer
pattern so for the Observer pattern we
have an abstract class called the
subject and in the subject we have some
methods for managing Observers so this
is like our separate uh class for uh
managing the dependent Observer objects
and in here we have a method for adding
an observer for removing an observer and
for notifying The Observers or updating
The
Observers we then have our uh data
source class which uh manages the values
and the data
source as well as a geta and a Setter
for those
values and we can see here that the data
source is is
inheriting uh the Observer uh methods
from this subject
class we then have the subject talking
to uh an observer interface which has a
single update method and we can see here
that the subject is composed of uh
Observer objects so this will store a
list of Observer objects okay and you
can see here that this abstract subject
class is coded to an interface and not
the concrete Observer classes and as you
can see here we have our two concrete
observers the sheet two and bar chart
which implement the Observer interface
allowing us to use
polymorphism okay because this subject
class when it notifies The Observers
doesn't have to check what type of
object we're dealing with because it
knows that they are of type Observer it
can just call the update method without
knowing the specifics so this actually
uh uh this solution now follows the open
close Principle as we can extend our
application by adding new Observer
classes without having to modify the
data source class so for example
tomorrow we may may want to add another
spreadsheet that finds the average of
the data source values and to do that we
can just create a new sheet three class
that implements Observer and the data
class doesn't care it just talks to The
Observer server interface and set values
in um the data source will uh simply
Loop through all of its observers and
call the update method on each and this
is polymorphic Behavior a different
update method will be called depending
on the Observer but data source doesn't
care or it doesn't need to know what the
specific concrete observers are each
concrete implementation figures out how
to update themselves so if we have a
look at the gang of four Observer
pattern here we can see that we have the
abstract subject class with three
methods for managing The Observers the
list of observers and we have an attach
detach and notify so that's basically
the same as what we had up here add
remove and notify or add detach and
notify then we have our Observer
interface with its update method and we
have our concrete subject and our
concrete observers so very similar to
the solution that we have up
here so um The Observer pattern is also
known as the Pu uh Pub and sub pan so
the publish And subscribe Pan and the
subject uh which is the publisher
publishes changes in its state and the
subscribers or The Observers subscribe
to those events so let's now refactor
our code to use The Observer pattern so
let's now refactor our code using the
Observer pattern so first of all we're
going to create an observer
interface and in here we give it a
single method called
update and then we can refactor our
concrete observers so we have bar chart
which needs to implement Observer and we
can see here we get a red squiggly line
indicating that we have an error because
we are not implementing The Observer
update method so here we can simply
change this method to update but we
still get an error because we are not
actually uh using the same uh method
signature so if we go into this Observer
interface we can see that update doesn't
have any parameters so we need to remove
this
parameter but we still need a way of
getting the values from the data source
so what can do instead of passing them
to this update method we can store a uh
field of type data
source and pass the data source object
into the Constructor whenever we create
a new bar
chart okay so that's everything we need
to do for our bar chart class so let's
now go into to our second Observer which
is sheet 2 so again we need to implement
the Observer interface and then we also
need to implement the
methods so we should we get an update
method here so what do we need to do in
this update method so I'm just going to
move this up a little bit so let's move
it to
here and what we want to do is we want
to set the total to the sum of the uh
values So currently we don't have any
way to uh access the values so again
let's uh create a new field for the data
source and we'll pass that via the
Constructor and now what we can simply
do is set the total uh field equal to
calculate total and we can pass the
values by getting them from the data
source object so here we can just say
total is equal to calculate total and
then we can get the values from the data
source object which we have passed into
this
object okay so that is everything that
we need to do for the uh sheet two class
so now what we can
do is we can create a uh our subject
class which is going to be the class
that manages observers so let's create
that
class and here we need to first of all
create a field for uh keeping the list
of Observer objects
okay so then we need to add our three
methods for managing observers so we
need a way of adding observers removing
observers and also notifying All The
Observers in the list that um our our
sort of source object has changed so
first of all let's create the ad
Observer method
and then here we pass the Observer that
we want to add to the
list and we can just call observers do
add
Observer and then for the remove
Observer and again we pass the Observer
to this method that we want to
remove and we just call observers do
remove and we pass the
Observer okay and finally we need a way
of well we need a method to uh notify
our
observers so here we can see we're
getting a suggestion for each Observer
and observers and that's what we need to
do and we can just call observer. update
so we can call
observer. update okay so here we can see
we have uh we are using polymorphism to
update The Observers this subject uh
class doesn't need to know anything
about the actual specific concrete
observers that are in this list it just
needs to know that they are some sort of
Observer so that we can then use
polymorphism and just call the update
method so this is a nice flexible clean
maintainable way of notifying The
Observer objects even though they may be
uh of different even though they are
different types of objects so next we
need to refactor our data source class
so in
here we no longer are managing The
Observers so we can remove this uh
dependence
list and let's see so we have our G
values uh method so we want to keep this
okay because this is used in our
Observer uh in our concrete
observers and the set value uh method
can now be cleaned up so we can see
before we were storing a list of just uh
objects and we had to actually check the
type of object and then cast it to the
type that it that it was found to be so
that we can uh could call the update
method on that object so what we can do
now is we can actually get rid of this
uh large block of code and simply just
call the notify observers method but we
can't do that yet because we actually
haven't uh inherited the subject class
so let's inherit
that and now we will have all of the
methods uh from this subject class so
we've inherited them which means that we
can just call notify observers so this
is much cleaner
and we also no longer need to have these
add and remove methods because we're
this class is no longer managing The
Observers so that is much cleaner so
that should be everything that we need
to do so let's now go into the
program.cs file and let's change this to
observer. good
example so let's see what do we need to
do differently here so we are creating a
new data source so let's
see uh let's actually start again here
so we'll say data
source uh data source equals new data
source and let's create our observers so
we'll create a sheet two
and actually this should be uh our good
example
sorry I'm not sure why we are getting an
error here uh let's
see so what did we do here let's see ah
so we're using lowercase s here actually
so let's just use a lower case
s actually no we'll change this here to
be correct so let's correct this so if I
use function F2
let's change that to the correct
casing and then come back into
program.cs there we go the error goes
away so now for Sheet two this is in our
first or second Observer I guess we need
to pass the data source uh object into
here and we also need to create our bar
chart
class and and again pass the data source
into that
object and let's see we
yeah and what did we do here let's
see H for some reason I decided to not
use
uh not uppercase the second word again
let's
see okay so hopefully that fixes that
issue okay there we go so now we can add
our observers to the data source object
so let's do
that okay so now if we set the values in
the data source it should then notify uh
notify our Observer objects and uh cause
them to be updated so let's try
that and we're going to pass an array of
values so 55 1 and
10 and let's run this program to see if
our observers are notified and updated
correctly so here the sum is 21 which is
correct and we are rendering the V bar
chart with new values so if we
also uh if we change the values now to
uh 1 2 3 so let's see what we get
now we can see that the total is updated
correctly and the bar chart is rendered
with new values so this is all working
perfectly so we can see
here let's have a look at how using the
Observer pattern has improved our
solution and made it more flexible and
maintainable so if we look first of all
in the data source
uh class we can see that we this is now
satisfying the single responsibility
principle because data source is now
only managing the values it is not
managing observers The Observers uh
methods and the Observer list are all
managed by this subject class okay so
now this subject class has a sole
responsibility for managing observers
and one a good advantage of this is that
this subject class could now be used for
for any other class that needs to be
observed so this is a much more flexible
and uh maintainable solution and the
second uh thing that we' have done is
because we are now using an observer
interface and forcing all observers to
implement this Observer interface we can
now use
polymorphism inside of our uh subject
class so we can see here that we can
simply call observer. update and treat
all observers as as though they are uh
the same object without having to check
the type of object and then call that
correct uh specific method on the
Observer we know that they have an
update method because they are
implementing The Observer interface and
we can just use polymorphism which makes
our solution much more clean and
flexible so we're now going to have a
look at the different types of
communication styles that can be used to
when implementing The Observer pattern
so beforehand The Observers get notified
of a change but they don't know what has
changed and one solution is to add a
parameter to The Observer update method
and this is known as a push style of
communication as the subject pushes the
changes to The Observers so beforehand
we actually the way that uh our
observers got the values from data
source is by actually storing the data
source in a field within the class and
then when we need to get the values from
data Source we call a method on data
source uh so a push style communication
would be different so we wouldn't
actually store a field uh for the data
source within the Observer and we would
actually uh push the uh values to this
update method so this update method
would have some sort of parameter and
that could be uh
any um object or just some sort of gen
generic type for
flexibility so the push style has the
advantage that the concrete observers
don't depend on or have any knowledge of
or coupling to the concrete
subject okay so the problem with uh this
solution with this push style uh
solution is that what if each Observer
needs a different set of values and this
is where we could use a pull style of
communication where the Observer stores
a reference to the concrete subject then
whenever whenever it's notified of a
change it pulls or queries the data it
needs from the concrete subject and you
can see here this is actually the
solution that we used for uh our example
where we have our concrete observers
that keep a reference to the concrete
subject and you can see here sheet two
and our barart both have a field with
reference to the concrete data source
object which is passed in Via a
Constructor and then whenever it needs
uh any values it can pull them or query
them using this Gap values
method uh so you can see the difference
here between push style and pull style
with push style we are pushing uh the uh
values to the update method by uh
passing them as arguments and this means
that the concrete Observer doesn't need
to be coupled to the concrete subject
however it's not as flexible as the
pulse style where the concrete Observer
keeps a reference to the concrete
subject allowing it to query any of the
values that it needs so again the
concrete Observer stores a reference to
the concrete subject in pul style and we
give concrete subjects a get Value
method so that the concrete observers
can get the data that it needs and this
gives us more
flexibility however we do have coupling
here between the concrete classes but
this isn't actually a bad type of
coupling a bad coupling would be between
the concrete subject and concrete
Observer so if we basically reverse this
arrow and this is because these
observers could change in the future and
we may also introduce more
observers and the concrete subject would
then have to keep reference to all of
the different types of concrete Observer
so this would
uh not satisfy the open close principle
because every time we added a new
Observer we would have to update the
concrete subject and we don't want to
change our concrete subject class uh
data source in our example every time
there is a new Observer so in reality we
never have zero coupling in software
what matters the most is the direction
of the relationship and in this case the
direction is okay so with p style
communication we pass the concrete
subject the data source to The Observer
uh just like we did when implementing
our Observer pattern for our data source
with the bar chart and Sheet two
observers the mediator pattern defines
an object called the mediator that
describes how a set of objects interact
with each other therefore reducing lots
of chaotic dependencies between those
objects so let's go through an example
to uh so that you can understand the
media a pattern in an easy intuitive way
so let's say that we have a Blog that
lists all of your blog posts and you can
select a post then edit that post title
so you can see here initially when the
page loads we have state one where we
have a sort of list of blog posts and
none of those posts are initially
selected so that's the initial State no
posts are selected and then the user can
select an article from the posts cont
container so this is the post container
and in this case they've just selected
post three and uh a sort of text input
is then populated on the right hand side
of the screen where with the title of
the post and then the uh save button
becomes enabled so the user can then
update the title of that post within
this text box and uh the save button is
disabled if no title is provided so if
the user deletes all of the characters
from this uh text box then uh the post
button is disabled and also if no post
is selected then the save button is also
disabled so you can see here the dis
save button is disabled because no title
is
provided so we need uh some components
for this uh application so first of all
we have a list box that contains the
posts so this is the list box then we
have a text box for editing the title
and a button that can either be disabled
or enabled and the above classes list
box text box and button will come from a
UI framework so that so we do not have
access to the source code to these UI
components um
so uh again when when an article is
selected from the list box the text box
should be populated and the button
enabled and when we clear the text box
the button should become disabled so the
question becomes how do these classes
talk to each other so they should be
able to ideally uh be able to talk to
each other without knowledge of each
other and one solution would be to use
inheritance so we can see here at the
top we have our UI framework classes
that we cannot touch so we don't have
access to these this is just like an
installed package and we have a list box
text box and a button class and then we
can extend each of those classes to to
create our own sort of custom versions
of these classes so we can extend list
box to create our own post L list box
class then we have a title text box
which uh extends or inherits from
textbox and same again for button for
the save
button and then these uh sort of custom
classes that extend the UI Library
classes can then talk to each other uh
like this so we can see here that posts
list box holds a reference to the title
uh text box then uh we can create an
unselect method so that when a post is
selected from the list it calls uh uh it
sets the text on the text box and
enables the save button and then within
title text box we have an unchange
method so whenever the uh user type some
characters into the box or delete some
characters we check to see if the text
is an empty string and if it is we
disable the save button and we can see
in save button it holds a reference to
the title text box because when the
button is clicked if the button is
enabled then it will get the text from
the text box and save it to the
database okay so the problem with this
solution is that as our form gets more
complex there becomes lots of
dependencies or connections between
these classes and also the logic for
this form is spread all over the place
it's spread between all of these classes
so to see what's going on in this form
you have to look at multiple classes and
it's very difficult to understand and
maintain so we can solve this problem
using the mediator pattern and using the
mediator pattern the UI components don't
need to know about each other as all of
the interaction logic is in this
dialogue box which is the
mediator so whenever a UI component
changes it notifies its owner which is
the dialogue Box by calling the changed
uh method and passing itself uh so each
of these uh components are UI control
components and it passes itself as an
argument to this change method which
then handles updating all of the other
components so this will make a lot more
sense as we implement this in code so
let's go ahead and do that
so I've created a new folder called
mediator and then first of all we're
going to create our dialogue box
mediator
class okay so this class plays the role
of mediator so every time a UI component
changes its state it will call a its
groups dialogue box so uh this is
actually going to be an abstract class
class so let's change that to abstract
and we're going to provide a public
abstract method called
changed that will uh take a UI control
or UI
component and this hasn't been created
yet so we are getting an error and you
might be wondering why this is actually
an abstract uh class and not an
interface and that is because in a re
guey framework we would provide some
concrete methods as well as these
abstract methods so that is why I've
created this as an abstract class so
next of next up let's create this uh
abstract UI control
class so uh the abstract UI control
class is going to ensure that each UI
component gets put into a dialogue box
and a dialog box is essentially just a
group of UI components so we're going to
need a
field called dialogue um of type
dialogue
box and we're going to call this owner
so uh all UI components uh can be
grouped into a dialogue box and know and
can talk to their owner so this allows
the owner to change all the the UI
components accordingly so all the UI
control components need uh a single uh
dialogue box or mediator
owner and we can now create a
Constructor
here where we can pass the owner to the
UI control so we're specifying you know
which class should be the
owner
okay so now we have our UI control uh
class okay so next up we can create our
concrete UI components that extend the
UI control class so first of all I'm
going to create the list box
class and this needs to extend UI
control so let's actually uh generate a
Constructor to satisfy this UI control
uh class and you can see here what we
are doing is we are passing a dialogue
box or mediator owner to the list box
instructor and setting the owner in the
base UI control
class so next up what we need to do is a
list box um we need to be able to select
a post so what we'll do is we'll just
simply store a private string called
selection and set that to an empty
string and then we'll create a couple of
of Getters and Setters for setting the
selected post um inside of the list box
so let's first of all create a geta
function or GAA method called get
selection and this will just return the
selection and then we'll have a set
selection
and we will set the selection and what
we need to do here is we actually need
to Now notify the owner that this class
has changed so if we uh select a title
from the list box selection will be
updated and we need to uh let the other
components know that this class has
changed so what we do is we notify the
owner by calling owner. changed and then
we pass this UI control class
or object to the changed method and then
within the owner uh the owner can see
that this a this list box has changed
and it can then update the other
components so the text box and the
button
accordingly so next up uh next up we're
going to uh create the concrete text box
class and this is going to again extend
uh UI control or inherit from UI control
and then we need to generate the
Constructor so that it satisfies the UI
control class and textbox is just going
to have a simple text
field initialized to an empty string and
then we need to create again our Getters
and Setters for this text field
so we set the text and again we need to
notify the owner uh which is a dialogue
box a sort of mediator class that uh
this class has changed so we call the
changed method and we pass this text box
object
and finally our final uh concrete UI
control component is the button so let's
create a class called
button and this is going to extend UI
control we then need to uh generate the
uh Constructor just the same as before
and a button class just needs to store a
uh field just to uh State whether the
button is en enabled or
disabled and we need some Getters and
Setters for this Ena um is enabled uh
field
and again we need to inform the owner
that the button has
changed okay so here again we are
telling the mediator that I this button
object have
changed so uh finally what we need to do
is create the uh posts dialog box that's
going to contain all of the UI
components for our post title editing
application and it's going to update
these components depending on which
component called the uh changed method
so that's going to make more sense as we
actually uh create this class so we're
going to create posts dialog
box and this class needs to extend
dialog
box so this is kind of like our concrete
mediator class so let's implement the
abstract class so it needs to have this
changed method and what we'll do first
is we will create all of our fields for
all the UI
components so we need a list
box a text
box and a
button uh we now need a Constructor so
that we can pass all of our UI
components to this uh concrete mediator
the post dialogue box so let's create a
Constructor and what we're actually
going to do is we're just going to
initialize them inside of the
Constructor rather than pass them so
we'll say post list box equals new list
box and if you can remember within each
UI control uh component we need to
actually pass the owner and the owner is
just going to be
this so then we do the same for all of
the other
components and also in the Constructor
we're going to set the save
button to
disabled because initially the save
button needs to be
disabled so next up let's actually add
the logic inside of our changed
method so what we need to do in
here is we need to check what the UI
control is so if the UI control is equal
to a posts list box or the post list box
then what we need to do is we're going
to set the title text box so we'll say
title text box uh do set text and we're
going to set that equal to the post list
box. get
selection okay and we also need to
enable the save button
and what we should do is we should set
enabl here okay so you can see that if
the UI control is a post list box so if
the post list box has changed then that
means that a post has been selected so
therefore we need to update the title
text box with the selected uh post uh
title and we need to enable the save
button okay so that is pretty
straightforward uh then we need another
conditional to say that if the UI
control is equal to a title text box so
this means that the title text box has
changed so the user uh has entered a
title or deleted uh the ti some
characters from the title so what we
need to do
here is we check to see if the title is
empty so we can create a Boolean
so here we are checking if the title
text box is empty and then what we can
do is we can set uh the uh we can get
the save button and set enabled equal to
the opposite of is title empty
so if the title is empty then the save
button will be disabled whereas if the
title isn't empty then the save button
will be
enabled okay so that is all the logic we
need however you can see that this is a
little bit bloated this change method so
let what we can do is we can create a
couple of sort of helper methods now so
it would be nicer if we could just call
handle post
changed uh to handle the post list box
changing and sort of abstract this logic
into its own separate
method so let's create a private void
called
handle and let's capitalize that
actually handle post
changed and we can paste the logic down
here and let's capitalize this and let's
do the same for our uh text box logic so
handle uh title
changed and let's cut
this and put it all in its own separate
method okay so that's a little bit
tidier much clearer what is going on
here and so now that is pretty much
everything we need to do so notice how
clear it is now uh because all of our
business Logic for our application is
centered inside of this one post uh
dialogue box our sort of concrete
mediator so our sort of logic isn't
spread out over multiple UI components
so this is much more readable much more
clear what is going on so let's um now
create a method inside of this post
dialogue box to simulate a user
interaction so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to create a method called uh
simulate user
interaction and what we're going to do
is we're going to essentially say that
the user has selected a post and the
post title is post
two and we're going to uh log to the
console the uh title inside of the text
box and we're going to check if the
button is enabled
okay so this is just a sort of method to
simulate a user interaction so the user
selects a post from the post box and
then we're just checking to make sure
that the title text box is updated
correctly so this should be post two and
we're also checking that the button is
enabled so now let's go into our
program.cs
file and check that this all is working
correctly so let's create a posts
dialogue box
and then let's simulate a user
interaction and run this
program and as we can see the title text
box has been updated correctly it has
been populated to post two which is
correct and the button is enabled which
is perfect so that's all working
correctly uh so let's also test out that
the user enters no title so if we come
back to our posts dialogue
box and let's set the
title to an empty
string so essentially the user has
selected post two and then they have
deleted the title from the post uh from
this uh title input box and then if we
go to our program.cs file and run this
let's see what we get so we can see that
the title text box is empty which is
correct and we can see that the button
button is no longer enabled so that the
user cannot save a post with no title so
this is all working perfectly so here is
the gang of fourl for the mediator
pattern so here we have an abstract
class called the mediator and this uh
was analgous to our dialogue box class
in our example we then have a concrete
mediator so this was like our posts uh
dialogue box which extends the mediator
class we then have an abstract class
called colleague in our case we didn't
make it abstract and our colleague class
was the UI control uh class and you can
see here the UI control class or the
colleague uh is associated to or sort of
stores a reference to uh it's mediate so
its owner and you can see here our UI
control which is our colleague sour
reference to the dialogue box or its
owner which is the mediator class okay
we then have our concrete colle classes
so these are in our example were our UI
components so text box list box and
button and you can see here that we then
have our concrete mediator so this was
our posts dialogue box which stores uh
reference to all of the UI components
that it owns okay so the concrete
colleagues are all unrelated or
uncoupled from each other they talk to
each other indirectly via the
mediator allowing them to be reused in
different contexts for example we are
not coupling a list box to a text box or
a button the only coupling that we have
is between the concrete mediator
and the concrete colleagues and this is
fine because in our example the posts
dialogue box needs to know about all of
its UI components so that they can
interact with each other the mediator
pattern can be used with the Observer
pan so one problem with our previous
solution is that the changed method on
the posts dialogue box can get bulky as
we add more UI components which means
that we'll have lots of if L conditional
statements to see what components has
changed so you can see here this was our
changed component and we're checking
what type of UI control has changed then
handling it accordingly so you can see
how this can get bulky as we have more
UI controls in our uh dialogue box so to
solve this we can actually implement the
mediator pan using the Observer pattern
so let's just remind ourselves of what
the Observer pattern looks like so we
have an abstract class or which is
called the subject and this has three
methods so we have an attach detach and
notify and this subject uh class will
sort of manage a list of
observers uh and then we have our
concrete
subject um which is the class which is
being observed we then have an observer
interface which has a single update
method and we then have our concrete
observers which implement this Observer
interface and it each of these observers
has an update method for updating the
Observer whenever the concrete subject
has changed and whenever it changes the
concrete subject calls this notify
method it Loops through all of The
Observers and um and calls this update
method on each of The
Observers so uh below now we have the UI
controls which are our subjects so we
have list box text box and button and
these are our subjects okay so these are
the uh components which are being
observed and we then have
our uh posts dialogue box in the middle
here and this is the Observer so
whenever a UI control changes the posts
dialogue box gets
notified so let's actually implement
this in code so that it becomes clear
what is going on so I've created a new
folder called mediator with Observer
where we're going to create our new
solution with the Observer pattern so
let's also create a folder called uh UI
framework and this is essentially going
to be the code that we would not have
access to within our application so it's
some sort of UI library that we have
installed and within here I'm going to
create a delegate called event handler
so I'm going to first of all create this
as a class and then we will modify it
into a delegate so let's remove all of
this and this needs to be a
delegate and we need to return void so
in cop we can use delegates to specify
what an event handler or a callback
method should look like so here we're
saying that event handler methods should
return void and receive no arguments and
uh just stick with me because this
doesn't really make much sense just yet
but it will make more sense as we
develop this solution further so next
we're going to create the UI control
class which is our subject class from
The Observer
pan so let's just extend this out a
little bit
and we're going to create a class called
UI
control and yeah as I said this is the
subject class from The Observer pan so
this is going to basically uh manage our
event
handlers so it's going to keep a list of
callback methods for updating the other
UI components when a user interacts with
them so let's create a
list of event
handers and we're going to need a method
for adding event handlers to this list
okay so we add the event handler onto
the list and we also need a method for
notifying the event
handlers or calling the uh event
handlers I should say so we're going to
call this notify event
handlers and we are going to Loop
through all of the event
handlers and we're just going to Simply
invoke each event handler method okay so
let's just call this uh
Handler okay so uh just to sort of
explain what we're doing here so each UI
component is going to extend this UI
control class uh meaning that we can add
certain event handlers to each UI
control components and whenever so for
example the uh posts list box uh what we
can do is we can give it or add an event
handler to the this component and then
whenever the post is selected we can
call this notify event handlers method
which Loops through all of the uh
methods and calls them so in our case
the posts whenever a post is selected
from the post list box it should um
update the title text box and enable the
button so again this is going to make
more sense a little bit further down the
line so just stick with me for now so
now what we're going to do is we're
going to create our uh concrete UI
components so first of all let's create
the list
box and this needs to extend UI
control and now what I'm going to do is
just copy and paste the uh code that we
essentially had before so here we have
our selected post we have our getter and
we have our Setter and whenever we
whenever we set the selection we are
calling this notify event handlers
method which we get from UI
control so now let's create our text
box and again we inherit from UI control
and I'm just going to copy and paste
this in because again it's the same as
what we had beforehand
okay so again we can set the text get
the text and whenever we set the text we
are going to notify the event handlers
that have been attached to text box and
our final concrete UI component the
button
class which inherits again from UI
control and again I'm just going to copy
and paste this in because it is the same
as what we had
beforehand
okay so again we have our set enabled
method which
notifies uh the event handlers or
invokes the event handlers that are
attached to the
button okay so now that is basically all
of the code that uh we need for our UI
framework or the the code that we have
basically downloaded or installed that
we don't have access to so now we can
actually create our custom code which is
going to be our posts dialogue
box so this is essentially now our
application so we've create we've
basically installed this framework and
now we are going to use this
framework so in post dialogue box so I
just want to mention actually before we
uh create any more code that post dialog
box is now going going to be both a
mediator containing all of the business
Logic for how UI components should
interact with each other as well as
being an observer which receives notice
whenever a UI component changes so it's
now both a mediator and an observer so
first of all let's create uh declare the
fields uh for the UI
components and we can see here we need
to import these uh these
classes from our UI framework
folder and then I'm going to create a
Constructor where we can initialize
these um
Fields
okay and now what we need to do is we
need to add our event handler methods to
each UI component so before we do that
we actually want to uh add our uh
methods for handling uh events so if we
have a look at what we did before in the
mediator um example if we go to our
posts dialogue box we have a handle post
changed method and we also have a handle
title change method so let's copy and
paste those in
okay because these are going to now be
our event handlers okay that we can
attach to each of these UI components so
now what we can do is we can call uh
posts list box add an event handler and
the event handler that we want to H to
add is the handle post change events uh
Handler or let's give it a better name
of uh post
selected
okay
and let's also
add an event handler to the title text
box and I'm going to change this to
title changed
okay so that's pretty clear what's going
on here so as you can see if we compare
this to beforehand in our post dialogue
box we had to uh check which UI control
had changed whereas now because we are
just adding event handlers to each of
the uh UI controls we no longer need to
check um which UI my control has changed
so it's a lot tidier and as we add more
components this is going to be a lot
cleaner than the solution that we had
beforehand so now what we can do is add
a method to simulate a user interaction
so let me copy and paste that in to save
some
time
so here we go so what we're doing here
is we are uh simulating a post being
selected from the post list box and
we're then going to log out to check
whether the title text box and the
button has been updated correctly so now
let's go into our program.cs
file and test all of this out so let's
create a posts dialogue
box and there should be posts dialogue
box um
mediator with
Observer and we then need to simulate a
user interaction so we can call that
method and then we can run the program
to test that all the components have
been updated correctly and as you can
see here the title text box is post to
and the button is enabled so let's come
back into our post text box now and
basically uh simulate the user deleting
the title and check that our other
components have been updated correctly
so as you can see the title text box is
now empty and the button enabled is
false which is exactly as it should be
so let's now just take a quick look at
what we have done to summarize what is
going on here so you can see here in our
post dialog box Constructor that we set
our components equal to uh our UI
components and then we are adding event
handlers to each of the UI components so
let's have a look at this post list box
we add an event handler called post
selected and if we take a look inside of
our list
box we can see that whenever we set a
selection um we are calling the notify
event handlers method which comes from
this UI control
component and this uh method Loops
through all of the event handlers that
we attached and if you remember in post
dialogue box we just attached this post
selected method and what we do is this
uh method is then
invoked so you can see here we call this
method
and uh this method then updates the
title text box and the save button
accordingly so this is great because we
have now combined the mediator pattern
with the Observer pattern and reduced
the ugly bulky conditionals that we
previously had in the post dialogue
box the chain of responsibility pattern
allows building a chain of objects to
handle a request a request is passed
through a chain of handlers each capable
of either handling the request or
passing it to the next Handler in the
chain so to understand this let's go
through an example where we first create
a simple naive solution then refactor it
into something more maintainable using
the chain of responsibility pan so let's
say that we have a web page that
contains some information that only
admins of the website can access such as
a page that allows an admin to manage
the website's users for example create
new users get information update user
information
Etc so say that a user makes a requ
request to the website server but before
returning the web page the users's data
must be validated so for example we
could trim any Whit space around the
user uh user entered data we need to
authenticate the user so for example
check their username and password are
correct and then log some information
onto the server about this request and
if any of those steps fail then access
denied is returned to the user so here
is an illustration so we have the users
request here which goes to the server
which validates authenticates and logs
some
information and if any of these steps
fail so if the uh authentication fails
then the user uh then access denied is
returned to the user otherwise we can
return the web page to the user so let's
now code up a straightforward solution
for this example
so I've created a new folder called
chain of responsibility for this example
and we're going to first create the HTTP
request
class so in here we need a cou uh four
Fields so the first two fields are going
to be the user input Fields so that they
are going to be
username and we're also going to create
a a second field for the password of the
user and these are going to be sent with
the HTTP request and we're also going to
provide a couple of other fields so
these are actually going to be C
Properties and one the first one is
going to be validated
username and that needs to be a
string and the second one is going to be
validated
password okay so when these uh when the
username and password pass through uh
validation then they will uh these
fields will be populated with the
validated username for example if
username is a string with some white
space at the front then the validated
username will just be this without the
whites space okay so it's essentially
cleaning up the user input data so let's
also create a Constructor so that the
username and password can be
set and we'll also create a get username
uh
method and also a getter for the
password
okay so that's everything we need in our
HTTP request object so let's also create
a class for the validator now which is
going to validate our um user input data
that is attached to this request
object so let's call this
validator and we'll have a method called
validate and this takes the HTTP request
object and let's actually get the
username and password from the request
object and let's also get the
password and then we're just going to do
some simple validation um and in this
case we're just going to trim the white
space around the uh import strings for
username and password so to do that we
can uh call uh username do trim and
password. trim and then we can set that
to the validated username and validated
password on the request object
okay so that's all we need to do in our
validator class now for the
authenticator so once the request has
been validated we can pass it to the
authenticator class so let's create that
class now
and let's get the username and password
again and we're just going to keep it
simple here and we're just going to
check if the username is equal to Dany
and the password is equal to 2 3 and if
so this will return true meaning that
the user has been authenticated
okay so that is everything we need for
the authenticator class and finally the
final step once we've been through uh
validation and authentication we can
perform some login so let's create a new
class called
logger and in here we will provide a uh
s single method for logging to the conso
okay and finally we need to create a web
server class um so let's go ahead and do
that and this needs to have a method
called handle which is going to handle
the request so let's go ahead and create
the handle method and this is going to
take a
HTTP
request okay so now what we can do is we
can actually uh put everything we have
done together so first of all let's
validate the
request and we can call the validate uh
method on the
validator and we can pass the
request so that will populate the
request object with the validated
username and password so in our case
we're just trimming the username and
password and we we can now create the
authenticator and for this we can call
authenticator do
authenticate and again we can pass the
request object so in a sort of real web
server we' perhaps um do something like
uh throw an error if the um if the user
wasn't authenticated or maybe we could
um uh return a web page with access
denied something like that but uh just
to keep things simple for now we're just
going to call the function uh call this
authenticate method and not worry about
whether it's true or false
okay and then finally we're going to uh
create a
logger a logger object and then we're
just going to
log and in here we pass the request
object okay so that's everything we need
for now so now now let's have a look at
how we would actually use this solution
in a client
so first of all let's create our web
server and let's also create our request
object and it should be this
one and I'm going to pass um the
username name and password into this so
this is kind of like our user input data
or perhaps some data that was stored in
a in the user
session and um this is the username and
the password and in this case this would
actually uh authenticate the user
because we want to check if the password
and username is Danny and 123 and it is
in this case so that would be uh an
authenticated user and then we can call
the server. handle uh method and we can
pass the request object so let's run
this and see what we
get okay so everything seems to be
working okay the the log file has logged
to the console so that all seems to be
working okay now this seems like an okay
solution um it's pretty
straightforward however there are some
problems with this approach so with this
solution the order of operations so if
we go into our main sort of web server
class which brings everything together
um we can see here the the order of the
operations so we have validate authorize
and log are hardcoded inside the web
server class so if in the future we
wanted to disable login or or
authentication for certain scenarios
certain Roots certain web pages we
cannot do so we'd have to come back and
modify the code in in the web server
class
itself um and this violates the open
close principle because if we wanted to
uh change the order of the steps or add
an extra step we'd have to modify some
existing
code and the chain of responsibility
pattern uh solves this as we can build a
pipeline with a chain of objects for
processing a request and the request can
be of any type not just just a HTTP
request uh another issue with this
solution is that because of the new
keyword so you can see here we're using
the new keyword uh three times within
this uh method inside the web server
class
um
um we can see that the web server class
is tightly coupled to these concrete
validator authenticator and log
implementation
so to solve this we could extract
interfaces from these classes and have
our web server talk to I authorizer I
validator and I logger interfaces and
this would make our web server class
more flexible because if we wanted to
use a different type of validator or a
different type of authenticator we could
then pass that into the web server so
that it's not um sort of tightly coupled
to these concrete
implementations so let's now try to
solve the problem using the chain of
responsibility principle so instead of
having all of our request processing
logic inside of the web server. handle
method we can create a processing
pipeline or a chain of objects so uh
here you can see that we have our
request incoming request our HTT request
uh HTTP request sorry and then we have a
sequence of objects so first of all we
have the valid data which validates the
request and then this points to the
authenticator and passes the request to
the authenticator and if it's
successful the authenticator points to
the logger and passes the request onto
the logger and if that is successful
then the user can be directed to the web
page or the web page is returned to the
user so here each object only knows
about the next object in the chain so
for example validator only knows that
the next object in the chain is
authenticator it doesn't know anything
about the logger object for example uh
so first a request is passed to the
first object in the chain which in our
case is the validator and if this
request is successful it passes the
request to the to the next object in the
chain if it's not successful it will
stop processing right there so that the
other objects aren't
used so here's the uml for the chain of
responsibility solution and you can see
here we have our web server which has a
handle method which takes the request
and web server is composed of a Handler
um which is an abstract class with a set
next method for setting the next Handler
so for example validator would we would
set the next Handler as authenticator
and then for authenticator we would set
the next Handler as logger and uh each
Handler need needs to have needs to
implement a handle method which takes a
request object okay
so uh we have an abstract class called
Handler uh that has a reference to
itself so it has a field called Next of
type Handler so with this each Handler
can know about the next Handler in the
chain and this is essentially a linked
list data structure and the handle
method is an abstract method because at
the time time of implementing this class
we don't know how to handle a request we
determine or implement this in our
concrete handlers which are in our case
validator authenticator and logger so
web server has a reference to the first
Handler in the chain okay and that is
the validator okay so when when the web
server receive the sees the request it
can pass the request to the first
Handler in the chain which in our case
would be the valid data
Handler so you should also note that web
server is not talking directly to the
concrete handlers it's talking to a
Handler interface so it's completely
decoupled from the concrete
implementations of handlers and this
satisfies the open close principle
because if we want to for example remove
login we don't have to go to the handle
method on the web server and change its
implementation also if we want to add a
new process we can create a new class
that extends Handler then add it to our
chain we extend the code but we don't
modify any existing source code so here
is the gang of for implementation of the
chain of responsibility patter so we can
see here we have our abstract Handler
class which has a next field of type
Handler okay so which is the same um
same type as itself and we also have a
set next method which takes a Handler
and this is how we can set the next uh
field and we also have a handle method
which takes a request object and in this
handle method we can see that we check
if next is not null then we call the
next handlers handle method and pass the
request we then have our concrete
handlers which
um inherit from this Handler abstract
class and then we have our client here
so this is how our client can create a
chain using this uh solution so we can
see here we're creating a Handler one
Handler two Handler
three and these are concrete handlers
that it's creating here so Handler one
Handler two Handler three uh you can see
we're using the new keyword and then we
can uh set up our chain so we can call
H1 so handle one. set next and what
comes happen after Handler one it will
be Handler two so we pass Handler two
and then for Handler two we call set
next and pass Handler three and then to
initiate the request we get our first
Handler and call the handle method and
pass the request object so let's now
implement this solution in
code so first of all let's create the
abstract Handler
class so first of all let's create the
abstract Handler class
and this needs to be an abstract
class and we need to store a reference
to uh the next Handler in the chain so
let's create a field of type
Handler and we'll call this next
Handler okay so let's create our set
next uh um method as well and this is
going to return a
Handler as well as accept a
Handler and we're just going to set the
next Handler equal to this
Handler so why would we actually return
a Handler from this set next function or
method I should say well the reason for
that is because returning a
Handler from this set Handler method
allows us to link handlers in a
convenient way so for example we could
call a Handler one so
H1 uh and if it lets me do it let me
just do it as a string so H1 and it will
be set
next and we could pass H2 in here so
Handler 2 and then because this set next
method is returning the Handler we can
then simply just keep on chaining the
set next methods and and very
conveniently can um create our chain of
uh responsibility essentially okay so
it's you can do it all sort of on one
line rather than having to you know do
it on multiple lines so it's nice and
convenient and that is why we return
Handler from set next and if that
doesn't make sense it will make more
sense when we actually use this solution
in the program.cs file so bear with me
for now uh so next up we want to create
our sort of handle template plate method
so let's go ahead and create
that and this is going to take a HTTP
request so what we want to do now is we
want to uh have an if statement so we're
going to say if do
handle
request and this should be do hand
handle and we're going to create this
method in a
second so if do handle
request then we can return from this
handle method so what this essentially
means is if do handle returns true we
return early and the request processing
H ends here uh
otherwise we are going to check
if uh if the next hand
is not equal to
null then we are going to
um call the next handler do handle
method and pass along the request object
so now let's actually uh create this do
handle method so this is actually going
to be an abstract method that returns a
Boolean and takes a a HTTP request
object
okay so this uh do handle method is
going to be implemented in the concrete
handlers so this is going to make more
sense shortly so again bear with me uh
so let's now create the concrete handler
classes so first of all let's create the
validator and this needs to uh extend
the Handler class so let's uh implement
this abstract class so we need to create
this do handle uh
method and in here we're essentially
doing what we did before so we uh get
the username and the password from the
request object trim the whitespace and
set the um appropriate Fields as we did
before okay now this time we also need
to return a Boolean value so what should
we return here so returning false means
that that that we are not done
processing the request so the next
handle it in the chain should be called
and returning true ends the request
processing uh here so um this in this
case we should always return false
because there's no reason for the
request to uh stop processing at this
point so here we can simply
return um request actually what we can
do is we can
return
um we can return true if the validated
username or the validated password or
empty uh empty strings so if the user
provides an empty string for username or
password then we will stop the process
in here and the user will not uh re go
through to the web page essentially so
let's let's go with that so request.
validated username equals empty string
or request. validated password equals
empty string so essentially if we return
false here then we are not done
processing the request so if the um if
the user has provided a username or
password uh sorry a username and
password then we will continue
processing the request otherwise the
request ends here if the username or
password is not provided okay so now
let's create our authenticator
class and this again needs to inherit
from the
Handler and for this one I'm just going
to copy and paste in what we had
before uh so you can see here if the
username equals Danny and the password
equals one 2 3 then this in the brackets
will be
true however true would mean ending the
request so what we actually need to do
is stick an exclamation mark to negate
or you know make this the opposite of
what the result in the brackets is so if
the username is Danny and the password
is correct
then we actually are going to return
false and the request will continue on
to the next Handler okay so that's what
we want to do here and just to remind
you why that is the case it's because in
this sort of template method this handle
method we are checking if do handle is
equal to true and if it is true then we
end the request okay so we if we want to
continue to the next request uh the next
um the next object in the chain then we
need to return false from this do handle
method so that's how that works and
finally we're going to create our logger
object and again we need to extend the
Handler class and Implement all of the
methods and this is a very simple method
all we're going to do is log to the
console and just return false to
continue with the request so essentially
this means that this uh sort of Step In
The Chain uh can never fail basically
it's a sort of fail prooof um Handler
okay so now let's have a look at how we
code up the web server class so let's
create the web server
class okay so in here we need to store a
reference to the first Handler in the
chain so let's do that
and we can pass the Handler in the
Constructor okay so let's also provide a
handle
method just like we did before it takes
a
HTTP
request
and we're just going to call
handler. handle
and we pass that request
object okay so now let's actually use
this solution in the
client so let's M get rid of all this
and we can say v v validator equals new
validator let's see I think it should be
this one
yeah and let's also create an
Authenticator
authentic authentic
a sorry having some spelling issues
there and logger equals new
logger okay so now what we can do is if
you remember when I mentioned earlier
that we are returning the Handler from
the uh set next method and because we're
doing that we can just chain everything
together in one line so we can call
validate data now this is going to be
our first object in the chain and we're
going to set next so the next object
needs to be the authenticator so that's
our next step in the
chain and because the set next is
returning a uh
Handler we can just chain on the next
Handler and that is going to be the
logger okay so we can do that all nice
and conveniently in one single line of
code okay so now we can create our
server and we pass the first um Step In
The Chain the first object in the chain
which is validator in our
case and
then let's create a uh HTTP
request and that's not what we
want let's
see I think we actually need to create
this uh HTTP request object inside of
our new uh good solution folder so let's
actually uh let's create this HTTP
request object cuz we forgot to add it
to this new uh good solution folder and
this is actually going to be the same EX
exactly the same as what we had
beforehand so let's copy and paste
everything that we have inside here and
we'll paste it inside of here so
hopefully that fixes the issues that we
had before
and and here we need to provide a
username so first of all let's actually
pass some uh credentials that are
correct so this will pass uh the
validation and authenticator steps so
let's handle this request Now by calling
the server. handle method and we can
pass this request to the uh server
handle method so let's just check what
happens
here and you can see that we validate
authenticate and log so it passes
through all of the steps no problem and
we can return the web page to the user
so this is like a successful request so
let's actually test what happens if we
create create a request with a with an
invalid
password okay so if we give it a correct
username but the password is incorrect
okay so the password needs to be 8123 to
pass and then if we call server. handle
request two let's see what happens
here so let me comment this out just to
make it clearer what's going on with
this new new request so we can see here
that we validate the request no problem
and then we authenticate the request but
because the password is incorrect the uh
chain stops at the authenticating step
and it never reaches the log step okay
so that is working perfectly now let's
see what happens if we
provide an empty username and password
so the user hasn't actually provided any
credentials
as you can see it just goes to the
validating step the validating step
fails because we have two empty strings
and the user is never uh authenticated
that we never get to the authenticate uh
authentication step in the chain so this
is working exactly as we want it
to so here we now have a flexible
solution that makes it very easy to
change the order of processes so as you
can see we can easily change the order
of processes in the client we without
having to modify any code in the web
server class so this is super flexible
and easy to change the order of
processes and it's also easy to add or
remove processes without having to
modify any existing code which satisfies
the open closed principle the visitor
pattern separates the algorithms or
behaviors from the objects on which they
operate so let's say that you are a
developer for a marketing agency that
has different types of clients so they
have restaurants law firms and
retailers so let's code up a quick
solution for this so here I've generated
a client class and this is going to be
like the sort of parent or base class
for each of the different types of
clients and you can see here we are
storing the name of the client and the
contact email of that client so let's go
ahead now and create create the uh Law
client so we can create a new C class
and we're going to call this Law client
and this needs to extend the client
class okay and then we just need to
generate the Constructor uh
Constructor uh to uh satisfy the parent
or base client class and you can see
here we just pass the name and the email
to this client class okay and we can
also create a uh a restaurant client and
a retailer client so let's go ahead and
quickly do that so we have a
restorant
client
and we extend the Base Class generate
the Constructor and we can do the same
for retailer
okay so we now have some very
simple uh client classes that all extend
this base client class which keeps track
of the name and email of the client so
okay so so far everything is just a
plain and simple csharp object there's
nothing interesting going on so far it's
all very very simple straightforward
stuff but your manager comes to you and
says that they need the ability to send
a specialized email with marketing tips
for each of the different types of
clients for example restaurants need
tips on how they can better Market their
food but law firms don't so it seems
like a good idea to add an abstract
method called send email to the base
client class then Implement that method
in each of the concrete clients so in
the uh client class we can create create
an abstract method called send
email so let's go ahead and add that in
okay and we also need to make this class
now
abstract okay and now you can see we
have errors in each of our uh client
classes so we can implement the abstract
class
here and let's just uh copy and paste
this in because it's pretty
straightforward stuff so in our law
clients we have we are overriding this
send email abstract method from clients
and we can just log sending law
marketing tips so specialized marketing
tips uh to the uh email address of this
client okay we can also do the same for
restaurant and
retail so again I'm just going to copy
this in to save a little bit of time
because it's very very straightforward
just logging
uh some basic a basic sentence just to
uh simulate sending an email and we need
to do the same for our retail client as
well so let's implement the abstract
class
and paste that in okay so this all looks
okay so we can now send our
emails uh by using
polymorphism so we can see here I'm
going to paste this into vs code so what
we can do if we go into our program.cs
file which is going to be our
client we can uh create a list of
clients so I just need to import these
classes
now uh let's see here what do we have
going on here
and let's
see okay these should be
uh we need to um add clients onto the
end of these class names okay so
basically what we're doing here here is
sort of simulating getting a list of
clients from a database so let's just
pretend this is some sort of database
query where we get our list of clients
from the database and we have a retail
client a restaurant client and a Law
client and these are are all of type
clients okay so this is a list of
clients okay and the reason for that is
because all of these classes law
restaurant and retail are all extending
this base client class
okay so back into our program now so now
what we want to do is maybe every week
we can schedule to send some sort of
marketing email so what we can do is we
can Loop through each client and we can
actually use polymorphism to send a
specialized email okay so our client
here needs no knowledge of the actual
specific type of client that we're
dealing with because the send email
method is in the base class which all of
these classes are extending uh our our
clients can just call this send email
class and delegate that to the specific
client okay so we're using polymorphism
here we don't need to know the exact
client so this appears to be a nice and
elegant solution because we're using
polymorphism everything looks okay uh
but the manager comes back to us and
says that they need to uh they need a
way to export
clients as PDFs and as XML and you
quickly realize that your manager is
going to keep coming to you and asking
you for more and more features for
clients so following our current design
every time that we want to add new
functionality we have to open up our
code for modification so we have to
modify our base client class and then
actually Implement um any methods uh any
specific methods in the client classes
um so this is not good because this
breaks the open closed principle and we
risk breaking uh working tested code and
we're also violating the single
responsibility Principle as clients are
now responsible for storing clients info
sending emails and exporting clients as
PDFs or
XML and also initially the clients were
just simple plain old C objects they
were very simple objects but adding the
ability to send emails means uh adding
thirdparty Library code into these
classes that calls email clients like
Gmail and Outlook and this can very
easily break our previously working code
so here is the uml for this current
solution we can see that we have our
client with name and email fields and
then we are adding a a send email method
and we have our concrete or our sort of
specific client classes such as retail
restaurant and law which implements any
abstract methods in the client
class so to solve the issues that we saw
previously we need to extract the
behaviors outside of the client classes
on which they operate so if you remember
the visitor pattern separates the
algorithms or behaviors from the objects
on which they operate so so let's
implement the visitor pattern so here is
the uml where we implement the visitor
pattern and we have here an abstract
client class and you can see that we've
removed the send email method from this
class and that will now be in the
concrete email visitor class okay so the
behaviors have been abstracted into the
concrete visitor classes which uh can
then be passed to the objects that they
oper operate on like so so here we can
see that we are looping through uh our
clients and sending an a marketing email
so we can see here we call the client.
accept method and you can see here that
all clients must have an accept method
which accepts some sort of visitor and
here we have an email visitor which is
used to send emails and then within the
uh specific uh sort of client classes so
for example in retail uh we call visitor
dovisit retail and then that deals with
sending a an email specific for uh
retail clients okay so we can see before
that the send email uh logic was
actually on the uh clients themselves
whereas now we've separated the the
behavior from the objects which they
operate
on so if we have a look at the gang of
fourl here we can see it's pretty
similar to what we have up here with a
small difference so we can notice that
design patterns are not super rigid so
for example in our case the element
class is an abstract class and not an
interface and this is because we want to
provide some common fields and some
common methods uh to all of the clients
so in our case we have the name and
email fields and also the get email
method which is common to all clients
that's why we're using an abstract class
and not an interface where we can't uh
sort of store any fields or or actually
Implement any
methods okay so let's now implement this
visitor pattern in code so that it makes
more sense first of all I'm going to
create a new folder inside of the
visitor folder called good and this is
where we're going to put our sort of
better solution that follows the visitor
pan so first of all let's create uh base
client method which will have an accept
method that takes a visitor object so
let's go ahead and create
that and this needs to be an abstract
class and here we're going to have the
same as before we're going to have uh
two Fields one for storing the name of
the client and another for storing the
email of the client and these are going
to be set within the Constructor of this
client class just the same as
before and we're also going to have a
getter for getting the email of the
client okay so this is all similar to
what we had before uh but now rather
than having a uh abstract send email
method we're going to have a an abstract
method called
accept that um that accepts a a type of
visitor okay so let's create that
method so this is going to be a public
abstract void method called accept and
this accepts a visitor
object and the visitor object is going
to contain the
behavior um that will oper and will
operate on a certain uh type of it will
operate on a specific client
object okay so this is uh hard to
understand at the moment so let's keep
on going it will make more sense as we
uh develop the solution further so next
we're going to create our visitor
interface and in here we're going to
create three methods one called visit
retail and this is going to accept a
retail client and we don't actually want
to import this from the previous
solution so let's ignore that for
now okay so let's just um ignore these
errors for now they will go away as we
actually create these clients and we
need one for visit uh
law and we also need a method for
visiting a
restaurant and we need to just rename
this to Law client
and we need to rename this to restaurant
client okay so now we need to create the
specific client classes uh so let's go
ahead and do that so we'll start with
the retail
class and this um retail class needs to
um extend the client base class and then
implement this abstract method which is
the accept
method okay so in here what we're
actually going to do is we're going to
call
visitor
dot visit retail
and I think we also need to implement
the con uh generate the Constructor
that's it okay so I'm not sure what this
problem is
here um oh yeah of course we have to
pass this object to the retail visitor
because the retail visitor is going to
operate on this retail client object
okay so that is the retail client and
now let's go ahead and create the uh
restaurant client
and this is going to extend
client and we also now again need to
implement the abstract methods and also
generate the
Constructor okay so in this accept uh
method we are simply going to call the
correct uh method on the visitor and
here we are visiting a rest restur
client so we need to call visitor
dovisit restaurant and then we pass the
restaurant that we want to visit which
is this object okay so next uh our final
uh specific client class is the law
clients so let's create the Law client
class and again we're going to extend
the client
class and we can implement the abstract
interface and generate the
Constructor and finally we're going to
call visitor dovisit law and pass this
object
okay so this is going to now make more
sense because we're going to now create
our concrete visitor class for sending
uh marketing emails for each specific
type of
client so let's create the email visitor
class
and this is going
to uh implement the visitor
interface okay so and here this is where
we implement the specific methods um uh
and and we have the
Behavior Uh that is now separated from
each of these client uh objects so what
we can do is to send
an email for law
clients we can simply uh
log uh
sending law
marketing
tips email to and then we can get the
email from the Law
client by calling get email so this is
pretty nice and if you can remember so
let me just try and tie this together a
little bit for you now so in the law
clients whenever we call the accept
method uh we pass the visitor uh which
contains the behavior that we want to do
so if we want to send an email we can
say law client. accept pass this email
visitor and then within this method we
are calling visitor. visit law and the
visit law method is implemented inside
of email visitor and it sends a law
marketing tips email to the LW client's
uh email address okay so hopefully it's
starting to make a little bit more sense
for
you okay so in here we want to send a
restaurant uh
marketing tips to email um sorry email
to and then we want to concatenate the
restaurant client's email
and finally for the visit retail I'm
just going to copy and paste this in to
save a little bit of
time sending retail marketing tips email
to retail and this should be retail
client. getet
email okay so that is the whole
solution so let's now use this solution
inside of our program.cs file
so let's actually use the name space for
our good
solution and we can see as before we can
create our list of
clients uh here so we have a retail
client a restaurant client and a Law
client and we have the name of the
clients so deams or Frankie and Benny's
Hamlin Migel for any people that have
seen Bal s and we have our email for
each client our contact email
uh and what we can do now is we can
again Loop through each of our clients
and now remember that the send email
logic is no longer stored on the client
objects themselves we've separated the
behavior which is send an email in this
case from the objects on which they
operate which are each of the unique
specific client objects so now what we
can do is we can say clients
do accept and then inside of this accept
method we can pass any type of visitor
and in our case we want to pass an email
visitor because we want to send an email
to each of the clients so we can pass
the email
visitor and if we now run our
program we can see that we are looping
through each of the clients and sending
them an email uh we send an email uh
retail marketing tips email to deams a
restaurant marketing tips to Frankin
Benny's and a law marketing tips email
to Howard uh Miguel Law Firm so this is
working
perfectly so the let's now take a look
at why this is such a good solution why
the visitor pattern is a good solution
to this problem so let's say that our
manager comes to us asking for new
features
and uh we can now extend our code and we
don't have to modify it beforehand if
our uh manager comes to us and say and
asks uh if we can add some export as PDF
logic then we beforehand we wouldd have
to modify the client class or each of
the individual client classes we would
have to modify our code uh breaking the
open close principle whereas now to um
to add a new functionality such as
export as PDF functionality we can
simply extend our code by creating a new
type of visitor so let's go ahead and
actually create a new visitor to show
you how this works so if we go inside
here and create a new class called PDF
export
visitor and this is going to extend uh
sorry implement the visitor
interface and now here I'm just going to
copy these
uh these logs into here to save some
time so here we just say that we are
exporting a Law client as a PDF and we
can just do the same down here this is
going to be a restur
client and this is going to be a retail
client
oops okay so this is our export as PDF
uh visitor class and then if we want to
export a list of clients as a PDF we can
come back into our program class and
let's say we want to um send an email
and then maybe we want to export as PDF
so let's now uh pass this visitor here
PDF export visitor and I'm just going to
comment this out actually uh so we can
see what's going on a little bit easier
and we can see we export retail clients
as PDF then the restaurant client and
the law clients so this is working
perfectly we didn't have to modify any
of our existing working code we just
extended our code Base by creating a new
PDF export visitor and then we can pass
that to each of the clients so this is
perfect because we are now satisfying
the single responsibility principle and
the open close principle The Interpreter
pattern defines a way to represent and
evaluate sentences in a language by
using an abstract class for Expressions
which concrete subclasses Implement to
interpret specific parts of the
language's grammar so The Interpreter
pattern is probably the most complex and
least used of the gang of for design
patterns and most courses on design
patterns that I've seen don't actually
include this interpreter pattern however
at the beginning of this course I
promised that I'd teach you all 23 gang
of four design patterns so let's give it
a go and after the the example that
we're going to go through I'll also
discuss why this pan is rarely used so
here are some example use cases for The
Interpreter pattern so it's used in
passing and executing SQL queries where
The Interpreter pattern helps to pass
the query syntax and execute it against
a database it's used in calculators or
scientific software that interpret and
evaluate complex mathematical formulas
entered by users it's also used in web
Frameworks that render HTML uh templates
with embedded expressions or directives
so for example templates in web
Frameworks such as laral or Jango and
for example in laral you have the blade
templating language where you can sort
of write your variables within curly
braces it's also uh used in jsx in react
and then that is paused by some parer
and turned into or interpreted into some
sort of HTML
template so let's say that we want to
build a calculator app that takes some
user input string and calculates the
result so here we have a user input
string so we have 1 + 2 * 3 and an
interpreter needs to convert or pass
this input or expression into an
abstract syntax tree or an expression
tree so you can see here that an
expression tree looks something like
this it's kind of like a tree of uh tree
structure of objects so you can see here
1 + 2 * 3 we can't simply just go from
left to right we can't say 1 + 2 and
then times three we've got to respect
Math's uh rules so the BD Mass rules
which mean that we have to perform the
multiplication first and then we have to
add the one so we have to do 2 * 3 and
then add one to that result so 2 * 3 is
6 then we add one to get seven and
that's the result result of this
expression so when we build the ab
abstract syntax
tree um we need to respect bod Mass so
we need to get the order of operations
correct so you can see here we first of
all have an addition expression which
contains two more Expressions okay so
you can see the first expression we do
is the multiplication expression which
is the 2 * 3 so we can see here we do 2
* 3 and then finally we add the one
onto that result so essentially what
we're doing here is we are converting or
passing an input string into a tree of
objects according to the grammar rules
that we specify and in this case the
grammar rules are the sort of maths uh
bod Mass rules so the result of the
expression that we have here can be
found by calling it interpret method so
on this expression tree all Expressions
will have an interpreted method and we
can call this and it will find us the
result of this expression which we know
is seven so we can essentially use The
Interpreter pattern to get from the user
input to create this abstract syntax
tree which can then be interpreted or
evaluated to get the result so here are
the components of The Interpreter
pattern so we have abstract Expressions
which establish the interface for all
Expressions within the L language so the
abstract expression is essentially going
to be an interface which has an
interpret method that all Expressions
will Implement so in our case that all
the Expressions that we have the
concrete expressions are the addition
expression the multiplication expression
and number expressions and all of these
implement this I expression interface
and we'll have an interpret method which
defines how these Expressions should be
interpreted we then have terminal
expressions
which represent the fundamental
components of a language such as numbers
or variables and in this above example
number expression is a terminal
expression or a leaf that represents
integers so you can see here we have
number expression where you pass a
number of some sort and we can pass
either a string or uh an integer in our
case and this can be when you call the
interpret method on a number expression
object it will just return an integer
value directly so in this case if we
pass two as a string it will return two
as an integer and in this case it will
return the integer of three okay so they
um can be interpreted directly basically
these terminal Expressions we then have
non-terminal Expressions which represent
more complex Expressions that are
composed of other expressions using
operators or functions so above the
addition expression and the
multiplication expression are
non-terminal or composite uh composite
Expressions so this means that the
non-terminal expressions are built up of
sub Expressions so you can see here we
have multiplication expression which is
built up of uh multiple Expressions it's
built up of two number expressions and
we can see here the addition expression
is also built built up of two
expressions we have this multiplication
expression and we have this number
expression so you can see here if we
call the interpretate method on a
non-terminal expression then it can't be
directly interpreted because if we look
at this multiplication expression it
first of all has to interpret this
number expression then it has to
interpret this number expression so it
has a left and a right expression if you
will and then it has to multiply these
results together and you can see here
this addition expression first of all
has to evaluate this multiplication
expression which has to evaluate these
number expressions and then once this is
evaluated it has to evaluate this number
expression so non-terminal Expressions
can't be directly interpreted like the
terminal Expressions uh they essentially
have to be
recursively interpreted we have to
recursively keep on calling uh the sub
Expressions interpret method until we
finally get to the um results of the
terminal expressions and then we also
have an interpreter which implements the
logic for interpretation and determines
how to evaluate different types of
Expressions so I'm fully aware right now
that you have no idea what is going on
so we're going to go through an example
and it will definitely help if you try
to code this example out a few times so
first of all we're going to create a
context class that is going to contain
any Global Information needed for
interpretation
so let's create that context class so in
our case for our simple calculator
example we don't currently really need
this context class but say that we
wanted to interpret English language
into Spanish and each Spanish-speaking
country speaks Spanish slightly
differently so this context uh object or
class could contain the country and city
that we are currently located in and it
could also contain the gender of the
person that we are speaking to as that
could also affect the interpretation but
for now we're just going to leave this
as an empty object so next up we need to
create the abstract expression
interface so we're going to call this I
expression and each expression needs to
have an
interpret method where we pass the
context to that method so each
expression will have access to any
context uh data so next up let's create
uh our first concrete Expressions so
first of all we're going to create the
terminal expressions and in our case we
just need one and that is number
expression okay so this needs to
implement the expression
interface okay so it's going to have an
interpret method so in number expression
we need to provide an a number when we
create a number expression so let's
create a number field which is going to
be of type integer and then we can
create a Constructor so we're going to
create a number expression Constructor
which takes in an integer number and we
can assign that to our number field and
what we'll also do is we'll overload The
Constructor so we're actually going to
copy and paste this Constructor down and
and we can also provide a string number
and then what we can do is we can
convert this string number so if
somebody creates a number expression
object and passes a string then we're
just going to convert the string into an
integer before assigning it to the
number field so this just makes this uh
class a little bit more flexible because
we can provide both integers and strings
okay so finally in our interpret method
because this is a terminal expression we
can just return the number okay so
that's very simply what number
expression does okay so next up we can
create our non-terminal expression so
first of all we will create our addition
expression so let's go ahead and create
that and this needs to implement the I
expression into
face okay so if you remember
non-terminal expressions are composite
expressions in other words they are
built up from multiple sub Expressions
so what we need to do here is let's
create two fields of type
expression and we're going to have a
left expression and we're going to have
a right expression so in addition for
example if we have 1 + 2 then the left
expression would be a number expression
where we pass one and the right
where we pass two and then we can
interpret both of those expressions and
then add them together and that's what
we're going to do in our interpret
method but first of all we actually need
to create a a Constructor or some way of
setting these uh left and right
Expressions so let's go ahead and do
that and we can assign the fields in the
Constructor so next up we need to
actually interpret these Expressions so
we're just going to say left do
interpret and we pass in the
context and then we need to
add the right expression interpreted so
again if these are number Expressions
they will just uh interpret to their
integer values and then they will be
added together okay so that's what we
have there so next up let's create
another non-terminal expression which is
the subtraction
expression
so
subtraction
expression and in here again we're going
to have a uh let's see where are we so
let's copy and paste these two fields in
I'm also going to copy in what we have
from addition expression and we're just
going to modify things a little bit so
this needs to be um subtraction
expression so the Constructor we set the
left left and right expressions and then
in interpret rather than adding them
together we are subtracting
them okay so finally we're going to
create a multiplication expression so
again this is going to be very similar
to what we have in the addition and
subtraction okay so again we're going to
have two fields and we're going to set
those expressions inside of the
Constructor so let's see let's copy and
paste that in change the name of the
Constructor and this needs to also imple
in fact we forgot to implement the uh
expression interface here so let's
Implement that in the subtraction
expression and we also need to implement
it here in the uh multiplication
expression and then implement the
interface and then here we're just going
to return the left
expression and and then we're going to
interpret it pass the context and then
we're going to multiply by the right
expression okay so that's everything
that we need for our Expressions so next
we need to create The Interpreter or the
parer class which needs to convert some
input string for example 1 + 2 * 3 and
it needs to convert that into an
abstract syntax tree or an expression
tree and first of all so let's go ahead
ah head first of all and create this
interpreter
class so The Interpreter is going to
hold a reference to the
context okay and it's also going to have
an interpret method which interprets the
expression or builds the uh expression
tree so let's create that method and
it's going to return an
integer in other words the sort of final
result from uh passing the expression so
this needs to take a string an input
string or some expression string you can
call that whatever you want and what
we're going to do is we're going to
build an expression tree so we're going
to create a separate method for building
the expression
tree so we're going to call this build
expression
tree and in here we're going to pass the
expression that we want to build an
expression tree
from and then finally we're just going
to return the expression
tree and we're going to call the
interpret method on that tree and pass
in the
context Okay so that's going to return
an integer value so let's now create
this build expression
tree um method which is going to return
a
expression and it's going to take some
input I'm going to call it input you can
call it expression whatever you
want so this is where things get a bit
more interesting because building a
parer that converts some input strings
such as 1 plus 2 * 3 is actually pretty
complex because we can't just sort of
Traverse this from left to right we have
to perform this 2 * three first and then
add the one so building passes are
complex which I'm going to show you very
shortly and it's very easy to get them
wrong so for Simplicity we're just going
to skip this building an actual parer
for now and we're just going to hardcode
in the expression tree for the input 1
plus uh plus 2 + 3 and of course in the
real world you would need to build an
actual proper parser or download one
from somewhere from some package so
let's actually uh hard code in a few
things here so we're going to say the
input is always going to be 1 + 2 *
and we're then going
to hard code our expression tree so
we'll say expression
tree is equal
to and what we're going to do is we're
going to build an expression tree for
this particular input example so first
of all we have to do uh the addition
expression
and inside of here we need to first of
all do the multiplication expression
which is 2 * 3 so we do a new
multiplication expression
and in
here we can pass in the number
expressions of two and
three and we can pass two in here or it
can be a
string and we do new number expression
three okay and then we also need to then
add this one so we do new number
expression and we say one
okay then from here we can return this
expression
tree okay which is going to be
interpreted in this interpret
method okay so now let's have a look at
how a client would use this
solution okay so let's say that we have
an input
string of 1 + 2 * 3 and in this case it
doesn't actually matter what our input
string is because we've hardcoded the
result in here we've hardcoded the input
and we've hardcoded the result of this
uh input example uh I am going to show
you how to build well I'm going to show
you what an actual parser for this would
look like and how it would build this
expression tree from this input but for
now let's just hard code things in for
Simplicity and for a little bit of
Sanity so we can then create our context
object and we can create our
interpreter and we pass in our context
object okay so let's actually get um the
result from interpreting this input so
we can say
interpreter do
interpret and we can pass our expression
our input
expression and
we can assign this to a
result uh
variable and that's let's actually log
this result to the
console okay so let's log this we should
get seven back because 2 * 3 is 6 + 1 is
seven so let's see what we get and we
will get result equals
7 okay so that is all looking good so
far next up I'm going to show you what
an actual interpreter class would look
like if we needed if we we actually
passed the input string correctly uh
programmatically so let me now show you
what an interpreter class would look
like if it actually passed the input
string into an expression tree and for
Simplicity and a little bit of my own
sanity The Interpreter only handles
addition and subtraction as handling
multiplication division and brackets in
an expression would require quite a bit
more complexity for example 1 + 3 plus
uh sorry 1 + 3 * 4 requires the 3 * 4 to
be executed before adding the one due to
Bod Mass so creating language or grammar
parsers is actually very very difficult
to get right even for this simple parer
that I'm going to show you now it only
actually handles uh addition and
subtraction I've not actually handled
multiplication and division and it's
still fairly complex it still takes
quite a bit of thought to build out and
it's very easy to get wrong so what I'm
actually done here is I've already built
out this second interpreter which
actually passes the input string and
it's exactly the same as The Interpreter
that we built before up until this build
expression tree method where we're
actually now we actually now have an
algorithm to pause the
input okay so we can see here this only
handles addition and subtraction so
first of all what we do is we split the
string into
a list of tokens or an array of tokens
so you can think of tokens as like the
words in a sentence or in our case the
the tokens will be the operands and The
Operators so the operands are these
numbers and The Operators are like the
addition and subtraction signs okay so
we build up a list of tokens by
splitting the string via the spaces we
then create an output queue and uh an
operator stack and this is pretty
complex and Way beond Beyond the scope
of this course to actually go through
what is going on here uh this is a
course on design patterns not on
algorithms but essentially what we're
doing is we're using an algorithm called
the shunting yard algorithm to um change
the sort of format of our expression so
that we can build an expression tree and
you can see here depending on the token
we are creating new expressions of
certain types so here if it's a plus uh
sign then we create we sort of add to
the stack and addition expression and we
add the left and right Expressions that
we need to add okay so it's pretty
complex and I don't want to go through
all of this and it's Way Beyond the
scope of this course but I just wanted
to show you that even for just having a
parer that handles addition and
subtraction it's actually very
complicated and if we if we wanted to
actually account for uh multiplication
and division and brackets then it would
be even more complex so I just wanted to
show you basically that building passes
is extremely difficult to get right and
yeah it's something that you're not
going to be doing too often in your life
as a software developer at least most of
you won't be doing that anyway so let's
actually use this in the client now so
we're going to change the input we can't
do multiplication this one so we're just
going to do uh let's see 2 +
3 uh and then we'll minus
4 and we will add 10 so this should give
us a result of five one so it should be
11 okay that's what we are expecting and
we're now going to use interpreter
2 instead of interpreter one okay so
that should all be okay so let's run
this
and we should get
11 and as you can see we get 11 so
that's all working
correctly so what is actually going on
here so let's sum up what we have so far
so that we can better understand what is
going on here so first of all we have
the client our sort of program.cs file
which initiates the interpretation
process by providing first of all an
input expression to interpret and it
also creates The Interpreter object and
the context object with information that
is needed for the interpretation process
is passed to The Interpreter and in our
case we are not providing any context
data okay so next of all the passing and
building of the abstract syntax tree so
the input expression is turned into an
array of tokens in The Interpreter so if
we go up here we can see we are turning
the input into an array of tokens and
tokens are analogous to words in a
sentence and these are passed via some
algorithm so we have our big algorithm
here um that creates an expression tree
that res represents the input and if we
go into our first interpreter the
expression tree will look something like
this it builds an expression tree that
sort of represents our
input okay so each operator and operand
so the operators being like the
multiplication symbol or the addition
symbol and the operands being the
numbers themselves are each represented
by a corresponding expression object so
the numbers are represented by the
addition expression and the operands are
um represented by the multiplication
expression or the subtraction expression
or the addition expression okay and
they're they're basically built of sub
Expressions okay so let's now have a
look and have a think through the
expression evaluation so we've built our
expression tree from our user input now
we need to interpret this uh expression
tree
okay so the ex The Interpreter so if we
go into this interpret method we first
of all create the expression tree then
we have to interpret it and The
Interpreter traverses the expression
tree and in interprets each individual
expression or node as it goes so for
terminal Expressions the operands or
numbers such as 1 two and three that
interpret methods directly return their
numeric values so if we have a look in
the number expression you can see uh
sorry number expression is just
returning the numeric value and for the
terminal Expressions The Operators such
as plus minus and multiply their
interpret methods call their left and
right sub
expressions and then it it calls these
left and right sub Expressions
recursively and then performs their
respective oper operations so either add
uh subtract or multiply and what we mean
by recursive if we just have a look in
here you can see that um we first of all
have to call this addition expression we
call interpret on this and then from in
here we call interpret on this
multiplication expression and then we
have to interpret this left expression
then the right expression then we
multiply them together and then we have
to interpret this number expression and
then we finally add them together so
we're recursively calling the interpret
method on each of these expressions as
we Traverse the expression
tree okay so then we need to combine the
interpreted results so The Interpreter
combines the results of the sub
Expressions according to the defined
grammar rules that should be represented
by the expression tree and in our
example following bod Mass 2 * 3 should
be performed or evaluated first and then
followed we then follow uh we then add
on the uh the one so that the final
output is then returned to the
client so here is the gang of 4L for The
Interpreter pattern so you can see here
we have our abstract expression
interface with an interpret method that
takes the context object which contains
some sort of data that is relevant to
the in interpretation and then we have
our two groups of Expressions we have
terminal Expressions which basically
kind of return the building blocks or
these kind of
fundamental um sort of words or digits
in our language so in our case that was
just integers and then we have our
non-terminal Expressions which are built
up of sub
Expressions okay so let's now have a
look at some commonly stated
justifications for when to and when not
to use The Interpreter pattern so if you
need to interpret and execute
expressions or commands in a domain
specific language The Interpreter patent
offers a flexible and extensible method
for implementing the languages grammar
and semantics if your task only involves
calculating simple operations that can
be handled by general purpose
programming languages or by a library
then using The Interpreter pan adds a
lot of unnecessary complexity so most of
the time a general purpose programming
language or Library will do the job for
you
and if the grammar of your language is
too com is complex then The Interpreter
pattern could lead to having a large
number of classes and increased code
complexity and in this case a dedicated
parser generator or compiler would be a
better option so now we're going to take
a look at why The Interpreter pattern is
rarely used so Steve yay a software
developer and blogger says that the
ganga 4 book contains 22 patterns and a
practical joke and The Interpreter
pattern is that practical joke so the
problem with The Interpreter pattern is
that you must turn your language into an
abstract syntax tree and as you saw
earlier with our calculator example
creating a parser or an algorithm for
converting some input into an abstract
syntax tree is a very difficult task to
get right and is very timec consuming
and for anything other than the simplest
of languages creating a parser is very
difficult and likely to fail so how did
the gang of four book deal with this
they basically ignored the paring
problem alog together and said that it
was a separate problem to The
Interpreter pattern so I've actually
copied and pasted a paragraph from the
ganga for book about what they say about
this kind of problem so The Interpreter
pattern doesn't explain how to create an
abstract syntax Tree in other words it
doesn't address passing the abstract
syntax tree can be created by a TBL
driven parer by a handcrafted usually
recursive descent parer or directly by
the client but when we use The
Interpreter pattern we have to somehow
generate this abstract syntax tree we
can't just ignore the complex problem of
paing and this is why yay characterized
the chapter as a practical joke and why
other programming techniques and
patterns are almost always preferred to
The Interpreter Pat and in your life as
a software developer most of you will
rarely have to develop your own
languages so the other 22 design
patterns will be of much greater use to
you however there will of course be some
specific good use cases for this pattern
in the real world okay so that's enough
of this pattern we're now going to move
on to structural design
patterns structural design patterns
focus on the composition of classes and
objects to form larger structures and
systems these patterns primarily deal
with how classes and objects can be
combined to form larger more complex
structures while keeping these
structures flexible and efficient the
key objective of structural design
patterns is to provide solutions to
design problems related to object
composition and structure allowing for
better organization and management of
code so structural design patterns help
to achieve several important goals in
software development they promote code
reuse ability and modularity by defining
clear and standardized ways to compose
and organize classes and objects and
this makes the codebase more
maintainable and scalable over time as
changes or additions to the system can
be made more easily they enhance
flexibility and extensibility by
allowing the system structure to evolve
without requiring major changes to
existing code and this is achieved by
decoupling the components of the system
and promoting loose coupling between the
different parts uh and structural design
patterns also improve performance and
resource utilization by optimizing the
way objects interact and collaborate
within the system thereby enhancing
overall system efficiency so overall
these patterns contribute to building
robust adaptable and well organized
software systems that are easier to
understand maintain and extend over time
so let's now learn some structural
design
patterns the composite design pattern is
a structural design pattern that enables
the creation of tree likee structures to
represent collections of objects where
both individual objects and groups of
objects are treated in a unified manner
so to understand what this means let's
create a scenario then code up a simple
naive solution then fix it with the
composite pattern so let's say that we
get an Amazon delivery of a large
package that contains multiple items so
as you can see the boxes can contain
groups of other boxes and items and the
above this diagram shows how a package
of items can be represented as a tree
structure so at the top we have the the
big main Amazon box that you would
receive and then within this box we have
two more smaller boxes and then within
the smaller box we have a microphone so
our first item that we open
and then the second box contains two
smaller boxes and this box contains a
mouse and this box contains a keyboard
okay and you can see that this is
represented as a sort of tree
structure uh so say that we need to find
the total price of the items within any
package so for example the total price
of all the items in this top uh main
package would be the cost of the
microphone plus the mouse plus the
keyboard where the price of the items
within this uh package would be just the
mouse or the keyboard and the total
price within here would be the keyboard
the total price of this package is the
mouse okay so the solution that
naturally pops into the head is to
create an array of boxes and items then
Loop through them recursively to find
the total price of the package so here
is The Simple Solution so we can see
here that we've created a keyboard cloud
class with a price a microphone class
with a price and a mouse class with a
price we can then have a box which is
just a list of any type of object and we
call this
items and within this box class we have
a method for adding an item and we just
add it to the list of items and then we
have a calculate total price class which
um first of all has a field called total
price which we set to zero it Loops
through all of the items in the items
list and it checks what type of object
the item is so if item is a keyboard
then we cast the item to a keyboard uh
object uh which means that we can then
access its price uh field okay then we
have have to do the same for Mouse we
cast it to a mouse and access the price
field on the mouse class add it to total
price and then we do the same for
microphone else if the item is a box
then we cast the item to a box and call
calculate total price so we're calling
this uh method
recursively then we just return the
total price of the uh box so you can see
that this method is ugly
because we're having to check the type
of object and then cast the object to
that type to be able to access its price
field so this is very uh very ugly
solution first of all it's very hard to
read this method is going to already
bloated with just three types of items
so the more items we add it's going to
become even more bloated and if we add
more items or remove items then we have
to modify this class breaking the open
closed principle
so if we use this solution to create the
package demonstrated in the uh previous
tree diagram we can see here that we
first of all create the uh big package
to deliver containing box one and box
two and then box one contains a
microphone box two contains box three
and four uh and then box three contains
a mouse box four contains a keyboard and
then we're just adding the boxes to the
correct box and adding the packages to
the correct boxes and then we can call
calculate total
price so you can see that this solution
calculates total price correctly but it
has some obvious flaws that we have
already discussed so we have lots of
conditionals which is very hard to read
and we're violating the open close
principle because whenever we add a new
item we have to modify the Box
class whenever we have lots of
conditionals that are checking the type
of an object and and casting it to
another object type it's often a good
sign that we need to use polymorphism
and we can use polymorphism by treat uh
by creating an interface called item and
extracting common methods or logic
between the objects into that interface
like so so here we have an item inter
interface with a G price method and we
can see that both box and each of the
product uh objects or classes are EXT
extending this item interface meaning
that they will all have this Gap price
method so a box is essentially composed
of a group of items so you can see here
this is represented by the diamond arrow
and you can see this field here a box is
composed of a group of items uh but a
box is also an item itself represented
by the arrow so a box is simply just a
group of items uh a box and its contents
can be treated the same way as items
thanks to polymorphism so now let's go
ahead and create the code solution okay
so I've created a new folder for our
structural design patterns and in here
I've created a composite folder for this
example so first of all let's create an
interface called
item and items are going to have a
single method uh
called Gap price which returns a
float
and we can now create our specific item
classes so first of all let's create a
keyboard
class and this needs to implement the
item
interface so each class will need to
have a field to store for its price so
let's go ahead and create a private
float called
price and I'm just going to set this uh
for now as a constant in a uh real
application it would be much more
sensible to uh create a Setter method
for this or uh set the price in the
Constructor but for now we're just going
to hardcode a value in for the
price and then within this Gap price
method we need to return the
price okay so let's now create go ahead
and create our other items so we're
going to need to create a
microphone and this needs to extend or
implement the item interface and again
we're going to have
a private float for the price
and again let's just hard code this in
for now and we just return the
price okay let's create our Mouse
class and I'm actually just going to
copy and paste this in to save some time
as it follows the exact same structure
as we have with our keyboard and
microphone
okay so now let's create our box
class and a box remember is just a a
sort of um class that stores a group of
items and a box is also an item itself
so let's implement the item interface
and now box needs to actually have a
field for storing a list of items
okay let's also provide a method uh for
adding items to the
list okay now we need to implement the
Gap price method so what we're going to
do is we're going to Loop through the
items in this items list and we're going
to add it to a total
variable so let's create a float called
total and then we're going to Loop
through each item in the items
list and we're just going to add it to
the
total and here we can call item. get
price
okay and we know that each item is going
to uh have a gap price method because
all items are implementing this item in
uh interface so we no longer need to
check the type of item object we can
just treat them all as items and we here
we basically using polymorphism because
this item um this item object can take
many forms it can be a keyboard it can
be a microphone or it can be just
another box okay so polymorphism is
allowing us to uh giving us a lot of
flexibility here and then at the end we
just need to return this
total so let's now actually uh use this
solution in a in our program.cs file and
what I'm going to do is rather than code
all of this out it's a pretty uh Hefty
bit of code so we're just creating the
uh tree structure that we had beforehand
basically
so what I'm going to do is just copy and
paste this all
in and then let's actually import the
correct name space so it is this
one okay so this all looks okay so just
to remind you of the tree structure that
we are creating here um let's see if I
go over here
so if I just scroll
up so we're essentially creating this
tree structure so we have one big
package that contains two boxes then box
one contains a microphone box two
contains two more uh boxes and then we
have a mouse and a keyboard okay so that
is what we have
there and let's see so let me go back
over here
okay so let's run this file to see what
we
get and I think actually we've messed up
the copy and paste in here so let me
just re copy and paste this in
okay so that should hopefully be
correct and the total price of the
package is $87.99 so if we quickly check
what we have in the packages we have a
keyboard a mouse and a microphone so we
have
40+ 29 which is $
69.99 and then we have a mouse so that's
$87.99 so the total price of the package
has been calculated correctly
okay perfect so you can see that there
has been no change in the way that the
client would actually use this solution
compared to what we had beforehand uh
the biggest change in uh using this uh
solution is that it calculates the price
um is in the way it calculates the price
using the Gap price methods uh because
we can now treat all objects in the Box
uh in the same way as they all implement
the item interface and this means that
we don't need uh conditionals to check
the type of each item and this satisfies
the open close Principle as our code is
open for extension but closed for
modification so we can create a new item
class uh extending our code without
needing to open any existing classes for
modification so here is the gang of
fourl for the composite pattern so you
can see that we have our component
interface at the top and then we have
our composite class so a composite
meaning that it contains uh sort of
multiple components so you can see here
that a a composite has uh some children
or it contains uh some other components
so it has a list of components and then
it has a method for adding components to
the list and it also has an execute
method to execute some sort of logic and
then we have uh our leaves which are are
the sort of individual products
themselves okay so the composite patter
is useful for representing tree
structures for example folders and files
uh and we can see here that a folder is
like a composite it contains either
other folders or individual files and
you can see here this folder contains
two files as well as another folder
which contains three files and the
composite pattern is very useful for
representing these kind of tree
structures and another example is a
graphical editor that allows you to
group shapes together and group groups
of shapes together as well so when you
drag a group all shapes should move
together in the same way so you can see
here we have a group which contains a
circle triangle and another group and
this group contains two groups and this
group contains two squares and this
group contains two circles
okay so you can see that this can be
represented as a tree structure and this
is where you might start thinking that
the composite pattern could be a good
way to uh represent this in code the
adapter pattern is a structural design
pattern that allows incompatible
interfaces between classes to work
together by providing a wrapper that
translates one interface into another so
let's create a scenario that will help
you to understand this pattern and the
pattern use cases so say that we have a
video editing application that allows
users to upload a video and change the
color of the video the application
provides preset color options for the
user to select such as black and white
or midnight purple so as you can see
here we have the original video with
color it then goes through some sort of
black and white algorithm and we finally
get the edited video uh with all of its
color removed in this case uh the video
is made made black and white so the
classes that change the color of the
application are built by us they are
sort of our own uh part of our own code
base our own custom code and these
classes Implement a color interface so
some sort of common interface so that we
can use polymorphism to treat these
classes in uh in the sort of same way so
here's how the application looks so we
just have a sort of BAS
uh basic video class here we have no uh
methods and Fields but let's just
pretend this class uh represents some
sort of video we then have a color
interface which has an apply method and
each apply methods takes a video class
and this is the video that we are going
to work on so we're going to apply a
color to this
video so we then have our sort of con
rete color classes so here we have a
public class called black and white
color which implements the color
interface and therefore has an apply
method which accepts a video to apply
this black and white color too and in a
real application this would be some
complex code to apply a a black and
white color to a video but here we're
just log in applying black and white
color to the
video we also can have other color
uh color classes of course so here we
have a midnight color which implements
color and has an apply method uh which
takes a video that we can apply the
color
to we then have our video editor class
which take which has a video field and
we pass a video to this video editor via
the uh Constructor and we then have a
method called apply Color which takes
some sort of color object and then calls
color. apply and passes the video that
we want to apply the color to okay so
using this solution in a client we first
create a video editor by calling new
video editor we pass the video editor a
video that we want to edit and we then
call video editor. apply Color and we
can pass any color object that we want
to apply to the video so in this case we
are applying black and white color to
the
video so this is all looking good so far
uh but we then decide to install a
thirdparty library into our into our
application that allows users to apply
more types of colors to their videos so
more complex uh color options uh to the
videos so the problem is that all of the
concrete color classes are expected to
implement our custom color interface and
have an apply method but the concrete
color classes from the installed Library
don't uh implement this color interface
meaning that we can't pass them to our
video editor. apply Color method like
this so you can see here that this
rainbow class is a color class from the
installed third party library and we
don't have access to this code and you
can see here we can't just pass it to
this apply Color method because this is
expecting an object which implements our
color interface and of course this third
party class doesn't Implement our third
our Uh custom color
interface so as mentioned we cannot
modify the thirdparty library code to
make the color classes Implement our
color interface so how do we solve this
so we can solve this by converting the
interface of the thirdparty color
classes to a different form using the
adapter
pattern so so far we can't use this
third party rainbow class because it
doesn't Implement our color interface
and we can't make it Implement color
because it's inside of a thirdparty
package so here's the sort of situation
drawn out in your uml where we have a
video editor with an apply app color
method where we can apply some sort of
color uh so any color that implements
this color interface and we have our own
sort of custom color classes such as
midnight purple and black and white
which implement this color interface we
then have our sort of third party uh uh
color classes such as
rainbow and these have some sort of
update method which um needs to receive
a video
however we can't uh pass these to the
apply Color method because they don't
Implement our color interface so let's
take a look at how we can solve this
issue so we can create a rainbow color
class that implements color and is
composed of the third party rainbow
class we can then call the apply method
in rainbow color and inside the apply
method call whatever methods that we
need to call from Rainbow to apply the
filter so we essentially adapt the class
to a different form so let's explain
that again so here we have our video
editor so again we just as before
nothing different here we apply a color
and pass it some sort of color so any
object that implements this color
interface and this color interface has
an apply method which accepts a
video so now this is the new class that
we've created we've created this rainbow
color class this is our own custom class
which um implements color has of course
an apply method which takes a video and
then within the apply method we can
actually call the Rainbow class or the
rainbow object do update and then pass
the video and this rainbow color class
that we've created is composed of so it
has a field of type rainbow
so essentially we've adapted this third
party rainbow class into a different
form we've adapted it into a a
color um object okay so rainbow color uh
this class that we've created is the
adapter it's converting the interface of
the rainbow class so the
adapter into a different form and that
form is color so let's now implement M
this in
code okay so just a quick reminder of
what we have so far so we have a video
class um which is just a class that
represents some sort of video we then
have a color interface which describes
what a color class or a concrete color
class should look like and me and all
colors should have an apply method that
accept a video object we then have our
concrete color classes such as black and
white color which implement the color
interface have an apply method that
takes a video then the uh apply method
applies the color to the Past video and
midnight color is also a uh concrete
color uh similar to black and white
color that implements the color
interface we then have our video editor
class which has a field which stores a
video to edit with pass the video via
the Constructor and we have a method
called apply Color where we can pass a
color that we want to apply to the
video so that's what we have so far so
let's now um create the video class um
from the third party Library so I'm just
going to create um let's actually create
a folder so this is kind of uh going to
represent a third party Library so I'm
just going to call this package and in
here I'm going to create a uh rainbow
class okay so let's say that um let's
say that colors from this third party
Library require some sort of setup so we
have to call a setup method before we
can actually use the color okay and uh
maybe this would be uh some sort of
method that we could pass some
configuration options such as I don't
know the brightness of the color or I
don't know anything like related to um
uh the color of a video but we're just
going to leave this as a simple method
called setup and I'm just going to log
setting up rainbow
filter okay and then I'm also going to
create a method called
update and this is going to be basically
the a similar s of um method to our
apply method so we're currently calling
the method apply the third party library
is going to call the method update okay
and this takes a
video and it applies the uh the color to
the video so I'm just going to say
applying uh
rainbow uh filter to
video okay so this sort of represents uh
what our third party rainbow color class
looks like and currently we can't use
this because it doesn't implement the
color interface so what we can now do is
we can create an adapter class that
adapts this rainbow class to use our
color interface so that it can be used
by our video editor class without having
to modify this source code okay so let's
create a rainbow color class and the
rainbow color class is one of our our
own classes it's not part of this sort
of installed package so inside of the
adapter
folder we're going to create a class
called rainbow
color and this is going to implement our
color
interface and if you're a member from
the uml we need to uh store uh a or uh
store a field of type rainbow
and this is composition so rainbow color
is composed of or has a rainbow
object so let's also create a
Constructor and we can pass the rainbow
object in
here okay and then in our our apply
method we can actually um uh interact
with our sort of third party rainbow uh
object now so we can call Rainbow do
setup so this is something that the
third party Library requires us to do so
we call setup and then once we've set up
the uh rainbow uh object we can call the
update method and pass the
video so now we have a rainbow color
class which implements color that we can
uh now pass to our our video editor uh
apply Color method and use this uh
rainbow color now as we would any other
of our color classes
so uh we can now apply rainbow color to
our videos just like the other colors so
let's now go into our program.cs file
and let's see if we can apply a rainbow
color so let's call this rainbow
color and inside of rainbow color we
need to pass the uh
rainbow um uh
object so let's
see and this is part of the third party
package so there we go so now we can
apply our rainbow color just like we
would our um just like we would our um
custom
colors so you can see here that rainbow
color is a
wrapper that translates one interface
into another so now to use any other
color from this third party Library we
can create a new rapper or adapter class
to make it compatible with video editor
satisfying the open closed principle so
we actually created our adapter via
composition so you can see here our
rainbow color adapter class is composed
of a rainbow object and this is our
third party color that we have adapted
into an object of type color so um we
can also use uh inheritance to create
our adapter classes so let me show you
how we can use inheritance instead of
composition to create an adapter class
so let's create a new class called
rainbow adapter
and what we're going to do here is we're
going to inherit from the third party
rainbow class and we're also going to
implement the color interface so let's
Implement that by pressing uh command
and Dot and implement the
interface uh so what we can do here is
let's just have a look what we did
before so we can see here because
rainbow color our sort of previous
rainbow adapter is composed of rainbow
we have to call the methods on this
rainbow object that we passed into
rainbow color whereas here we can call
the methods directly because they've
been inherited uh by the rainbow class
because you can see here this third
party rainbow class has a setup method
and an update method and we are
inheriting them so we can just call them
Direct L like
this okay so this does exactly the same
as what our rainbow color adapter uh
did so these do these adapters both do
the same thing but one's using
inheritance and one is using
composition so with inheritance the
rainbow methods can be called directly
now the problem with this inheritance
approach is that it's not as flexible as
using composition because in
C A Class can only extend one class and
in this case the rainbow adapter is
extending this rainbow
class and in this case this is okay it's
okay to use inheritance here because uh
color is an interface but you can see
that inheritance is less flexible than
composition uh and therefore uh
composition should be preferred and that
is because um if color wasn't an
interface and and it was some sort of
class that we'd need to extend then you
can see that c would give us an error
because this rainbow adapter would then
need to extend two classes which is not
allowed in C so as you can see
composition gives us more
flexibility than inheritance and
therefore should be prefer the preferred
option the bridge pattern is is a design
pattern that separates a large class or
a set of related classes into two
separate hierarchies so that they can be
developed independently from each other
so say that we have a remote for
controlling radios and there are
multiple different brands of radio and
there are multiple different types of
remotes so in this diagram we have an
abstract class for what a remote should
look like and then uh extending remote
or inheriting from remote is is the LG
remote and the Sony remote and LG and
Sony are different brands of radium and
then we have another different type of
remote called Advanced remote which
extends or inherits from this remote
class and underneath here we can see
that we have an advanced LG remote and
an advanced Sony remote we then have
another different type of remote called
a mega remote which will have uh some
additional function functionality that
extends from remote and then we can see
that we have the brands LG and Sony for
um the mega remote so here we can see
that every time that we add a new brand
for example Samsung we'd have to create
three new classes so we'd have to create
Samsung remote Advanced Samsung remote
and mega Samsung remote and if we create
a new type of remote for example radio
and TV remote for controlling both a
radio and the TV then we'd have to
create a new class for every uh brand of
radio so we'd need to create a radio and
TV LG radio and TV Sony and radio and TV
Samsung so you can uh very easily see
that this is not a maintainable solution
so let's have a look at how this looks
in code we have our base remote control
class which is an abstract class with
four methods for controlling a radio so
we have a method for turning the radio
on turning it off uh for turning the
volume up and turning the volume down so
let's now create our Advanced remote
abstract
class and this is going to extend the
remote control
class and as you can see we're getting
an error here uh because it's not
implementing the inherited abstract
methods from remote remote control but
we can solve that by making this an
abstract class and now we're just going
to add a an extra method called set
channel which takes an integer of the
channel number that we want to set the
radio to okay so this is now our
Advanced remote with one extra bit of
functionality uh let's now create our uh
radio and TV remote so this is another
type of remote
control that can control control both a
radio and
TV so let's call this um let's
see yeah sorry radio and TV
remote okay and this needs to again
extend or inherit from remote control
and this needs to be an abstract class
okay so then what we're going to do is
we're going to add a couple of extra
methods uh in here and we're going to
have a control TV and a control radio
method so we can select which device we
want to control so if we uh call this
method we're controlling the TV if we
call the control radio method then we
will control the
radio so now what we're going to do is
we're going to implement these remote
control types uh for LG devices so the
LG brand okay so we're not going to
implement them for all of the brand
types because that will take way too
long so for brevity we will just
Implement these remotes for LG devices
for now and not worry about uh Sony or
Samsung so what we will do is we will
create the basic LG remote
and this needs to inherit from remote
control we then need to implement this
abstract class with all of these methods
and to save a little bit of time I'm
just going to copy and paste these in
for now to save some time so let's
see okay so I'm just logging the um some
different stuff here so if we call turn
on we just say turning ALG radio
off and we also need to add the volume
up uh
method okay so we're now implementing
all of the abstract methods from remote
control so now let's create our Advanced
LG
remote and this is going to
uh inherit or extend the advanced L um
Advanced remote class and then again I'm
just going to copy and paste to save us
some time here because it's all very
basic stuff we just need to implement
all of the methods from Advanced remote
control so it's all the same as the
regular ALG uh remote but we also have
this additional set channel
method and finally let's create the alga
radio and TV remote so let's create
that and this needs to inherit from
radio and TV
remote and we can then implement the
methods so we have control
radio and we
have all of the methods that we had
before okay so we just have an
additional two methods here for
controlling the radio or controlling the
TV okay then we can use this solution in
a
client so if we go to our program.cs
file
and let's empty this
out so first of all let's create a LG
remote and let's just uh turn the uh
radio
on and then turn the radio off
okay that's all working correctly and
then if we create an ALG radio and TV
remote okay so this needs to be ALG
radio and TV
remote and then we can control the TV
and turn it on and then turn the volume
up okay so we control the TV now
controlling lgtv we turn the um TV on
and then we turn the volume up so let's
check that all check that that is
working
correctly okay so that's solution is all
working correctly however this solution
is very inflexible because every time we
add a new remote type we need to create
a new class for every brand of TV and
every time we add a new brand we need to
create a new class for every remote type
and the reason that we ended up with
this structure is because our hierarchy
is growing in two Dimensions so we have
the abstract Dimension or the remote
type and an implementation Dimension
which is the
brand of the
device so we saw before that we have a
structure that is growing in two
Dimensions both the remote type and the
brand Dimension so to simplify this
hierarchy we can break it down into two
separate hierarchies so here we have a
sort of remote type hierarchy on the
left and on the right we have a sort of
device or brand hierarchy so you can see
that these uh two hierarchies are
connected via a bridge so you can see
here that remote control is actually
composed of a uh some sort of device and
it talks to each device via the device
interface so you can see here the remote
control has a turn on method and within
this turn on method it just calls the
device. turnon so it uses polymorphism
to turn on the device and it doesn't
require any knowledge of the specific
device that it is turning on because
it's coded to this device
interface okay so whenever we have an
hierarchy growing in two separate
Dimensions we need to split them in half
and connect to them using a bridge so
that the two hierarchies can then grow
independently from each other uh meaning
that we don't have to create a subass
for every combined remote type and brand
so let's now implement this solution in
code so that it makes more sense okay so
first of all we're going to create our
device
interface and this is going to contain
uh three methods we're going to have
turn on turn off and set
channel and the device
interface uh defines all of the methods
that a device should have and currently
we're just going to have these three
methods we're not going to worry about
any other method such as turning the
volume up or turning the volume down
we're just going to keep it simple for
now so next up we're going to create our
remote control class this is like our
base remote control
class and remote control needs to be
composed of a device so we're going to
say private
device
device and then we're going to pass a
device into this remote control Class
via the
Constructor okay so now we can Define
what a basic remote control should do so
a basic remote control uh just like
beforehand if we go into our remote
control on before uh um a base remote
control can turn a radio on or it can
turn a radio off uh we're not going to
worry about volume up and down for now
just to uh keep things a little bit more
simple and short so let's um
create uh first of all the turn on
method and in here we can just call
device. turn on because we know that all
devices will have a turn on method
uh we can
then create a turnoff
method and simply call device.
turnoff okay so this doesn't matter what
the brand of device is whether it's LG
Sony or Samsung because it's coded to
this device interface uh we can just
simply call these methods on the device
without checking what the brand of um
devices okay so we're using polymorphism
here which makes our solution nice and
flexible okay so let's just leave it as
that for now keep things simple so let's
now also create our Advanced remote
control
class uh let's see
and this needs to inherit from our base
remote
control and uh this should
be uh we need to generate the
Constructor and pass the device up to
our base remote control
class okay so the advanced remote is
going to do everything that a remote
control uh can do so it's going to
inherit our turn on and turnoff methods
but an advanced remote can also set the
channel so let's add a set channel
method okay so you can see that an
advanced remote can do everything a
remote control can do but it can also
set a channel um uh by passing an in
integer of the channel number okay so
let's now go ahead and create our uh
device um our devices our sort of
concrete devices so first of all we're
going to create an LG radio device so
we're going to call this LG radio and
this is going to implement the device
interface so let's inter Implement all
of those methods and you can see
here that in LG radio we need to
implement all methods from device and it
doesn't matter we're not actually
worrying about whether this is going to
be an advanced uh device or a regular
base sort sort of remote uh the remote
type isn't is no longer related to the
device we control the sort of
limitations of what we can do Within
These remote control classes so in
remote control we can uh specify that if
we have a remote control we can only
turn on or turn off the device whereas
if you have an advanced remote control
you can turn on turn off and also set
the channel uh and Within These LG
Within These concrete device classes we
just Implement all of the methods
possible for any different type of
remote so now what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to copy and paste these
methods in to save some time because all
we're doing is well we're doing exactly
as what uh uh as what we did previously
so we're just logging a few things out
when we call these
methods so let's also create a Sony
radio
now so phy radio
device and again this is going to
implement
device and I'm just going to copy and
paste these in to save some
time okay so you can see that Sony
devices can be turned off on turned off
and we can also set the
channel okay so now let's have a look at
how a client would use this solution so
you can see previously if we wanted to
uh control an LG
radio uh with and with a radio radio and
TV remote we had to create this very
specific uh subass uh so this solution
is going to be a lot different so let's
actually create an LG remote
control in fact let me just comment this
out so you can see the sort of
differences a little bit more clearly so
first let's create an LG remote control
and this should
be a structural
dot bridge. good
okay so a remote control you need to uh
pass the device uh that we want to
control so the brand of device that we
want to control is an alga radio so
we're going to pass an algae radio into
here and now if we call alga remote
control dot turn
on and we can also turn the device
off so let's actually run this
program and you can see that that works
correctly so now we can see that we have
two separate hierarchy is we have the
remote type which is separate from the
brand or device type okay whereas
beforehand we were sort of combining
them into subclasses here we have an LG
sort of radio and TV remote so radio and
T TV remote is the remote type and LG is
the brand whereas now we are uh creating
a new remote control object so the
remote type we specify here and then we
pass the device that we want to control
Okay so we've separated the two
hierarchies and we've connected them
using this bridge this device
Bridge Okay so let's also now have a
look at how we could create an advanced
uh Sony remote control so uh let's do
that so here we specify Advanced remote
we're not saying Sony Advanced remote
and then to make uh this an advanced
Sony remote we just pass uh the Sony
radio device or the sort of brand that
we want to control and then we can
pretty much do what we did
before so we can turn
on we can turn
off and we can
also let's see set the channel to some
channel uh number so if we run
this we can see that that is all working
correctly so now as remote
control uh our remote control class is
now
delegating okay you can see here it's
delegating the work to the device via
the bridge and uh and the bridge is is
is using is basically composition so the
device hierarchy and the remote type
hierarchy can now grow independently
from each other so now if we add a new
brand of radio we only need to create
one new class so our code is now more
flexible and easier to maintain the
proxy pattern is a structural design
pattern that provides a proxy or agent
object to control access to another
object allowing for a add functionality
such as caching logging lazy loading or
access control without changing the
client's code so you can see here we
have some sort of client object which is
trying to reach a Target object but it
has to go through this proxy object
before getting to the Target so you can
see that this proxy is like a sort of in
between object so let's say that we have
an application that fetches a list of
YouTube videos from YouTube's API and
displays those videos in a list in our
application we are using a thirdparty
YouTube package to handle fetching the
YouTube videos from the YouTube API and
then we render the video on the screen
with the video controls so the problem
is that every time a request is made to
our application our server has to
redownload the videos from the YouTube
API and this takes a long time
especially if lots of requests are made
to our application at one time so here
is the interface for what a video object
would look like from our third party
video library from YouTube so this is an
interface called video and we have a
render method as well as a get video ID
which Returns the string ID of the video
and we also have in this third party
package a YouTube video class which is
is a class again from the third party
YouTube Library which um essentially
creates YouTube video objects by
fetching the video from the YouTube API
via its video ID uh so in the
Constructor you can see here that we
pass the video ID that we want to fetch
from the YouTube API and then the video
starts to download So as you can see
whenever we create a new YouTube video
object it downloads the whole video as
you can see here we just log downloading
video with ID video ID from the YouTube
API and then we also have a render
method for rendering the video onto the
uh UI and we also have a method for
getting the video
ID okay so that is
basically the uh sort of third party
package that we would be dealing with
for YouTube uh so let's actually now
create the code that would be uh part of
our source code so we're going to create
a class called video
list and this is outside of the YouTube
third party package this is our own uh
sort of custom code
now and we're going to have a
dictionary um to store a list of videos
and then we're going to have an add
method for uh adding a video to this
list and this should be
video. getet video ID so it looks like
I've imported the wrong type of video
here so let me import the correct
one so it should be from proxy bad
example and the third party
package okay so now we should be able to
get the you the uh ID there we
go and we're going to pass in the
video okay so as you can see this
dictionary has a key uh a string key and
the string key is going to be the video
ID and the value for that key is going
to be the actual video object
itself so next thing we want to do is
we're going to create a method called
watch and this is going to take a video
ID it's going to get the video from the
video
list and we can do that by accessing the
uh video ID value so we're getting the
video at this
key and we can then call video.
render okay so that's everything we need
to do in our video list so we store a
list of videos with a string uh key
which is the video ID and then we store
the value as the actual video object
itself so let's now take a look at how
we could use this solution in side of a
client so first of all let's create a
video
list and then let's create a uh sort of
list of video IDs
and let's call this video
IDs okay so just some random strings
there and then let's Loop through these
uh video IDs and add them to our video
list
okay so here we Loop through all of our
video IDs and for each ID we are adding
to our video list a new YouTube video
and we pass the video ID to the YouTube
video class and if you remember this
class will download the YouTube video
whenever we create this YouTube video
object so it automatically
downloads
okay so then what we can do is let's
actually uh watch a video so let's say
we want to watch the video with ID AB
CDE e so we can say video list
doat and we can pass the ID of the video
that we want to watch so let's run this
now to check that it's all working
correctly and we can see that uh we are
downloading all of these videos so uh 1
2 3 4 a bcde e and Java SC c123 all been
downloaded and then we render the video
with ID AB CDE e so this one is ready to
watch on the
screen okay so just adding a video to
our video list causes that whole video
to be downloaded so even if the user
doesn't want to watch that video it's
still going to be downloaded and the
user uh here uh the user here only wants
to watch the video with ID a b CDE e so
it will be much more efficient to
download the video only after the user
has selected a video from the video list
and this is called lazy loading or
delaying the loading of something for
when it's actually required so the
problem is that our YouTube video class
is from a third party Library so we're
unable to modify its source code so the
solution to this is to use a proxy
object which we create ourselves so you
can see here that the video list our
video list is no longer going to be
talking directly to these third party uh
YouTube video objects instead it's going
to be talking to these Video Proxy
objects which we are going to create and
these Video Proxy objects are going to
Lazy load these uh YouTube video objects
so here is the uml for the solution that
we are going to come up with so as you
can see our video list objects will now
talk to Video Proxy
objects instead of these third party
video objects and this uml shows that
our Video Proxy object will
implement the third party libraries
video interface which is this interface
here so this comes from our third party
package and this means that we can add
these Video Proxy objects to our video
list and video list won't care whether
it's a third party video or a Video
Proxy as long as it is of type video so
so you can see here that Video Proxy
which we're going to create and the
third party YouTube video class both uh
implement this thirdparty uh video
interface meaning that they can be
treated the same in our video list so
now in inside of our video list we can
add Video Proxy objects instead of our
third party YouTube video objects which
gives us some control over when the uh
video is downloaded so uh inside of the
render method of a Video Proxy object we
can see here we can check if the video
field is equal to null and if it is we
then create a new YouTube video and then
render the video so now uh a third party
YouTube video is only going to be
created when the render method is called
which means that when the user actually
wants to watch the video so no videos
are going to be downloaded until the you
uh the user actually wants to watch
them so here is the gang of 4 uml for
the proxy pattern and as you can see we
have our client which is talking to a
subject and we have a real subject and
our proxy object and you can see that uh
the proxy object uh both uh implements
the subject just like the real subject
does meaning that it can be treated the
same as the real subject in our clients
but but it means that we can also run
some custom code uh before we call the
real subjects request method and some
things that we might want to do or lazy
load or
cash and or uh log some information
before we call this request method on
the real subject so let's now implement
this proxy patent solution in code so
the first thing that we're going to do
is we are going to create our YouTube
video proxy class so we're going to come
into uh we're not going to make this
inside of the package by the way because
this is our own uh code whereas this
package remember is our third party
Library code that we wouldn't actually
have access to in a real application so
let's go ahead and create the YouTube
video proxy class
and uh this class needs to uh implement
the video interface from our thirdparty
library so we have a lot of videos here
so I believe it could be any one of
these let's try this one
and okay is this
correct okay I think that's correct so
yeah we are implementing the video class
from our third party YouTube package and
then we need to actually implement the
interface okay
so inside of this class we need a couple
of
fields so first of all we need a a video
ID
field and we also need a field for
storing a reference to the actual
YouTube YouTu video and this is going to
be of type YouTube
video from our third party
Library so I've been a little bit
inconsistent here with uh capitalizing
the t's but it'll be okay so let's now
create a Constructor so we can pass in
the video ID for the video that we want
to download and watch so we're going to
create a public Constructor called
YouTube video proxy and we're going to
pass in the video
ID okay we're not passing in a
video okay so now what we need to do is
let's actually
uh return the video ID here
and then Implement our render method so
inside of render we want to actually
lazy load the YouTube video so if I just
quickly show you what a YouTube video
looks like from our third party Library
you can see that the YouTube video is
downloaded as soon as we create one of
these YouTube video objects and we want
to Lazy load the video so you can see
here when whenever we create a YouTube
video proxy we just pass the video ID
and we don't actually create one of
these YouTube video objects because if
we do it's going to download the video
and we only want to download the video
once this render method is called which
means that when the user uh clicks on
the video to actually watch the
video so what we can do here is we can
check to see if the YouTube video is
equal to null so let's check if video
equals
null and if it does we can then set
YouTube video equal to a new new YouTube
video and in here we pass the video ID
that we want to
watch okay so this means that if the
render method is called multiple times
then it's still only going to download
the YouTube video once it's only going
to create uh this new YouTube video one
time uh because once this has already
been called YouTube video will no longer
be null Okay so uh finally we can call
YouTube
video.
render okay and that's going to render
the YouTube video so we are now lazy
loading YouTube videos with this YouTube
video
proxy so now that we have these Video
Proxy objects that Implement video we
can now in our in our clients we can add
these proxy objects in place of the real
YouTube video class so here we are
adding YouTube videos but instead what
we can do now is add YouTube video proxy
objects instead so let's do
that and what we want to do now is get
rid of our
previous uh example
code okay so this all looks okay so
that's all we've done we've just changed
this from YouTube video to YouTube video
proxy and our video list doesn't care
whe whether we had YouTube video proxies
or whether we had real YouTube videos
because as far as the video list is
concerned they both implement the third
party video interface and it can treat
them uh as the same using polymorphism
so now let's see what
happens okay so when we watch the video
we can see that the video is downloaded
from the YouTube API and the video is
rendered but if I comment this app
out let's see what
happens so you can see nothing is logged
to the console when we add videos to the
list whereas beforehand if you remember
uh let's actually show you what happened
beforehand so YouTube
video and let's play this run this you
can see that even before the so even if
the user doesn't click on one of these
videos to watch them whenever we add
them to the list or create one of these
new YouTube videos the video had to be
downloaded from the YouTube API so this
would take potentially quite a long time
whereas Now using the uh V YouTube video
proxy you can see that no videos are
actually downloaded until one of those
videos is clicked on or the user wants
to actually watch one so the video that
we want that the videos are now laid
easy loaded so the only video that is
actually downloaded is this ABCDE e
video uh because the user actually wants
to watch that one the flyweight pattern
is a structural design pattern that aims
to minimize memory usage by sharing
common state between multiple objects
allowing for efficient handling of large
numbers of lightweight objects with
shared characteristics so say that we
have a farming game that includes
different types of crops such as
potatoes carrots and and wheat and each
crop is represented by a crop object
that includes it its X and Y coordinates
the crop type and an icon for that crop
so here is the uml with its x uh x-axis
position y AIS the type of the crop and
an icon and the crop type you can see
here is an enum which will have type of
either potato carrot or wheat in our
example and we have an icon and icons
can can be represented by an array of
bytes okay so here we have our crop type
enom which can take the value of either
a potato a carrot or wheat so these are
the these are the three crop types that
we have in our game so let's now go
ahead and create the crop
class and a crop has a position on the
screen so an x and y
coordinate it also has a crop type
field and it also has an icon which we
can represent as an array of
bytes okay so let's now create a
Constructor for this crop class
this needs to be of type crop type and
then we can set the
values set the
fields and finally this crop class needs
a render method for uh rendering the
crop onto the
screen so I'm just going to
log drawing the crop type
at the
position of X and
Y okay so that's everything we need to
do for this crop uh class so let's now
create a crop service
class which is essentially going to be
used to fetch our
crops and the are going to be stored in
probably uh some database okay so let's
create a method called get
crops and this is going to return a list
of crop
objects okay so let's first of all uh
create a crop list
and then let's uh simulate fetching our
crops from a
database so here what we can
do is we can create some uh crops so I'm
going to say V carrat equals new
crop and we can say it can be at
position one four
and it can be a crop type of
carrot and I'm just going to pass null
for the icon uh just for convenience
rather than creating uh an actual array
of
bites so let's also create a few more
carrots so let's just call this carrot 2
and carrot three and let's just change
uh the position that it will be rendered
on on the
screen okay so that will do so that's
kind of like simulating uh fetching our
crops from a
database so next thing we can do is we
can add these crops to this crop list so
we can call Crop list dot add and then
we can add a carrot and then we can also
add carrot 2 and carrot
three and then we can return earn this
crop
list okay so you can see this kind of
crop Service uh get crops method is just
sort of simulating what we would do in a
real application which is probably fetch
the crops from the database and then
return the sort of list of crops and
each crop knows its position that it
should be rendered its type of crop and
also the um icon for that crop type
okay so using this solution in a client
now so if we go into our program.cs file
we can first of all create a crop
service and we can then Loop through our
crops and render them on the screen so
we can say V crop in crop
service doget
crops and then we can just call CR crop
dot uh oops sorry that should be
crop dot
render okay so now if we run this
program we can see that we are drawing
all of our carrots at the correct
position on the
screen so the problem with this solution
is that for every carrot or crop that we
create we are storing a new object with
all of the information about a carrot
stored within that object so this means
that if we create 1,000 carats then
we'll be storing 1,000 karat icons in
Ram and that's going to take up lots of
memory and many mobile devices will
struggle to handle that so if we
actually have a look at the uh crop uh
object uh we can see that this takes up
uh four bytes so integers take up four
bytes this is 4
bytes the crop type is also uh 4
bytes and the icon will be around 40
kilobytes so if we if we actually create
a new icon for every single crop that we
create if we have say a th crops in the
game that will be 1,000 * 40
kilobytes which is uh uh 40 uh megabytes
for 1,000
crops and that is a lot of RAM for um
smaller devices such as mobile phones
and the game may slow down lag or crash
so this is not
ideal
so so what if we could share icons
between crop objects of the same type so
if we have say three 100 carrot objects
what if all of those carrot objects
could share one single uh carrot icon
rather than creating uh 300 of the same
icons so if a carrot is created with the
crop class then its icon and crop type
Fields will remain constant for the
lifetime of the object but its X and
y-coordinates will vary as the crop can
be harvested and moved around so State
That Remains the Same throughout the
object's life is called the internal
state of the object and state that can
be changed is called extrinsic state so
you can see within our crop object the X
and Y coordinates are dynamic they can
change throughout the crop's life cycle
so these are called extrinsic
State and the crop type and the icon are
constant throughout the crops life cycle
so a a carot is never going to become a
potato and a carrot is also never going
to look like a potato so this is
constant therefore we call it the
intrinsic state of the object so if we
can extract the intrinsic or constant
state out of this crop object or crop
class and place it into a new object
called crop icon then we would only need
to create three crop icon objects for
potato carrot and wheat TW in our
application even if there are thousands
of crops in the game we only need to
create three of these crop icon objects
and this is going to save a lot of
memory so we can then for example just
have one carrat icon object stored in
memory then all crops of type carrot can
reference or reuse that carrot icon
object throughout the game so you can
see here we have a crop with its X and
and Y uh Dynamic uh fields and it's
composed of a crop icon object and only
one of these crop icon objects are going
to be created per crop type so uh
carrots or are going to all share a
single crop icon uh object for carrots
and potatoes will also share a single
crop icon object for potatoes Etc so an
object again an object that contains
only intrinsic State uh is actually
called a flyweight
object okay so let's just remind
ourselves the intrinsic state is the
constant state and you can see here an
object that contains only intrinsic
state is called a flight weight so this
crop icon object is going to be our
flyweight object but it should be
noticed that we shouldn't create crop
icon objects directly so we can create a
factory class that creates creates an
icon depending on the icon type and
caches that icon in memory ensuring that
it's only stored in one place and
ensuring that it's only created once so
here is the overall structure following
the flyweight pattern so we have our
crop with its extrinsic State we have
our crop icon with the um with the
intrinsic state so the um the uh con
States we then have a crop icon Factory
which is essentially going to ensure
that crop icons are only created once
per crop type and stored in a single
place in memory and then we have our
crop service which is going to sort of
simulate getting our crops from the
database and creating a list of crop
icons so here is the gang of four
representation for the flyweight pattern
we can see that we have our flyweight
object with some sort of repeating
State we then have our flyweight Factory
which caches flyweight objects ensuring
that they are only created once and then
we then have our
context uh which in our case is like our
crop
object with its unique state or its
Dynamic State that's going to change it
stores a reference to the flyweight
object and and we then have some
operation so Flyway do operation uh with
its unique
State okay so let's now implement this
flyweight pattern for our uh farming
game so we are now going to refactor our
code to follow the flyweight pattern and
we're going to basically store these uh
Fields inside of a separate class so
that it can be cached in memory and we
don't have to create multiple icons for
the same crop so we still have our crop
type enum so nothing's going to change
there but inside of our crop class we no
longer need these
fields okay so we're actually going to
instead reference a crop icon object
which we haven't created
yet so vs code is going to give us an
error and let's call this crop icon
and inside of our Constructor we can
again remove these fields cuz we're not
going to pass these anymore we're
instead going to pass a crop
icon and vs code is going to give us
again an
error and we can set this crop
icon equal to crop icon
okay so in here we no longer have direct
access to this crop type field so
instead we can call Crop icon. getet
type because we are going to provide
that method on the crop icon
object okay so that's everything that we
need to do in our crop uh class and we
now have some errors that we need to fix
so let's go ahead and create the crop
icon object
okay so this is going to be our
flyweight class that stores intrinsic or
constant state the state that remains
constant throughout the object's life
whereas our uh crop glass is storing our
extrinsic state or our Dynamic State um
that is going to change throughout the
object's life so in
here we can store two Fields so we're
going to store the uh crop
type and we are going to store the
icon which is going to be again an array
of
bytes and what we can do is we can
actually make these fields read only to
ensure that once they are constructed
they can not be
changed so let's create make those read
only okay so let's create our
Constructor
now okay and remember we also need to
create a geta for the crop type so that
we can get the crop type inside of our
crop
icon uh inside of our crop
object okay so I think that is
everything we need to do
here so now we need to create our crop
icon fact
class so this class is going to ensure
that each unique crop icon object is
created only once it is cached and then
reused or shared between the crop
objects so first of all let's create our
crop icon uh cache so this is going to
be a dictionary
and in here the key for the dictionary
is going to be crop type and the value
is going to be the uh the crop icon
okay so now let's create our get crop
icon class which is going to uh
essentially ensure that icons are only
created once per crop type so here we
are going to return a crop
icon uh that should be crop
icon and we're going to call this get
crop
icon and it's going to take a crop type
that we want to get the icon for so if
we want to get the icon for a carrot we
can pass crop type. karat into this get
crop icon uh method so first thing we
need to do is we need to check if the
icon already exists inside of our cache
so I'm just going to make a little
uh a little comment here to say that
this is our
cache um so what we can do is we can say
that if I icons and this needs to
be
uh negative so if icons does not contain
key of the crop
type then that means that the icon does
not exist in our cache which means that
we need to create one and add it to our
cache so let's create an icon so V icon
equals new crop icon and we can pass the
crop type and for the icon uh I'm
actually just going to pass null um and
I'm just passing this again for
convenience but this could be for
example a reference to uh some file
location of the image but just to keep
things simple I'm passing null for now
to not make things too uh complicated so
once we've created our crop icon class
we can add this icon to the dictionary
so the key is going to be the crop
type and the value is going to be this
crop icon
object
okay so
finally uh if we get to here we know
that the icon exists so the icon e
either already existed so this wasn't
necessary so this uh conditional uh we
just skipped this bit here or if the
icon didn't exist we created a new one
so if we get to here we know that we
have uh this icon so we can
return icons and access the crop icon
object via its crop type
key okay so this all is looking good so
we now have our crop icon Factory which
is ensuring that each crop icon object
is only created once per crop
type okay so finally we can come into
our crop service class and we can now do
some refactoring in here so crop service
needs to store a reference to the crop
icon Factory so we can create a field
called crop icon
Factory and we can call this icon
Factory and we need to pass this via the
Constructor
okay so let's have a look at our G crops
method so we are storing a list of crops
so we don't need to change this and then
we simulate fetching the crops from the
data base so this is where we need to
make uh some modifications so we can see
here that now in our crop uh class we
are no longer passing the uh the sort of
a constant state okay because this is
now stored in our flyweight object so
instead of passing um the crop type and
the
um and the icon we now use our uh icon
Factory to create a uh crop icon object
so we can say icon
Factory
dot uh get crop icon and then we pass
the crop type that we want to get so we
can we can say crop type do carrot okay
and all of these carrots now are going
to be sharing the same crop icon object
which is stored in Cache uh due to our
icon Factory so this is exactly what we
want and then here we add our crops to
the crop list and return the crop list
okay so now let's go into our program.cs
file or our sort of client and let's see
how we now use this new solution using
the flyweight
pan so here we create our crop service
and we can see we have an error here so
there is no argument given that
corresponds to the required parameter
icon Factory of crop service. crop
service crop icon Factory so you can see
here that we need to pass a crop icon
Factory so let's let's go ahead and pass
that
in and we are now doing exactly what we
did before we are lipping through our
crops and we're calling crop. render so
as you can see there's not much
difference in the way clients use this
class we just uh sorry the way the
client uses this solution we just now
need to pass a crop icon Factory to the
crop service to ensure that uh uh so
that this is actually handling the
creation of crop icons okay so now if we
run this file uh run this program you
can see that we get exactly the same as
what we did before which is perfect so
to summarize we have created three
carrot crop objects but only one carrot
crop icon object so this solution will
save lots of ram when rendering many
crops at one time the facade pattern is
a structural design pattern that
provides a simplified interface to a
complex system encapsulating the
complexities of multiple subsystems into
a single unified interface for clients
so say that we have an e-commerce
application that allows users to submit
orders here are the steps involved in
that process so we have a user that is
submitting an order and then we have a
server which has multiple steps for
handling this order so first of all we
have to authenticate the user check
inventory so make sure that we have
enough of the items that the user wants
to purchase we then connect to some
payment service such as stripe we then
fulfill the order which might involve uh
something like reducing the inventory uh
then we charge the
user and send them a response which can
either be successful or if any of the
steps fail then we can send some sort of
fail response so as you can see there
are five main steps involved in
processing and order so let's first of
all implement this roughly in code so
I've created some classes to simulate
the steps involved in processing and
order so let me show you what we have
here so we have an order request class
and this is going to be the request
object containing the User submitted
data so say that the user has some form
they enter their name their card number
uh we also send the amount for the order
the address of the user and the item IDs
that the user wants to order okay so
this is like the order request object uh
we then go through uh some
authentication steps so I've just
created an empty class for now to keep
things super simple but this might check
uh the user's session checks whether the
session is valid uh that their username
all checks out and then we have an
inventory uh class with a couple of
methods so we can check the inventory
for the item IDs and we also have a
method which can reduce inventory by a
certain amount for the specified item
id okay
so um and check inventory we're just
going to return true so we we're always
going to say that we have an item in
stock and then we have a payment uh
class for handling the payment uh step
within the order process and here we
can uh set the name c number and the
amount that the user owes for the order
um and then we have a method called pay
which is going to
simulate um you know maybe connecting to
some payment service and charging that
users's card and then next up we have an
order fulfillment um class which is
going to Che uh check the
inventory that we have sufficient
inventory uh so we can see here we have
a fulfill method which is going to uh
loop through the items in the item list
so the items that the user wants to use
and it's just going to reduce the
inventory of of those items in the loop
and we also have like we've also logged
inserting the order into the database so
uh that we have record of um this order
in our database a sort of permanent
record so these are just sort of classes
that are simulating the steps involved
in the order process just sort of some
rough code that we can uh use to sort of
demonstrate this
example so this is now the sort of
important bit so I'm going to show show
you how a client would actually use this
solution so first of all we can create
an order request
object and this is going to be equal
to a new order
request we can then create our authentic
uh authentication object
we then need to create our inventory
object and in here what we can do is we
can Loop
through our order request item IDs so
you can remember in our order request
object just for convenience I've sort of
hardcoded these values in obviously a
real order request wouldn't have these
values hardcoded in I've just done that
for
convenience so what we can do is we can
Loop through uh all of the item IDs in
the order so we can say order
request do item
IDs and then we can check the inventory
for each um Item
ID and this is always going to return
true so we don't have to worry too much
about that this is just a quick rough
example then we can create our payment
object so we can say VAR payment equals
new payment and in here we can pass the
uh some information from the order
request object so we can pass the
name um the card
number and the amount for the
order okay then we can call payment. pay
and finally we need to do the order
fulfillment so let's create our order
fulfillment
object and this should be
lowercase and in here we need we just
need to pass our inventory
object okay then we can
call order fulfillment.
fulfill and we can pass the
uh some information again from the order
request
object so then we pass the
address and finally the order
items so the item
IDs okay so that's everything that we
need to do for processing and Order okay
so let's run this program to see that
everything is working
directly and we can see that we are uh
charging the card with the name Dany we
insert the order into the database and
we are reducing inventory uh of all of
the items that the user has ordered by
one so we are fulfilling the
order so as you can see every client
that needs to make an order has to go
through all of these steps to make a
single order so you can see here every
time we want to make an order we have to
go through all of these steps and every
client uh that needs to make an order
becomes coupled to or dependent on four
concrete classes the authenticate class
inventory payment and Order fulfillment
so if we had 10 classes that needed to
make an order then we'd have 10 classes
dependent on these four classes so
that's a lot of
coupling so if one of these four classes
changes then that's going to be 10 10
classes that need to be updated and this
is not good this is not maintainable so
each client that needs to make an order
will depend on four classes so here's
the client it's going to depend on these
four classes so let's now take a look at
how we can solve this issue using the
facade pattern so clients making an
order don't actually care or they don't
actually need to know about the steps
involved in making an order they just
want to make an order so let's introduce
a new class called order service with a
single method called order that
abstracts all of the logic so that all
other classes that need to make an order
only have to depend on this one class so
you can see here we've created an order
class which has an order method that
accepts and order request object now
this order service class uh depends on
these four classes which are the sort of
steps involved in making an order so
this order service is essentially
containing all of the steps that we had
here all within this one method so that
now all classes that need to be able to
make an order only need to depend on
this one order service class and not all
of these uh individual sort of steps
involved in making an order but let's
now go ahead and make our order service
class so this class is going to act as
our facade that encapsulates all of the
complexities and steps involved in
making an order so clients can then make
orders without having to know about all
the details or steps involved in the
order process so let's create a single
method called order that takes an order
request
object and in here we can simply uh go
through all of the steps in creating an
order and these are actually going to be
exactly the same as what we have in our
client over here so let's copy and paste
those
in
okay so this is everything we need to do
to make an
order uh and now inside out of our
clients we can remove all of this
stuff so all we need is our order
request object so this is a sort of
incoming order request from the user
which contains all of the users sort of
uh inputed uh data such as their name
card number address Etc we can then
create an order service
object
and we can can then call order
service do order and quite simply just
pass this order request
object and now that's all we need to do
to make an order so let's run this and
we should get exactly the same as what
we got
before so we can see here exactly the
same as what we had previously so now
clients can make orders without having
to to without having to depend on many
classes and without having to know about
all of the complexities uh involved in
making an order as all of these
complexities have been abstracted away
and encapsulated within this order
service class so now you can see it's
much more simple for clients to make
orders by using a facade class The
Decorator pattern is a structural design
pattern that allows Behavior to be added
to individual objects dynamically
enhancing functionality with without
altering the objects structure and it's
used to extend or modify the behavior of
objects by wrapping them with additional
functionality through composition so say
that we have an application that allows
users to store data in the cloud the
data can be sent to the cloud as it is
without any processing or it can be
compressed Andor encrypted before it's
saved to the cloud so here's a uml
diagram for a basic uh sort of of almost
naive solution to this problem so here
we have our cloud data class with a URL
for the location where this data is
going to be stored in the cloud we have
a Constructor where we pass and set the
URL and we have a save method uh where
we pass the data that we want to save to
this URL location in the cloud we then
have some extra classes that extend this
cloud data class and add some extra
functionality so we have an encryption
class which also has a save data uh
method and here we are overriding the
method in cloud data and adding some
extra uh functionality to encrypt the
data before it is saved we also have a
compression class which compresses the
data before it saved and then we have a
an encryption and compression class
which both encrypts and
uh and compresses the data before it's
saved to the cloud so so far everything
looks okay but then the boss says that
we need to create a new validation class
to validate and clean the data before it
sent to the cloud and we can see below
that our code starts to look bloated as
we need to make lots of new classes just
to add one extra feature so you can see
here our sort of class library is
becoming very very quickly bloated so to
add one new feature this new validation
feature we have to create four new
classes and uh class library is actually
growing here exponentially so this is
not good maintainable or flexible so
let's see what this looks like in
code so first of all let's create our
base cloud data
class and this cloud data class needs
have a URL
field and we're making this a protected
field so that the classes that inherit
cloud data will have access to this URL
field if we made it private then it
wouldn't be accessible to all of this uh
classes
subclasses so next up we will create a
Constructor
where we can pass the URL uh location of
where we want to store the data in the
cloud so finally we need to create a
save method and we're going to make this
a virtual method so that it can be
overridden in sub
classes and we're just going to make the
data some sort of string to keep things
simple for now and we're going to log
saving
data to Cloud at the URL
location okay so that all looks okay so
now we're going to create our compress
data
class and this needs to extend the cloud
data CL uh class cuz we're adding some
extra
functionality and here we can generate
the construct uh Constructor for cloud
data so we pass the URL location and we
can then override the save method uh
inside of this
class okay so what we want to do here we
are let's remove this for now so what we
want to do is first compress the data so
I'm going to say for compressed equals
compress and then I'm going to pass the
data to this method so let's create this
compressed uh sorry let's call this
compress and let's create a method
called
compress and we can pass the data and
what we're going to do is we're just
going to tr trim or sort of create a
substring from the data so we're going
to return data do
substring and then we're going to go
from the first character up to the ninth
character in the uh well this will be
the eighth character so from index0 to
index 9 in the uh string okay so we're
just trimming the string down
basically and this is uh our way of sort
of pretending or simulating comp
pressing the data so next
up let's create our encrypted data class
which will encrypt the data before it is
sent to the
cloud and again we need to inherit from
cloud data and we need to generate the
Constructor for the cloud
data and again we're going to override
the
uh save
class and again we're going to call
base. saave so base is going to be the
base class which is cloud data and we're
calling the save method on cloud data
and passing the data but what we need to
do is pass some encrypted data
so we can say VAR
encrypted equals encrypt
and we're going to pass the data so then
we can pass this encrypted data to our
save method so let's actually create
this encrypt method
now so this is going to be a public
method that returns a string it's called
encrypt it takes some string data and
we're just going to return uh some
random strings so we're going to pretend
to encrypt the uh data
okay so this is like simulating
encrypting the data basically okay and
we're going to pass that to our uh cloud
data save so here we encrypt the data
then we save it okay so essentially
we've added some functionality to this
cloud data class by extending it okay so
finally let's create our compressed and
encrypted data class
so let's create that so we're going to
say
compressed and encrypted
encrypted uh
data and again we extend cloud
data generate the
Constructor and we're going to
override the save
method okay
so in here what we want to do is we want
to get the compressed
data and we want to pass the URL which
we have uh inherited from cloud
data and we want to call
compress and we need to pass the data to
this method so now we have the
compressed data let's now
uh encrypt this uh compressed data so we
can say
and uh encrypted and
compressed equals new encrypt data and
we pass the UR
URL and then we can call encrypt and
pass the data and then we can pass this
encrypted and compressed data to our
base cloud data save method so so that
we store it to the cloud okay so this is
everything that we need so let's now go
ahead in our program.cs file and use
this solution so I'm just going to copy
and paste a few things in here to save
some time so here we have a URL for the
location to store the data so I've just
put Google Cloud for now we have our
data that we want to
save and we have a bu Bull in here that
says compress equals true and we have
encrypt equals true so here we want to
store some data to this URL location in
the cloud and we also want to compress
and encrypt the data and this can
essentially sort of simulate some sort
of user input data okay so the user
might uh specify the location and the
data they want to save and whether they
want to compress and compress uh encrypt
the data before saving it so now that we
have um the user uh this input data uh
we have to select the correct cloud
storage object so first of all we can
create our cloud data
object and we pass the
URL and then what we can do is we can
check we can add some conditionals to
check whether we should compress and uh
or com uh encrypt the data so we can say
if
compress
and
encrypt then we can reset uh reassign
cloud data to uh a compressed and
encrypted data object so we can say new
compressed and encrypted data and we can
pass the URL
and then we can say else
if uh else if
compress then we want to set cloud data
equal
to compressed data and we pass the
URL okay and finally we want to check if
we are just encrypting the
data and then we can say
uh cloud data
[Music]
equals encrypted data and pass the
URL and that should be new encrypted
data okay so as you can see in the
client we have to check whether we
should compress and encrypt or just
compress or just encrypt and then we set
the cloud data object equal to the
appropriate uh uh class type so
finally we uh now we have now that we
know that we have the correct uh way of
storing the data we can simply just call
cloud
data do
saave and then we pass the data to this
method so let's run
this okay so this seems to be working
correctly the data is being uh
compressed and encrypted because these
are are both
true so as we discussed our total number
of classes is going to increase
exponentially with this solution but
another issue is that we have to perform
lots of conditional checks in the client
um whenever we use this
solution so for example if we add a
validated data class then we'd have to
add conditionals for encrypt and
compress and validate and also press and
validate uh encrypt and validate and
also just validate by itself so we'd
have to have four extra conditional uh
statements uh just to add one new
feature and this is really not good and
this is actually going to continue to
get worse and worse uh exponentially as
we add more classes uh or features so
this is a really bad solution so let's
now now use a design pattern to solve
this mess so the solution to this is to
move away from inheritance and use
composition instead so you may have
noticed by this point that a lot of
design patterns are based on moving away
from inheritance and towards composition
so with composition one object has
reference to another object and
delegates that object some work and this
allows you to use polymorphism and
switch between objects at runtime making
your code more flexible whereas with
inheritance the object itself is able to
do that work inheriting the behavior
from its superclass so with inheritance
we have to create lots of new classes
with composition we can wrap or decorate
existing objects to add new
functionality so here we have the uml
for the decorated patent solution so we
can see here we have a data interface
with a save method that accepts the data
we then have our cloud data class which
has as before the URL location for
storing the data in the cloud and we
pass this via the Constructor and it has
a save method uh which we have to
implement from this data interface we
then have a data decorator class and
this also implements the data interface
and you can see here that we have a
wrappy field and the wrappy is
essentially the object that is going to
be wrapped and in our case that's going
to be our cloud data object because
we're essentially what we want to do is
add additional functionality or at least
have the option to add additional
functionality to this cloud data class
so uh we want to be able to uh add the
ability to encrypt or compress or both
compress and encrypt so here we can
essentially wrap this cloud data uh
object in in a uh encryption decorator
or and or a compression decorator so you
can see here we can pass the um wrappy
into the Constructor and we also have
our save uh method because we are
implementing this data interface and
then we have our sort of specific uh
decorators so this dat decorator class
CL is kind of like a little bit of a
helper class that contains some sort of
common Logic for uh what decorators
should be able to do so if I just read
this paragraph here so above and this
uml we're making the encryption and
compression objects decorators because
they are decorating the cloud data
object with some additional Behavior Uh
because decorator classes have some
common logic
uh for example referencing a data source
object uh we have created a data
decorator class where this logic can be
inherited to prevent code repetition so
this means that encryption decorator and
compression decorator will share some
common fields and logic and for example
in our case uh both of these classes
need to wrap the cloud data object and
this should probably be
uh referencing a cloud data
object so essentially our decorator
classes are composed of or are
decorating or wrapping a cloud data
object or any object that implements the
data interface to add extra
functionality so let's take a look at
the gang of four uml for The Decorator
pattern and as you can see it's
basically the same as what we have in
our solution uh the only difference
being
the names of the
classes so if this isn't making much
sense then don't worry because things
will become a lot clearer as we code out
this
solution so now we're going to implement
our solution using The Decorator pattern
so first up let's create the data
interface and this needs to have a
single method for saving the data
okay so next let's create our cloud data
class and this is going to be the class
that we are going to wrap or add
functionality too in other words
decorate so we're going to decorate this
class with additional functionality but
first of all let's actually create this
cloud data class and this needs to
implement the data interface so let's
implement the
interface and in here again just as
before we need to um store reference to
the URL that we want to save to so I'm
actually just going to copy and paste
what we had beforehand because it's
exactly the same so you can see here
that we have
um uh a Lo a URL location for storing
the data we passed that by the
Constructor then we have a save method
for actually saving the data so this is
exactly the same as what we had before
the only difference is that we are now
implementing this data interface so now
let's create our data decorator abstract
class and again this needs to implement
the data
interface okay so this needs to store
reference to uh some sort of data object
so this is going to be the wrappy object
or the object that we are decorating or
adding functionality too so let's create
a protected field of type data and the
reason it's protected is because the
encryption decorator and the compression
decorator need to have access to this
data field so that's why we are making
it protected and not private so next up
let's create the Constructor so that we
can pass a data object to wrap
and then we can set the data object in
the Constructor and then we have our
save method so we actually don't want to
implement this method inside of the data
decorator class itself we want to make
this method abstract so that it can be
uh overridden or implemented in the uh
compression and encryption sub classes
so we can make this an abstract method
and then we need to make this class
abstract
and that is everything we need to do
inside of this data decorator class so
now we can go ahead and create our
compression
decorator and this needs to extend data
decorator uh we then need to generate
the uh or we need to implement the class
and also generate the
Constructor so we're passing the wrappy
object again to this base dat data
decorator class and we're also
overriding this abstract save method
from data decorator so this is where
we're going to add our compression logic
so this is going to actually be the same
as what we had beforehand in our
compressed data class so we can copy and
paste the save and compress methods from
what we had before
and that is all okay we just have an
issue here because we um actually need
to say base dot data so we're now using
uh composition here so we call base.
data to get the data field and then we
call the save method on that data field
and we can press the compressed
data okay so that's all we need to do
there
um so I'm also just going to uh log
whenever we call the save method so that
it's easy to see what's going on so I'm
just going to put compressing
data okay so I think that's everything
we need in our compression decorator
class so let's now go ahead and create
our encryption decorator
and this needs to extend the data
decorator and let's now implement the
abstract class and also generate the
Constructor so you can see here that
this data decorator is just a kind of
class that makes it easier to uh to
create the different uh decorators it's
just basically a kind of helper class
where we have uh some basic setup for a
decorator which is uh essentially just
passing some sort of wrappy object uh
into uh the class and it saves us from
having to write this logic inside of
both of these classes we don't have to
uh bother recreating this okay so it's
just presenting a little bit of
repetition
basically um so here we have our
encryption decorator we have our
Constructor so now we can implement the
logic for encrypting and saving some
data
so let's copy what we had before because
it's not going to be uh any different in
terms of the uh logic so let's copy and
paste those methods and again instead of
calling base. saave what we need to do
is call base. dat.
Save and then we pass the encrypted
data okay so that is everything we need
to do so now let's actually use this
solution in the client
so what I'm going to
do is I think I'm going to remove all of
this and I think I'll also remove this
and let's reimport these objects okay so
first of all let's create our cloud data
object so this is going to be called
cloud data and it's going to be equal to
new cloud data
and in here we need to pass the URL that
we are saving
to okay so next up we can add our
conditional statements so we can say if
encrypt uh if encrypt is true so if the
user wants to encrypt the data before
saving then we can
reset uh cloud data equal to uh new
encryption decorator so let me show you
actually this is going to be easier to
just show you so cloud data equals new
encryption decorator so we create a new
decorator and we pass the cloud data to
this
class okay so you can see here that we
are wrapping or decorating the cloud
data with an encryption decorator okay
so we're adding some additional
functionality by wrapping this object
inside of a
decorator okay rather than creating a
new specific subass okay we're wrapping
using composition instead of using
inheritance and creating a new uh
encryption uh data class like we were
before and now what we can do is we can
say if we want to compress so if we want
to also compress or just compress alone
we can call uh we can wrap this cloud
data in inside of a compression
decorator
okay so that's all we actually need to
do those are the only conditionals that
we need we only need to add one extra
conditional uh for every type of feature
that we have so then at the end we can
call cloudd data.
saave and then we can pass the
data and then let's run this
program and we can see that we are
compressing the data and then saving
data uh to the cloud at google.com so we
are compressing and encrypting the data
if we make compress
false let's see what
happens uh we can see that we are just
encrypting the data if we make both of
these false let's see what we
get we just save the data as it is and
everything seems to be working uh as it
should
be okay so this is perfect because now
if we for example want to add a new
feature say a validation uh step then we
just have to add one more uh conditional
we just have to say if validation equals
is true then we can wrap in a validation
decorator we don't have to create um a
load of new sub classes we just create
one new decorator Class A validation
decorator and we just just have to add
one new conditional to the client we
don't have to create a validation plus
compression a validation plus encryption
validation Pro Plus compression plus
encryption subass we don't have to
create all those subclasses and then add
conditionals for all of those new
combinations of uh steps so this is a
much much more maintainable solution
using The Decorator pattern so so far
we've looked at the behavioral and
structural design patterns
but last but not least we need to look
at the group of creational design
patterns so first of all massive
congratulations on getting this far into
the course and your award is that
creational design patterns are probably
the easiest group of design patterns to
learn and understand so if you feel like
giving up at this point please don't the
hardest work has been done so creational
design patterns are a category of design
patterns that to focus on object
creation dealing with the best way to
create objects while hiding in the
creation logic and making the system
independent of how its objects are
created composed and represented so some
benefits of creational design patterns
are that they uh help to encapsulate
object uh creation uh object creation
logic uh hiding it from clients and this
promotes loose coupling and allows the
system to be more flexible to changes in
how objects are
instantiated and they enhance
flexibility
and
extensibility by promoting uh by
providing ways to create objects
dynamically based on varying
requirements or conditions and this
makes the system more adaptable to
changes and new features so we also have
um improved code reusability uh by
encapsulating object creation logic in
reusable patterns such as factories or
Builders developers can leverage
existing patterns to create similar
objects in different parts of the
application promoting code reuse we also
um they help these design patterns also
help to promote the separation of
concerns so creational patterns helps to
separate the responsibility of object
creation from the rest of the systems
logic and this separation of concerns
improves code maintainability and
readability uh creational pattern also
uh Provide support for depend dependency
injection so they often play a crucial
role in supporting uh dependency
injection by providing mechanisms to
manage the creation and injection of
dependencies promoting modularity and
testability and if you've never uh if
you're not really sure what dependency
injection is we will cover it uh
throughout the design patterns and it's
a very very common uh term that you'll
come across in software development and
it's used in backend Frameworks such as
larabel spring boot or net and uh
creational patterns help to centralize
the control over how objects are created
allowing developers to apply consistent
instantiation strategies across the
application and uh creational patterns
also encourage adherence to important
design principles that we've covered
earlier such as abstraction and
capsulation and separation of concerns
contributing to a more robust and
scalable a architecture so in summary
creational design patterns offer
numerous benefits that contribute to the
overall quality flexibility and
maintainability of software systems by
providing effective solutions to object
creation challenges and promoting best
practices in software design each
pattern addresses specific aspects of
object creation catering to different
scenarios and requirements in software
development so now let's learn all of
the ganga four creational design
patterns
the Prototype pattern is a creational
design pattern that allows objects to be
copied or cloned providing a mechanism
to create new instances by copying
existing objects without explicitly
invoking their Constructors and it's
used to efficiently produce new
instances with identical properties to
existing objects so say that we have a
guey a graphical user interface that
allows the user to create new shapes on
the screen such as circles and
rectangles when the user right clicks on
a shape an actions menu opens up and the
user can then select duplicate to clone
the shape so you can see here we have
the original shape on the left if the
user right clicks and then clicks on
duplicate from the actions menu the
shape is duplicated and rendered on the
guey so let's come up with a solution to
this problem so you can see here we have
a shape interface with a draw method and
then we have our concrete shape classes
that implement this shape interface and
then we have a shape actions class that
contains the logic for duplicating each
shape and this uh duplicate method uh
and this shape accents class is
dependent on all of the shapes that can
be duplicated so you can see it see here
that um we can see that this class
depends on all of these concrete shapes
by and that's represented by this dotted
so can you see the issue with this
solution and can you also spot what
solid principle we are violating and as
we code out this solution um the issue
here is going to become very obvious so
let's go ahead and do that so first of
all let's create a new folder for our
creational design patterns part of the
course and then we'll create a new
folder for this prototype
pattern okay so first of all let's
create the shape
interface and this is going to have a
single method called
Draw now let's create uh a few concrete
shapes so let's first of all create a
circle and this is going to implement
the shape interface
SP okay so we have the draw method here
and let's just uh log here drawing
circle okay so we also need to give the
circle a property for its radius CU all
circles need to have a radius so we'll
say public int
radius and then we'll give it a getter
and seter okay so the nice and simple
and I think what we'll do so whenever
the user sort of creates a circle on the
uh screen so if they click you know a
little circle icon that produces a
circle to appear on their canvas then I
think it would be nice to give it a
default radius so let's give it a
default radius of
five for all newly created
circles okay so next up let's create the
concrete rectangle shape
and again we implement the shape
interface and all rectangles have a
width and a height so let's go ahead
and give it a width and height
property and also a
height and again let's give it a default
height of 10
and a def sorry a default width of five
and a default height of uh 10 actually
no we'll go with 10 and five
okay okay so let's uh just log drawing
rectangle
here okay so that's all we need to do
for our shapes so now we can create our
shape action class which uh is going to
depend on all of these concrete
shapes okay so let's create our
duplicate
method which is going to accept a shape
so it has a shape
parameter now in here what we need to do
is we need to duplicate any shape that's
passed into the duplicate method so
first of all we need to actually check
what the type of shape uh what type of
shape has been passed in so we can say
if shape is circle first of
all and let's see what's going on here
the type name space Circle could not be
found let's see ah I've misspelled
Circle here so let me correct
that okay and that fixes the
issue so let's see so first of
all let's um cast this shape object into
a circle so we'll call this copied
shape so the shape that we are copying
and we'll cast it into a
circle and that's how we cast and again
I spelled Circle wrong there we go okay
so now we will create our new shape
which is going to be the Clone so I'm
just going to make a note this is the uh
copied
shape and then we will have
our uh new
shape the duplicated
shape okay so we create a new Circle and
this is the Clone and then what we can
do is we can set the new shapes
radius equal to the copied shapes radius
okay and then we can draw this shape
onto the
canvas by calling the draw method and
then we also need to check um if the
shape is a
rectangle and if it's a rectangle again
we're going to create
um we're going to cast the uh shape into
a
rectangle okay so now we can uh treat
this shape as a rectangle so we also
need to create our new shape or our
clone
so this is going to be a new rectangle
and then we can set the new shapes width
and height equal to the Past shape the
past in shapes uh width and height so we
can say uh new shape dot width equals
copy shape do width and we can say new
shape. height equals copied shape do
height and then we can draw the new
shape onto the canvas
okay so it would also be a good idea to
um check at the end here so if the shape
or is not a circle or a rectangle then
you know we could prevent uh we could
just throw an error so let's do that so
we'll throw a new argument
exception and we'll say invalid shape
provided okay so we can't duplicate uh a
shape that that isn't a circle or
rectangle in our current
implementation okay so here's how a
client would use the solution so let's
go ahead and show you how this solution
would be used so we can create a
circle and I cannot spell circle today
so let's create a new
Circle and let's draw that
Circle so render it onto the
canvas and then let's simulate uh the
user clicking
the um clicking the circle and dragging
to resize so this is like user clicks
and drags to
resize so we can say
Circle do radius equal 12 so we increase
the uh
radius and let's say that a
user uh
adds a new rectangle to the guey so I'm
just going to copy and paste this in for
now to save a little bit of time so we
can see here we create a new rectangle
draw it onto the guey so this is like
the user adding a new rectangle to the
guey and then the user clicks and drags
the rectangle to resize the width and
height so now let's take a look at how
we could duplicate these shapes so let's
simulate the user uh right clicking
and uh clicking and
selecting
duplicate okay so we can simulate that
so shape actions equals new shape
actions and then we can call shape
actions. duplicate and pass the shape
that we want to duplicate so if we want
to duplicate the circle we can do that
if we want to duplicate the rectangle we
can do that okay so let's run this
program to see if everything is working
correctly and as you can see we are
drawing the circle and rectangle onto
the uh guey so that's these two uh
methods here so Circle do draw and
rectangle do draw and then we duplicate
the circle so we draw the circle again
and then we duplicate the rectangle so
we draw the rectangle again so this is
all working correctly so hopefully by
now you have spotted the main issue with
this solution and the uh it should be
pretty obvious that the issue is in this
duplicate method so here are some of the
obvious issues that I can spot so first
of all we are violating the solid open
close Principle as we need to modify
this shape actions class every time we
add so that means extending our code
base a new shape so whenever we add a
new shape we're going to have to add add
uh
modify uh our existing code because
we're going to have we're going to have
to add a new conditional uh block of
code to check for this new shape and add
the logic for duplicating that
particular shape and you can also see
that shape actions is coupled to the
concrete shape classes and so far that's
Circle and uh rectangle so you can see
it's coupled because we're calling the
new keyword here
and uh so shape actions has to know
about or depend on all kinds of shapes
and their specific fields and methods so
you can see here that this shape actions
CL actions class has to know that
circles have a radius field and it has
to know that rectangles have a width and
height so it has to know about the
specific implementation details of each
of these concrete
shapes and at the time of writing code
shape has actions has to know about all
the shapes that we support so what if we
wanted to make this app extensible so
that other developers or other people
can build plugins for this uh
application so that they can Define
other types of shapes that can be added
to the guy and that can't be achieved
with this current implementation because
at the time of writing code or at
compile time they this shape actions
class has to know in advance about all
of the types of shapes so this is not a
flexible solution and it currently
depends on concrete implementations of
shapes so let's now take a look at how
we can solve the issues that we found
previously so the logic for duplicating
a shape can be moved to each concrete
shape class rather than having it all in
the shape actions. duplicate method so
in other words we can move uh all of
this duplication Logic for a circle and
add it into the circle class and we can
do the same for rectangle put it all
into the rectangle class okay so we can
then decouple shape actions from all the
concrete shapes and have it talk to the
shape interface which is much more
flexible and
maintainable so note how the shape
actions class
has been sort of lifted up to talk to
the single shape interface rather than
having it talk to many concrete classes
so you can see
beforehand it depended on the many
concrete classes because we had to check
uh what the type of shape was before
duplicating it where now it's been
lifted up to talk to the shape interface
and we've added the duplication Logic
for each shape into its own uh into its
own class class okay so let's have a
look at the gang of four representation
of the Prototype pattern so here you can
see we have the Prototype interface with
the Clone method and then the concrete
prototypes implement this clone method
so each concrete prototype knows how to
clone itself rather than having this
clone logic inside of some sort of
client or other class as we had
previously and this means that the
client can use polymorphism and talk
directly to to the Prototype interface
rather than talking to the many concrete
prototype classes so let's now implement
this solution in
code okay so now let's refactor our code
to use the Prototype pattern so the
first thing I'm going to do is I'm going
to change uh well I'm just going to add
an extra method to the shape interface
so that all shapes can be
duplicated and you can see the dup liate
method is going to return a shape so
next up we need to solve a few errors
that we're now getting so you can see
here that Circle does not Implement
imple interface member shape. duplicate
so we need to implement this duplicate
method so we've already created the
duplication logic beforehand in our
shape actions class so what we can
actually do is we can copy uh this here
so we can can say New Circle and shape.
radius equals copied shape. radius so
let's add that into
Circle and you can see here that we
don't need to reference this copied
shape anymore we can just uh use the
radius field directly on
Circle okay then finally we need to
return this new shape
like so so here we create the new shape
to clone and then we just set the radius
equal to the current Circle radius and
return that new shape okay so New Circle
and let's actually re rename this now to
New
Circle
okay so next we need to do the same
thing for rectangle so let's implement
this shape class so we need to add the
duplicate method and then we can uh copy
and paste the logic for um copying a
rectangle so let's add that in and we
actually need to create a new
rectangle okay so we create a new
rectangle and then we set the width and
height equal to the current rectangle
width and height okay so let's again
change uh the name of this to something
a little bit more specific so new
rectangle and then we need to return
this new rectangle from the duplicate
method to satisfy the uh method
signature okay so that's everything we
need to do in the concrete shapes so now
we can go to our shape actions class and
we can see here this very bloated oakly
method can now
be uh
refracted into something much much
cleaner now what we have to do it's
called is return shape do
duplicate okay and we're actually going
to return a shape this time from the
duplicate method so I'm just changing
the kind of implementation details a
little bit here so rather than drawing
the shape onto the screen we're just
going to return the shape and allow the
client to decide what they do with with
that duplicated shape okay so I'm just
also going to log uh just so it's clear
uh duplicating
shape just so it's clear what's going on
when we run the program okay so now
let's go into our
client and see what happens if we run
this as you can
see everything seems to be working
correctly
okay so what I want to do here is
because now duplicate is returning the
new duplicated shape let's see if we can
um uh let's see New Circle equals that
so now we can um store this return shape
in a variable uh so let's say shape uh
new rectangle equals that and then we
can decide in the client whether we want
to draw it on the screen or do whatever
we want with this new uh cloned uh or
duplicated uh shape so let's actually
draw it so this is basically now doing
exactly what we had beforehand we
duplicate and draw the shape on the
screen but we're now controlling whether
we draw it or not in the client so it's
just a slightly different implementation
detail that gives the client a little
bit more control over what they do with
this duplicated shape so let's run this
now
and I think what I'm going to do is
actually duplicate uh create the new
Circle then draw it just so it's a
little bit more
clear okay so we can see here we first
of all draw a circle just the same as
before we then draw a rectangle we then
duplicate the uh Circle we then draw
this new duplicated circle on the screen
then we duplicate the rectangle and draw
the rectangle on the screen
okay so this is all working perfectly
and we can now also add new shapes
without having to modify existing code
in the shape actions class so the great
thing about this prototype pattern is we
are now satisfying the open close
principle because we can create a new
shape such as a triangle and we don't
have to modify any existing code the
Singleton pattern is a creational design
pattern that ensures that a class only
only has one instance and provides a
global point of access to that instance
the single instance is commonly used for
managing shared resources configuration
settings or logging functionality within
an application a common use case of the
Singleton pattern is to use a single
Global instance of a database object
throughout an application this means
that all clients that need to connect to
a database will retrieve the same
database object and will not be creating
new separate database objects the
database object is only created once the
first time it is needed and then all of
the clients that need to connect and
query the database will use the same
database object so here's a user making
a request uh to fetch some products
there are two classes user
authentication and products both require
fetching things from the same database
notice that we we are not using the new
keyword to get the database object we
are using a method called get instance
that Returns the exact same database
object throughout the application
ensuring that we always use a single
database instance so you can see here we
have our user which goes through uh two
classes so first of all we authenticate
the user and to get the database object
we are calling db. get instance we are
not calling DB equals new database uh
whatever okay so we're not using the new
keyword we're using this sort of factory
to get the same instance of the database
object so it's going to be cached
somewhere in memory so you may be
wondering why we can't just create a new
database object every time we need to
connect to a database so here are some
good reasons to use a single Global
database object in all clients so you
can see here we have two clients the
authenticate user class is a client of
the
database uh object and this products
class is also a client okay so here are
some good reasons to use a single uh
Global database object so first of all
uh for resource efficiency so database
connections and resources are typically
limited and can be expensive to
establish so by using a single instance
of a database object you minimize the
over head of creating and managing
multiple connections optimizing resource
utilization also consistency and State
Management so having a single database
instance ensures consistent State
Management and transaction handling
across different parts of the
application changes made to the database
state are visible universally within the
application avoiding inconsistencies
that could arise from multiple database
instances so we also simplify
configuration and management so with a
Singleton database instance
configuration settings such as
connection parameters credentials and
initialization logic are centralized and
managed in one place and this simplifies
application setup and maintenance we
also have performance optimization by
reusing a single database instance you
can optimize database query performance
and reduce latency associated with
establishing new connections or
reinitializing database
resources so the singles and patter is
great for storing app configuration
settings uh well it's also great I
should say for storing app configuration
settings login configuration session
information authentication tokens and
making this information available
globally via a single instance ensuring
that it is the same throughout the app
so you can see um there are many reasons
why we would want to keep a single
instance of an object throughout the
application rather than creating new
versions of that object in multiple
clients and we can see here some more
specific reasons why we would want a
single database
instance so say that we need to keep an
app settings object that stores Global
variables such as the name of the
application the database configuration
for example what database type we're
using whether it's postgrad SQL uh
mongodb the username and the password
and also logger settings such as the
file location for our log file the
format whether it's text versus Json Etc
and we need to create only a single
instance of this object throughout our
application to ensure that it only needs
to be configured once in one place and
to ensure consistency throughout the
application so first of all we're going
to create a PO solution to this
problem so first of all let's create a
new folder for our Singleton pattern
example and that is a creational design
pattern so let's create it in there and
this is called single
ton okay so first of all let's create
our app settings object or class I
should say so app
settings and in here we're going to
create a dictionary
field and each dictionary uh the
dictionary is going to have keys which
are strings and the values are going to
be
objects okay and this is where we're
going to store our settings okay and
each setting is going to have some key
such as app name and then some object
and the app name could be um design
patterns Mastery for example okay so
first of all we need to create a method
called get for getting uh
values from our settings uh
object so here we first need to check if
the setting with this key name actually
exists in our settings dictionary so
here we can say if the settings and
contains key so if the settings does not
contain the key provided then we're just
going to return null otherwise we can
return the settings object corresponding
to the provided
key okay so next up we can create a sept
method and this is for setting uh
settings values so we provide a key and
an object value and here we can simply
call settings key equals value okay so
we set a settings um uh value with this
key and this value so next up let's have
a look at how we can use this solution
in a client so what we can do is first
of all create a settings uh object so
we'll create new app
settings equals new app
settings and then let's actually set a
few settings so we can call settings.
set and then we'll say app name is is uh
design
patterns
Mastery and let's also set
um a another setting for app
creator and I'm just going to put my
name so
Danny okay so then let's actually
console log um one of the settings just
to check that it's working correctly so
we can say
settings. get and let's get the app name
okay so this should be design pattern
Mastery so let's run
this and we can see that it's been set
correctly and we are are retrieving it
from the settings uh object without any
problems so next up let's actually
test um getting a setting from a
different client so this is here a
client a class that is using this app
settings object so let's now create a
test
class and in here I'm just going to
create a uh method called run so run the
test and let's see so first of all we
need to get our settings object so let's
get our uh settings object here and then
what I want to do is
retrieve this app
name okay so as you can see in
program.cs we are setting the app name
and then we get the app name here and
then in a different class in a different
client a client has some class that's
using this app settings object or class
and we are trying to get the app name
which was set in
program.cs so now let's actually run
this
test so maybe if we make this static we
can just access it directly just for
convenience and let's run this program
and we can see we get null so null is
returned here because in test the app
name does not
exist okay so you can see here that we
need to use the Singleton pattern to
ensure a single instance of app settings
is maintained throughout our application
because here we can see we are creating
a new a completely new app settings
objects and this is kind of fine if this
is the first time we're doing doing it
but then we're also creating another app
settings object a separate different
settings object and then we're trying to
access app name on a different object to
what we created in here so we're going
to need to use the Singleton pattern to
solve this issue because every time we
need to use the app settings object
currently we are using the new keyword
and so creating a new object so the
solution is to use the Singleton pattern
so to ensure that we have only a single
instance of this app settings class we
first have to make the Constructor
private so notice in this uml diagram
that the Constructor so this app
settings Constructor has a negative
symbol in front of it meaning that it's
private and this means that we won't be
able to use the new operation uh or the
new keyword with this app settings class
and and also notice that we have a
private static so static is being
symbolized by this underline here in the
uml so notice that we have a a private
static instance field that holds an
instance of the app settings class in
other words this class is responsible
for maintaining a single instance of
itself and we also have a get instance
method and this again is a static method
for getting
that single instance and the reason that
this method is static is because it's
static um Fields so this static field
here for example and static fields are
only visible to static methods so if
this wasn't static it wouldn't be able
to access this instance field because
static Fields belong to the class itself
rather than the objects that are
instantiated from it so let's have a
look at the gang of four representation
here we see it's very similar to what we
have up here we have a class called
Singleton with an instance uh a static
private instance of itself we have a
private Constructor so that the new
keyword cannot be used uh outside of the
class itself and then we have a get
instance method which basically
um returns uh uh a sing the instance of
itself so to implement the Singleton
pattern you have to do a few things so
first of all we need to make the
Constructor private so that the new
keyword can't be used to create multiple
instances of this class okay so we can
only create an instance of the class
inside of the class itself so another
point is that we have to create a
private static instance field to keep
reference to the single instance that is
created inside of the class and we have
to create a public a public static get
instance method for creating that single
instance the first time the method is
called in the application then returning
that very same instance every time the
method is called so let's now implement
this solution in code so let's now
refactor our app settings uh class to AA
to the Singleton pattern so first of all
we need to create a private static fi bu
for holding a reference to the instance
so let's create that so private static
app settings so this is going to be an
instance of itself we're going to call
this instance and we're going to leave
it as null initially so next up we need
to make the Constructor private this is
a very important step in the Singleton
pattern to ensure that um instances of
absent settings cannot be created
outside of the class itself so this
means that the clap class itself will be
able to create and maintain a single
instance of itself throughout the
application uh globally so let's make
the con The Constructor
private so private
Constructor and it's just an empty body
so next up uh we have a we need to
create a method for creating a single
instance of the this class and we're
going to call this method get instance
so this is going to be a static method
called app
settings and we're going to call it uh
get
instance and what we're going to do here
is we need to check if the instance is
null and if the instance is null so the
first time that this method is called
the instance is going to be null so we
need to create a new instance
okay otherwise we just return the
instance so the second time that this
get instance method is called instance
will be set to an app settings object
and therefore this will not run and we
will just return that very same instance
as we returned
previously okay so I believe everything
else should be the same as before so we
have our get method for getting um
certain settings via their key and we
have our set method for setting
different settings so I believe that's
everything that we need to do so now
what we can do is we can go into our
program.cs file and I'm just going to
change the name space to this uh new um
solution and let's see what is the error
we get here so app settings is
inaccessible okay so now we can see that
because we were previously using the new
keyword to create an app settings object
it's now giving us an error because app
settings do app settings so this is the
Constructor is inaccessible due to its
protection level so if we look in app
settings The Constructor is now not
accessible outside of the class so we're
going to get an error so now to create
the settings object we need to call app
settings dot get instance and this now
returns an instance of the settings
object and we can use the settings
object just as we did before so we set
some values here and then we um we log
the app name at the bottom so let's test
that this works correctly as it did
before and we can see that we get design
patterns Mastery just as we should okay
so that's perfect so now let's actually
test out um getting this instance any
different client somewhere else in our
application so if we go into our new
example folder and create a test
class and in here I'm going to create a
public static method called
run and what we're going to do is we're
going to again get our settings
instance and I'm going to try to
retrieve the app name
so let's actually see if this works so
now if we run test. run we should get
design patterns Mastery because here we
get the instance from settings from our
app settings and this creates a new
instance and caches or um uh stores this
instance in the instance variable on the
class so you can see that this is a
static field meaning that it's stored on
the class itself and not within new
objects created
um um elsewhere in the
program so let's see if this
works and as you can see we get design
patterns Mastery logged twice so this is
perfect we now have a
global um instance uh object for our
settings the factory method pattern is a
creational design pattern that defines
an interface for creating objects but
allows subclasses to alter the type of
objects that will be created providing a
way to delegate the instantiation logic
to subclasses enabling flexibility in
object creation without changing the
client code so say that we are
developing a new model view controller
backend framework or MVC framework to
rival the popular PHP framework laravel
so let's code out a a basic solution so
I've created a view engine interface
with a render method and this takes a
file name so this is going to be the
file location of our template and we are
we can pass that template some data and
then this view engine is going to
render this uh template it's going to
pass it the data and turn it into a
regular um string of HTML and return
that HTML so that um it can be
understood by a browser and we also have
a couple of template engines so here we
have a blue um sorry a blade view engine
which implements the view engine
interface with a render method and here
we're just returning view rendered from
file name by blade and then we have a
twig view engine so this is just a
different templating engine uh and then
we're just saying view rendered from
file name by twig and this is all within
our MVC framework folder so this is part
of our uh framework that we are
developing and these view engines will
actually be third party code to our
framework because we are going to be
sort of downloading these view engines
um installing them into our application
as packages so we would not have access
to the source code to these view engines
okay so now let's create a base
controller class to handle requests uh
made to our application so let's create
a
controller and in here we're going to
have a method called render and this is
going to take a file name for the
template that we want to render and
we're also going to have some data that
we can pass uh pass to it
okay so first of all let's create a view
engine object that we want to
use and we're going to use the blade
view
engine and then let's actually use the
view engine to uh convert our template
uh and pass it the data and then convert
it into some regular HTML so we can say
VAR HTML equals View engine. render and
then we can pass the file name and the
data and finally what we're just going
to do is we're just going to uh log to
the console this
HTML okay so this is our base controller
class uh so remember this is all part of
our MVC framework that developers can
use to create their own
backend uh applications or
apis so developers can extend this base
controller class to create their own
controllers to handle requests to their
application for example a controller
that deals with order related requests
so let's come out of this MVC framework
folder and create a new class called
orders
controller and this is going to extend
the uh base controller from our MVC
framework okay so remember this would be
uh some developer creating there's some
other developer not related to our MVC
framework they're creating their own
maybe eCommerce application and they're
using our MVC backend
framework so in here what we can do is
we can create a method called list
orders and what I'm now going to do is
I'm just going to copy and paste some
code in here to save some time
okay so this is basically simulating
fetching uh some orders uh from a
database so we can see here we have a
dictionary um and we have the name of
the item and the price okay so this is
just to uh simulate fetching some sort
of order data from a database and then
it uh below this we can call the render
method which we have inherited from
controller and we can then pass the
location of our template file so at the
template that we want to R render so
this will be our blade template in this
case because in controller we are using
the blade view engine so this will be a
blade view so maybe we can call this for
example orders uh. blade. PHP and then
uh we can pass the data
that we want to uh populate our template
file with and that's going to be this
orders
data okay so um I think that is
everything that we need to do for now um
I I've also created a method called get
order to get a single order by ID inside
of here so I'm just going to paste that
in for now just to save again a little
bit of time you can see here this is
just another controller method that we
can use to get a single order okay by ID
and here I'm just simulating getting an
order by ID we're not actually getting
it by ID because we don't have a
database set up but it's just to show
you a different method that we could add
to our controller so our backend
framework code where our base controller
class is stored uh we can see here will
be downloaded by developers as a third
party framework so other Developers will
be downloading this MVC framework folder
essentially as a package so that they
can use our framework to create their
own applications and this aord
controller is an example of what a
developer might create using our
framework where they extend our base
controller
class now uh so developers won't
actually be able to modify the code
directly in this MVC framework folder so
this means that if the developer want
wants to use a different view engine or
template engine then this solution is
poor because our controller class is
tightly coupled to this blade view
engine and it cannot be changed by
developers we have the developer has no
way of switching to a different view
engine so for example if they want to
use the The Twig view engine to create
their templates using the uh twig
templating language then we have
provided them with no way oft switching
a to a different view engine so let's
try a different approach what if we
allow developers to pass a view engine
as an argument to the controller. render
method So currently we have the file
name and the data that we want to pass
to the view but let's also allow the
developer to pass the view engine that
they want to use uh whenever they render
a uh render a
view so let's pass the view engine that
we want the the developer wants to use
and now we can actually remove this uh
view engine we don't need to create the
view engine because it's been passed
here and then just as before we can call
view engine. render and then we can log
it the the resultant HTML to the
console so this allows developers to
select a view engine every time they can
call uh every time they call this base
control render so if we come into our
orders controller we can see that we now
get an error because we are not passing
the view engine that we want to use so
the developer now needs to pass the view
engine that they want to use and if they
want to use the twig view engine for
example they can pass the twig view
engine so here we can pass Again The
Twig view
engine so this is a more flexible
solution because it allows the developer
to choose whatever view engine that they
want to use however uh the problem is
that we have to now pass or the
developer has to now pass the view
engine every time they call the render
method and usually developers will be
using one view engine for all of the
templates in their application so it
doesn't make much sense to make the
developer uh to have to keep passing a
view engine every time the render method
is called so the solution is to create a
template method and we can add a create
view engine template method inside of
our base controller class and by default
we can return the blade view engine but
if the developer wants to switch to a
different view engine such as twig then
they can use our alternative controller
class twig controller that overrides the
create view engine template method so
here is the
uml and you can see here we have our Bas
controller class which is part of our
MBC framework package and we have our
render method just as before and we also
have our create view engine method which
by default returns a new blade view
engine so if the user doesn't um specify
any differ view engine then they will
get the blade view engine and also
within our uh MVC framework package so
this is part of our package back
framework code we're going to create a
twig controller which extends the base
controller and overrides the create view
engine method and in instead it Returns
the new twig view engine instead of a
blade view engine so if the developer
wants to use uh The Twig template engine
then they can extend the twig controller
instead of the regular Bas
controller so create view engine is is
our template method uh let's show this
in code so let's now refactor our code
to follow the template method pattern so
let's actually remove this view engine
parameter from the controller's render
method and we're actually now going to
use a template method to create our view
engine so this is going to be a
protected
virtual method that returns a view
engine and it's going to be called
create view
engine and by default the default
implementation is that we return a new
blade view
engine so now up here we can create our
view engine by calling this create view
engine
method okay so by default the view
engine for our framework will be
blade okay so now we can actually create
our uh alternative controller that the
developer can use so we're going to
create a twig
controller so this is going to extend
our base controller
class and we're going to override the
create view engine template method so
we're going to say protected override
view
engine so it's going to return a view
engine and it's called create view
engine okay so what we're going to do
here now is return The
Twig view
engine
whoop
okay so now if the developer wants to
switch to The Twig view engine they can
extend our twig controller class rather
than the base controller class so if we
go into our orders
controller uh we can see here what we
get we are getting an error because we
no longer have a three uh parameters in
this render method so we can remove this
last uh argument because we no longer
need to specify the controller type in
the render method and if we want to use
uh The Twig template language now we can
just extend the twig controller and our
render method will use the twig template
language because this create view engine
is a template meaning it can be
overridden and it will affect the
behavior of the render method because we
are calling it in here and this can
return uh different types of view
engines depending on whether it is being
overridden or not
so
essentially
um yeah as we've said this create view
engine is acting as our Factory method
as it returns a new object okay and it
can be a different type of object uh
depending on if we override it or not so
essentially what we've done is we've
deferred the creation of an object the
view engine to a subass and in this case
the subass is Twig controller because
because it's a subass of the base
controller class and another option
would be to make this create view engine
um method an abstract method and force
subclasses to implement it so in this
case we have made it just a regular
method and we've provided the virtual
keyword meaning that it can be
overridden but we could also make it an
abstract method with no default
implementation so no body essentially
and Force subclasses to implement it so
in that case we'd need to create a blade
controller that um implements this
create view engine method and returns a
blade view engine so that it would force
the developer to select either blade
view engine controller or The Twig view
engine
controller here is the gang of four
representation for the factory method
pattern so we have some Creator class
which has an operation method that calls
the factory method and you can see that
a factory method returns some object and
then we have our concrete Creator
classes which can override the factory
method from the Creator uh class and you
can see here each Factory method can
return a different type of object and
you can see here the uh Factory method
is called inside of the operation so
essentially we can change the behavior
in the Creator class by overriding this
Factory method so the objects return
from Factory methods are referred to as
products in the gang of four book and uh
the factory method pattern is often
misunderstood it relies on inheritance
and polymorphism to add flexibility to
the design inheritance allows methods to
be overridden in subclasses and
polymorphism allows different object to
be returned from the overridden methods
and many people implement the factory
method pattern incorrectly for example
using a static method such as this so V
engine equals view engine Factory do
create view engine but static methods
cannot be overridden so there's actually
no flexibility when using a static
method as it and it isn't correct uh
because we cannot change the
implementation of the create view engine
method so using the factory method
pattern we can defer the creation of an
object to its subass or subclasses and
this is possible through
inheritance the abstract Factory pattern
is a creational design pattern that
provides an interface for creating
families of related objects without
specifying their concrete classes
promoting encapsulation and allowing for
the creation of object families that can
vary independently so say that you have
an application for Windows and Mac the
UI components such as buttons checkboxes
and text boxes are different for each
operating system but each type of UI
components will have the same behaviors
for example a chatbox will have an
onselect method uh no matter whether
it's on Windows or Mac so our
application needs a way of knowing what
the current operating system is and then
selecting the appropriate family of UI
components for that operating system so
first let's Implement a more obvious
solution in code okay so inside of an
abstract Factory folder for this example
I've created an enome for the different
types of operating systems that our
application is going to support so so
far we have Windows and Mac I've also
created a UI comp component interface
for the different UI components to
implement so all UI components whether
they're going to be Windows or Mac need
to implement this UI component interface
and it has a single method for rendering
a UI component into the uh UI or the GUI
so next up I've created uh a
checkbox um interface and this extends
the UI component interface so all
checkboxes are UI
components um and I've not actually
created any checkbox methods just for
Simplicity but we could have for example
um um on select uh method or and any
other checkbox related methods I've also
created an i button interface which also
uh extends the UI component
interface okay so now for the concrete
Windows components so I've also created
a UI Windows folder for all of the
actual concrete Windows UI components
and here we have a Windows button which
implements the I button interface and
also implements the render method and we
also have a Windows checkbox which again
implements the chatbox interface and
also implements this render
method we also have the Mac components
the Mac UI components and we have a Mac
button which implements the I button
interface the render method which is
just logging Mac render button and we
have a Mac checkbox which again
implements the I checkbox interface okay
so this is the way we are set up here so
now for the app that we are actually
building so these uh all of these
classes so far would be uh probably
installed at some sort of package uh so
next up let's actually create our sort
of application uh class and that's going
to be called a user settings form so
let's create a new
class and let's say we have some sort of
form which will have uh a checkbox and a
button so what we can do is we can
create a render
method which will accept the operating
system
type so whether we are whether we should
render for Mac or
Windows and then we can check what the
operating system type is so if we can
say if OS is equal to operating system
type do
windows then we can create a new Windows
button and render it to the
screen so we call the render
method and we can also create a new
windows chat
box okay then we need another uh
conditional statement to check if the
operating system is Mac
and then we can render a Mac button and
a Mac
checkbox
okay so hopefully you can already start
to see what solid principle we are going
to be violating using this solution but
let's first of all before we discuss
that let's go ahead and actually use
this solution as a client would so if we
go into
program.cs first of all let's specify
the operating system that our app is
running on so this would probably be
some sort of environment variable or
some sort of system variable uh some
sort of uh thing that we could obtain
from the system that the application is
running on but but for now we're just
going to say for OS is equal to
operating system uh type and then we're
we're just going to say mac so we're
running on Mac okay so then let's render
our user settings
form so we can say new user settings
form
and let's then render this form so we
can say user settings form do render
and we can pass the operating system
type which in our case is
mac and then let's run
this
program and as you can see we are
rendering for mac and uh the button and
the chck box for Mac if we change to
Windows we should render for
Windows problems with this solution can
be seen in this user settings form class
so for every UI that we develop we're
going to have to have conditionals to
check what the current operating system
is and render the correct concrete UI
components for that particular
UI and this is a maintenance nightmare
as every time we add or remove a type of
operating system we have to modify a
load of classes which is going to
violate the open closed principle and
another issue is that we have to
conditionally render concrete UI
components so you can see here we're
having to uh render these concrete UI
components and it is in this case it's
easy to make mistakes such as
accidentally rendering a Windows
checkbox on the Mac operating system
because we're going to have lots of
different UI components this is just an
uh sorry different UI um so different
pages or different forms uh maybe um
like homepage and about page um a a
different window for um giving some
information uh after a user has clicked
a button uh lots of different UI
Elements which are going to be built
from these base UI components and we can
see that as the application grows it's
going to become easier to accidentally
render the wrong type of UI components
for a certain particular operating
system and our program isn't going to
know if we've actually done that by
accident it's only going to result in an
error when the application runs on that
particular operating system so the
solution to the issues that we faced
previously are to create an abstract
Factory class to create families of UI
components such as the family of Windows
UI components or the family of Mac UI
components so here you can see we have
an interface called UI component Factory
which has a create button method and a
create checkbox method and we then have
our concrete component Factory so here
is the Mac UI component Factory and this
create button method will return a Mac
button and the create checkbox method
will return a Mac checkbox and we also
have a Windows UI component Factory
which will do the same but for Windows
components so essentially we're going to
be able to create families of UI
components from these component
factories so here is the gang of four
representation of the abstract Factory
pattern and you can see here we have our
abstract Factory interface with create
uh which with methods to create
different products and then we have our
concrete factories which actually
Implement these methods so rather than
discuss the advantages of using this
method here I think it's going to be
better to implement this in code and
then discuss as we uh code so continuing
on from our previous code we can create
uh the abstract Factory interface so I'm
going to create this in the abstract
Factory
folder and this is going to be called I
UI component
Factory and here we just need to create
two methods one for creating a
button and another for creating a chat
box okay so now we can create our
concrete factories so first of all let's
create our Mac UI component
Factory and this needs to implement the
um the our UI component Factory so UI
component Factory and then we need to
implement this interface so here we very
simply just have to return a Mac button
okay so let's import this correctly so
there we go and then here we just need
to return a Mac uh chat
box
okay so that's everything we need to do
there so let's create our Windows UI
component Factory for creating families
of Windows UI
components and again we need to
implement the UI component Factory
interface and very simply we just have
to return a Windows button
here and that should be Windows button
and then let's
import use the correct namespace and
here we just have to return a Windows
chat
box okay so now in our form class so
let's go to our user settings form we
can see here that beforehand we were or
currently we're checking we're having to
check the operating system type before
rendering the operating system specific
UI components so now what we can do is
we can actually use polymorphism so that
this client requires no knowledge of the
uh specific uh of the operating system
basically it can just call uh the uh it
can just use the UI component Factory to
create a uh button or check box and then
render it to the screen and it can do
that because we're going to pass the UI
component Factory into this render
method so now rather than having to
perform all of these checks we can
simply use
polymorphism uh so we can call UI
component Factory doc create button and
we can render that to the screen and
then we can do the same thing for the
create chat
box okay
so here you can see that we're using
polymorphism by talking to a factory
interface uh to create relate Ed UI
components and this client requires no
knowledge of the specific operating
system okay so this is much cleaner uh
we no longer need to perform all of
these checks in every single um UI that
we create such as this user settings
form so let's now have a look at how
this solution would be uh used so if we
go into our program.cs file we now need
to do a few extra things here so first
of all let's create the uh UI component
factory and we're not going to uh assign
this any objects initially because what
we now need to do is we have to perform
our operating system checks uh inside of
the program.cs file so we can say if
operating system equals operating system
type. Windows then we can assign the UI
component Factory equal to a new
windows UI component
Factory and then we can do another check
here for
Mac then we can assign it to a new Mac
UI component
Factory and if the operating system
doesn't match any of the supported
operating systems for our application
then we can throw an
exception and here we'll just say
unsupported operating
system
okay so now here I'm just going to do
this on one line actually so rather than
calling render on a separate line I'm
just going to create the user settings
form and then call render directly on
this line and then we can pass into this
render method the UI component
Factory okay so that should be
everything that we need so let's run
this
program okay so you can see here that
it's rendering our user settings form
correctly and if we switch to
Mac then we should render for Mac
okay perfect so this is all working
correctly just as it was beforehand um
but here you might be wondering what is
the advantage of using this abstract
Factory pattern uh compared to what we
did previously because we're still
having to have all of these conditional
statements to check the operating system
type we're just doing it now in a
different place rather than within our
settings form class and the advantage of
this is that these checks now only need
to be done just once upon app
initialization then throughout the
application the UI component
Factory can be used to ensure that the
correct family of UI components are used
for the current operating system all
throughout the application so here we we
once we've um uh assigned the correct uh
UI component Factory it can be used all
throughout our application and we know
longer need to check um what the
operating system is in every single sort
of UI class that we create so if we
create uh a different uh class such as I
don't know maybe um orders uh orders
page for example which lists uh all of
the orders that a user has made from
some e-commerce store then we wouldn't
have to do all of these checks inside of
that class and every other class that we
create we can just pass the correct UI
comp component Factory that has been
initialized here just once so that is
the advantage of using the abstract
Factory pattern the Builder pattern is a
design pattern used to construct complex
objects step by step providing Clarity
and flexibility in the creation process
so let's say that we have a class called
car uh and we use this to create car
objects and we also have a manual class
that is used to create core manuals for
certain cares so you can see here that a
manual has a set of fields and a car
also has the same set of fields here so
you can see that a car or a manual is
composed of these fields and we can see
we have the car type and if I just go
into this components folder where I've
stored all of these kind of components
to make up a car or manual we can see
that car type can either be Sports SUV
or Saloon uh the dashboard can be
configured to either have a rev counter
or not uh we have an engine class here
which we could provide methods and
Fields for the speed model Etc a GPS
navigator class and also a class to
represent wheels and I've just put the
dynamet of the wheels in inches as a
sort of example
field
so we can see here in car and manual
they share a lot of common fields and
currently we have Seven Fields that are
shared between car and manual and also
in car we have a uh field here which is
specific to this class so it's not
relevant in the manual class and this CL
this field is called Fuel and this sort
of represents the amount of fuel that is
in the
car uh and then in manual we also have a
print method which is used to print the
text or create the manual from the
fields or information that has been set
on the object so let's take a look at
how a client would use this solution to
create cars and their corresponding
manuals so first of all let's try to
create a sports car so we can say sports
car equals new car and this needs to
come from the Builder pattern and now we
have to Ty uh provide the sort of
configuration options for a sports car
so first of all we need to provide the
type of the car and we can use the car
type enome for this so we can say car
type do
Sports and then we need to provide the
number of seats so sports car will have
two seats we then need to provide is
convertible so we're going to say false
this is not a convertible sports car uh
we need to provide an engine
and that's everything we need there uh
we need to provide a
dashboard and we can provide uh whether
this has a rev counter or not so and
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
type out the name of the field just so
it's nice and clear and put
true okay so then we need a Wheels
object and then we need to provide the
diameter of the wheels in inches so
let's say 20
in and then we need a new GPS navigator
so let's provide GPS
navigator and finally I think actually
that is everything that we need to
provide okay so that is our sports car
and then we can also specify uh the
amount of fuel in the sports car
so let's just say it's full 100% uh
filled okay so then we could also create
an SUV so rather than type out all of
those configuration options again let me
just copy and paste an SUV so we have
the car type
SUV uh so I believe this is
the uh number of seats so I guess it
would make sense here to again provide
the name of the field and then is
convertible so we could do that okay so
you can see that there are a lot of
configuration options that we have to
provide every time we create a sports
car or a car I should say and also I
just noticed that we don't need
this or
this
okay so let's also now create a sports
car manual and again we have to provide
some configuration options lots of
configuration options and then I'm just
logging out uh the sports cor manual uh
print so we print the sports cor manual
and log it to the console and we can
also do the same for
SUV and you can see that um when we
create a manual and when we create a
sports car so a sports car and a sports
car manual we're actually providing the
same fields to create these things but
they are two separate objects that are
not really related okay they don't share
a common interface because a car is
different from a
manual so let's run this to see what we
get and you can see we have the two
different manuals so we have a manual
for sports car here and we have our
manual for our
SUV so as you can see here with there is
a large number of configuration
variables that we have to pass to the
Constructor of core or manual when
creating them so as you saw with the
example there are a large number of
configuration variables that we have to
pass to the Constructor every time that
we create a car or car manual object and
this is pretty ugly and also a large
number of the configuration options are
not needed most of the time for example
most cars are not convertibles and
therefore we have to just keep on
providing false um for all of our cars
or car manuals for many of the fields so
one way way of not having to specify all
of the configuration options when
creating a new object will be to create
sub classes for each type of car or
manual so here we can see we have our
original base car class and we have some
sub classes to create specific types of
cars and we also have the same thing uh
for the manuals here to create the
manuals for these cars so the problem
with this solution is that our library
of subclasses is likely to grow very
large as more configuration variables
are added to car and also if we for
example change the wheel size on a
sports car then we'd also have to change
the sports car manual class to uh
correspond to this changed uh wheel
diameter so the above Solutions here are
ugly and difficult to maintain so let's
now introduce the Builder pattern to
solve these issues so here is the uml
solution for the Builder pattern
so we can see here we have a builder
interface with a few methods so we have
here set C type set seats and we'll also
have the rest of the methods such as set
engine set dashboard Etc so these
methods kind of represent the steps
involved in building either a car or a
manual and then we have the sort of
concrete Builder classes so we have one
for building a car and one for building
a manual and you can see here in this
car builder that we store a a reference
or a field of a car object and then we
use these methods so such as set car
type we'll set the car type on this car
object and then we have set seats and
we'll also Implement all the other
methods that we need from this Builder
interface and then finally at the end we
have a get core method which will just
return this builtup car and then we have
the same thing for manuals where we have
a manual field so in this manual Builder
we're going to be building up a manual
using these methods that we have
implemented from this Builder interface
and then again finally we have a sort of
geta method where we can return this
builtup manual object so a car and its
manual are two different objects that
don't share a common interface however
they can be constructed using the same
steps as each specific component in a
car needs to be documented by its manual
so by abstracting the object creation
logic into Builder class
we can create cares and manuals by only
specifying the steps required to build
that specific core or manual so let's
take a look at how we can implement this
in code so let's now solve this problem
using the Builder pan so first of all
let's create or recreate our car
class so you can see beforeand that we
The Way We Were creating cars is that we
pass all of these values into the
Constructor
uh now what I'm going to do is I'm just
going to provide um I'm going to change
these from fields to C Properties just
for
convenience and you don't have to do
this we could still have car uh exactly
the same as we had it beforehand uh as
we had it in here uh we could pass all
of the fields into the Constructor
however I'm now just going to build up a
car by um setting the uh properties with
gets and sets
so uh let's now uh import these
components and then let's create our
manual in the same way so we're going to
move away from passing the values into
the Constructor and we're just going to
use properties to set the fields uh
within the Builder classes that we are
going to create so let's create a manual
class
and I'm just going to copy and paste
this in because it's pretty much what we
had before but we're now using C
Properties rather than setting the
values in the Constructor as we did
before so we just need to import these
components so we're going to use this
namespace okay so now we can build uh
our Builder interface that will contain
all of the possible steps for building a
car or a a manual so let's call this I
Builder and in here we're going to have
some methods so first of all I'm going
to provide a reset
method and this is going to essentially
in our concrete Builders it's going to
reset the kind of object field so for
example if we have a car builder the car
builder has a field of car and it builds
up that car with the methods that we
provide in here and the reset method is
basically just going to kind of reset
that core object to a brand new object
so this is just a common method that is
often included in the Builder pattern
and it'll become more clear when we
actually use this method so next up I am
going to create a set core type method
and this is going to return an i Builder
and the reason we're actually returning
uh a builder from this set core type is
because it will allow us to chain
methods onto each other when we are
creating a core so again hang on this
will become much more clear if you don't
understand when we actually use this
solution so I'm just going to copy and
paste in the other methods now to save
some time because it's pretty obvious
what we are doing so we're just adding
in the other methods so as you can see
we have um all the steps that we need
here to build a car or manual so we can
set the engine we can set the wheels we
can set the dashboard and pass a
dashboard in ETC so now let's build the
concrete Builders so first of all let's
create the car
builder and this is going to implement
the I Builder or the Builder interface
so let's Implement that
interface
so let's see so the core build if you
remember needs to store a field of a car
of type car so let's go ahead and do
that and then in the Constructor we can
uh call the reset method okay so
essentially whenever we create a new car
builder object we are going to set this
car equal to a new blank core object a
fresh core object so to do that we can
first of
all create a Constructor and we don't
need to pass anything to this
Constructor we just want to call the
reset method and inside of the reset
method I'm actually going to move this
up so it's a little bit more
clear we're just going to set the car
field equal to a new
car okay
so next up let's Implement some of these
methods so first of all let's implement
the set call type method so where is
that okay so in here we pass the car
type that we want to set the car to and
so the way we can do this is we can just
call car do
type equals type okay and then remember
we need to return an i builder at the
end of this method so we can just return
this Builder because this is a car
builder which is a a builder because
we're implementing the Builder interface
and again this will become clear why
we're doing this shortly so what I'm
going to do is I'm just going to copy
and paste the rest of these methods in
because it's again very obvious and a
little bit laborious so let me just copy
and paste those
in so I'm just going to copy and paste
the whole class in actually
okay so that should be everything we
need so let's just go through what we've
done here so again we have a car object
which we are setting to a blank object
upon the Builder's construction we then
have our methods which are the steps
involved in building a car so here we
can set the car type we can set the
dashboard and we pass the dashboard in
uh we can set an engine the GPS
navigator the seats is convertible set
wheels and then finally we have our get
core method which will return the car at
the end and we can see here that we
store the car in a variable and then we
call reset so that we are essentially
resetting our car as a new car object
once we get the car and this isn't um
necessary in the Builder pattern but
it's just something that's commonly done
um so it's it's kind of like an optional
step whether you reset the object when
you get the uh object or whether you
just leave it as it is okay and then
maybe call reset from the client so
that's just um an implementation option
I
guess so next up let's build the core
manual Builder class
and we need to implement the Builder
interface okay so what I'm going to do
again is I'm just going to copy and
paste these methods in to save us some
time
so it's going to be exactly the same as
what we have in our car builder because
it's implementing the Builder interface
the only difference is that we are
storing reference to a manual rather
than a car that's the only difference
that we have here and we just need to
import uh or use this namespace for the
components folder okay so that's
everything that we need to do here and
as you can see it's exactly the same as
what we have before so if I just go
through one method we have the set core
type method here where we pass the core
type and then we call manual. type which
is a property on this manual object we
set the type and return this core manual
Builder so that we can chain the methods
onto each other whenever we are building
a car manual and again that will become
clear when we use these classes and
finally we have our get manual method
which sets um store the manual in a new
variable calls reset to reset the manual
field to a new manual so a new blank uh
Manu uh manual and then we return the
manual okay so that's everything that we
need to do here so let's take a look now
how we would use this class in the
client so I'm actually just going to
Let's comment this
out and let's go down here and first
let's let's create a car
builder okay so then we need to import
this okay so next up let's actually uh
build a car using the car builder so we
can say core Builder do set core type
and then we can set the core type to
core type do Sports so we're going to
build a sports core again exactly the
same as we did beforeand
we can then set the number of
seats let's see set
seats H do we not have a set seats
method
here H maybe we're missing a
method okay so it looks like we didn't
actually include our set
seats uh method in here so let's add
that in
and we're going to set it
to
and okay so we pass in an integer for
the number of seats and then we actually
need to add this method into
our car and car manual Builders so let's
just come down here and we'll say public
I
Builder set seats and then we'll say int
seats and we'll set the seats and
return the Builder Okay so let's see
what have we done wrong here Caril
already defined set seats with the same
Okay so we've actually provided this
method
already ah okay so we didn't have it in
the Builder interface but we did have it
in the in the Builder itself the
concrete
Builders okay so we we just needed to
add it here okay so let's go back into
our
our client and we can now set seats
hopefully there we go so this is going
to have two
seats and we can set the engine to a new
engine and let's see set
dashboard to a new
dashboard see what do we need to provide
here uh
has rev counter we'll say
true and let's see so we've got a
dashboard set the
wheels and it will have four wheels
actually we need to provide the wheels
components and then we set the dynamite
in inches to
20 and uh that I believe is everything
we need to do to create a sports car so
now we should be able to get the sports
car
so we can say car builder
dog uh
car and let's see we then should be able
to set the fuel on the car so let's car
do Set uh maybe it's Fuel and then we'll
say
100 okay so let's run that to make sure
that we've got no issues
here and I believe believe that's all
okay so let's now create our manual
builder for a sports
car so here you can see we're using the
car manual Builder and then we are
calling all of the same methods as we
did
previously
and then we get the sports uh the sports
car manual by calling manual builder.
getet manual and then we are logging the
printed manual ual to the screen so
let's see if that logs
correctly okay so that all looks good so
this is a nicer solution as we now only
need to specify the core or manual
properties that we need for example we
don't need to specify if the car is
convertible like we did beforehand when
we were uh when we had had to provide
all of the data in the Constructor of a
car or a manual when we're creating
those objects and also notice how we can
conveniently chain methods onto each
other because we are actually returning
the current object from each method call
so if we check set seats you can see in
this interface we have to return the
Builder which means that we can keep on
chaining these methods onto each other
and we could also return void from each
of these methods and then call each
method line by line so for example car
builder. set car type and then we'd say
car builder. set seats but it's just
nice and convenient to be able to chain
these methods onto each other so the
problem with this solution here is that
we still have to specify a large number
of fields when creating cars and manuals
and also because car builder and car
manual Builder both implement the same I
Builder or Builder interface we can now
use polymorphism to create cars and
manuals as producing a manual for a
specific type of car for example a
sports car requires the exact same steps
so for example if a car has a GPS then
it also needs to be documented in the
manual so we can Implement uh this using
a director class which I will show you
next so you can see here we still have
the exact same Builder pan that we had
beforehand we can see we have the
Builder interface and then our concrete
Builders which imp lement the Builder
interface but we've now added this
director class to our pattern and you
can see this director class has two
methods here one for constructing sports
cars and one for constructing SUVs and
you can see that we pass the Builder
that we want to use into each of these
methods so for example if we wanted to
construct a sports car this method would
contain all of the steps in this
sequence for producing a sports car and
if we wanted to produce a sports car uh
you know a sports car car then we would
pass the car builder if we wanted to
produce a sports car manual then we
would pass the manual Builder and
because the steps for producing a sports
car and a sports car manual are the same
we can just pass the Builder and it will
construct um the sports car or sports
car manual correctly and we could also
do the same for different types of cars
different uh such as SUV or um any other
type of car um so we can see here that
we have this uh dependency relationship
between the director and the Builder and
that's because we're passing the Builder
into as an argument into each of these
methods
so the director class is actually
optional in the Builder pattern as the
build steps can be specified in the
client and that's what we did here
but it's often useful for putting common
construction routines into this director
class so that they can be easily reused
throughout your application so let's now
take a look at the ganga for
representation of the Builder pattern so
you can see here we have our direct uh
director class which has methods that
contain commonly used routines and we
can pass the build that we want to use
into each of these methods we then have
our Builder interface with a reset
method
for uh resetting the uh object that we
are constructing to a new object we will
and then we have our build steps we then
have our concrete Builders which
implement the Builder interface and each
concrete builder needs some sort of
method for getting the result of the uh
Builder after the product has been
built so note that above we are passing
a build that to each method in the
director class but it's also fine to
store a reference to a builder and then
use methods for changing the builder at
runtime like so so here you can see we
have a different way of implementing the
director class so rather than passing
the Builder to each of the methods we
can actually pass the Builder to the
director's Constructor when we are
creating the director object and then we
provide a method for changing the
Builder um so for for example let's say
we first of all want to build a sports
car we pass the car builder then we call
construct sports car and then if we
wanted to produce a sports car manual we
can call the change Builder pass the
manual Builder and then construct the
sports car again and this time it will
produce a sports car manual so as you
can see both ways of implementing the
director class are totally fine um I
just wanted to show you a couple of
different ways of of uh implementing
this class so let's now build the
director class in code so let's create a
new class called
director and we're going to give this
class two methods one for constructing a
sports car and one for constructing an
SUV so first of all let's create the
construct sport call
method and we need to pass the Builder
to the
method and then we can call the Builder
uh well we can call all of the build
steps on this Builder so what I'm going
to do is I'm just going to copy them
from our client code that we have here
and this needs to be
Builder and we also need to import our
components
okay so I think everything should be
okay
here okay I'm just going to move this in
a little
bit okay so that should be okay so let's
now
also create a method for constructing an
SUV and again we pass the
Builder and then I'm just going to copy
and paste this code in that I have
here so this time I've actually uh
called the steps on the or the methods
on the Builder line by line so just so
you can see the difference between
chaining the methods and sort of calling
them one by one so just two different
ways to do it there personally I like
chaining it's a little bit more
convenient and we don't have to keep on
writing the Builder over and over again
but both ways of doing things are
totally fine so note that we don't
actually return the product for so the
product being either call or a manual
from this director uh well from each
method within this director and that's
because each product is returned from
its respective concrete
Builder and this is because call and
manual objects don't share a common
interface so let's now go into the
client and see how we can use the
director class so I think what I'm going
to do is I'm going to comment out all of
this code here
and let's first of all create our core
Builder and then let's create our
director
class and then let's create a sports car
so we can call director do construct
sports car and then we want to build a
car so we pass the car builder
and then we can say sports
car is going to be equal to our car
builder car builder. Gat sports car
actually sorry it should just be G car
okay so then we have our sports car and
let's just check here so that should be
sports
car then we can call Sports car. Fuel
and put it equal to 100 okay so that's
pretty nice
um so let's also now construct an
SUV so we can say director do
construct uh
SUV and we can pass the car
builder and then we can get our
SUV uh let's say SUV car equals car
builder dog
car okay and then we can set the fuel to
let's see fuel equals
40 okay so let's now produce some
manuals for these cars so we can first
of all create a manual
Builder and this should be car manual
Builder and then we can call director.
construct sports car so just the same as
we did here um but instead of passing
the core Builder we now pass the manual
Builder so that we build a sports car
manual
so then we can actually get our sports
car manual so we can say sports car
manual is equal to manual builder. getet
manual okay and then we can print the
manual to the
console okay so you can see that um vs
code is giving us no errors here because
here we are returning a a car object
which has a fuel property and here we
are returning a manual object which has
this print method for printing out the
manual okay and we can also do the same
for an SUV so I'm just going to copy
this in to save a little bit of time
here so you can see that we are also
constructing a manual for SUV so let's
run this program to make sure everything
is working
correctly so let's see what we have here
so we have first of all of all we have
our sports car manual so we can see the
car type Sports the seats the diameter
of the wheels Etc which is all correct
and then we have our SUV with five seats
a slightly smaller diameter of wheel etc
etc so this is all working as it should
be so here we have used the Builder
pattern to reuse the same object
construction code or build steps to
build different kinds of products so
cars and their corresponding
manuals um so other creational patterns
focus on producing objects that share a
common interface but the Builder pattern
differs in that it can construct objects
of different types providing that they
share a common set of build steps
congratulations you have now completed
this design patterns course and you now
have all the tools to create readable
maintainable flexible and top quality
software so I hope you found this course
useful and I thank you for watching if
you did find this course useful please
do like comment and subscribe to my
channel it will help a lot thank you
very much and I will see you in the next
one